<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Natural allegiance, and a national protection, truly stated, being a full answer to Dr. G. Burnett's vindication of himself</title>
            <author>Northleigh, John, 1657-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18568</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12112283</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12112283</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54220</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54220)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 818:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Natural allegiance, and a national protection, truly stated, being a full answer to Dr. G. Burnett's vindication of himself</title>
                  <author>Northleigh, John, 1657-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 107 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Northleigh. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715. --  Dr. Burnet's vindication of himself from ... a pamphlet, entituled, Parliamentum pacificum.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:54220:1"/>
            <p>Allowed to be Publiſh'd,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54220:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Natural Allegiance, AND A <hi>National Protection,</hi> TRULY STATED: Being a Full ANSWER TO <hi>Dr. G. Burnett's</hi> Vindication of Himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and ſold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:54220:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54220:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Remarks on the Second Part of the Reflections of Dr. <hi>Burnett,</hi> on the <hi>Parliamentum Pacificum;</hi> being an Anſwer to the Vindication of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>AN Apology <hi>for ſo many Months ſilence</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> pag. 1.</note> (which is ſometime Interpreted, a Conſent to the Accuſation) would be now as requiſite and neceſſary for our ſelves; and be better excus'd by the long, deliberate, and ſerious Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that has been had of what is here <hi>Writ;</hi> than that of our Authors, <hi>from his uneaſineſs</hi> in <hi>Writing:</hi> Himſelf, and his Admirers, I am ſure, think he Writes very <hi>eaſily,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> and the many Calumnies he has caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and the Prince that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in it, in multiply'd <hi>Reflexions,</hi> in repeated Libels, aggravated with Arrogance and Applauſe, only from their being the moſt Audacious Crimes, and the ſevereſt Satyrs on the Crown: This does certainly declare, that they do not come from him with ſuch a deal of <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54220:3"/>
but are more probably, the ſudden Productions of his eaſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ile: The haſty Tranſports of an <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter to my Lord <hi>Middleton.</hi>
                  </note> avow'd and Animated Paſſion, or the gratifying the Popular Fame he has here acquir'd, partly for his Meritorious Learning, and more by his ſtudy'd Affectation.</p>
               <p>Had this Paper but the half of that <hi>Modeſty</hi> it <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends</hi> to, it could not with ſo bold a <note n="*" place="margin">Paragraph.</note> Front term thoſe pieces that have been publiſh'd in defence of a Prince and Government he defames, but ſo <hi>many Libels,</hi> only becauſe they have <hi>toſt about his Name;</hi> I cannot ſee how they can be call'd ſo, unleſs this Celebrated <hi>Name,</hi> to which ſo <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>any</hi> are aſcrib'd, like ſome Cabaliſtick Spell can make a Metamorphoſis, and blot the very Papers that offer but to mention it: Thoſe are look'd upon as the greateſt <hi>Libellers</hi> by the <hi>Civil</hi> Law, that invade and abuſe the <hi>Civil</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Atrox inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria eſtimatur, Si Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp;c. Inſt. 4. Tit. 4. Si ad ſeditionem: Vis Publica eſt. <hi>Vid.</hi> Pacii Analyſ. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> power and the Magiſtrate, which if it tend to Sedition, is there call'd, a <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid</hi> Tuld. hic. c. 5. per l. Un. C. Si quis Imp. maledixerit. Quiſque vel cogitavit, <hi>&amp;c. Vid. C.</hi> 9. &amp; 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Invaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had our Author, that Chriſtian Temper, which he tells us he propoſes for a Pattern and Imitation<hi>:</hi> I humbly conceive, he ought to have been ſo <hi>humble</hi> too, though ſuch an <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> and kept the <hi>Prieſt</hi> from being ſo <hi>high,</hi> as to revile the <hi>Prince,</hi> that Divine Pattern our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, is indeed the greateſt Example of ſuch a ſort of deference and ſubmiſſion; <hi>that</hi> would make him ſuch a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> as to pay it to his <hi>King,</hi> though <hi>Pagan;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> though Dr. <hi>B.</hi> were of the Opinion of Mr. <hi>I.</hi> in the point of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Julian</hi>'s Popery and Paganiſm.</note> 
                  <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54220:3"/>
In the next place, his Apology for the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is but little better than what he makes for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Ibid.</hi> pag.</note> for the Protection they have given him, might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Miſrepreſentation he has given them, and their Lordſhips we thought would have had too much Honor for Crowned Heads and their own Allies, than to protect a perſon that Libel'd and abus'd <hi>both;</hi> at leaſt, if they allowed him the priviledge of a Naturaliz'd Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <note place="margin">K. of <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>England</hi> in his Reflect.</note> they could not indulge him a Liberty that muſt be deny'd any Native; that is, to offer to defame the Proceedings of thoſe Princes, whom not only their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Character ſhould preſerve Inviolate, but whom, themſelves were oblig'd by ſolemn Leagues and Articles of Alliance, (Sanctions that in ſuch National Concerns are more ſeriouſly to be obſerv'd) to maintain in their wonted Honor and Eſteem; and to deliver up ſuch <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi> Fugitives; or puniſh at home ſuch <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders as do endeavour to diminiſh it: The <hi>little</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection that was paſt upon their Government, one <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Parliam. Pacif.</note> would have thought might have been paſt by too, by one that reflects upon <hi>ours</hi> ſo <hi>much;</hi> and Stateſmen will allow, even <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf, that the Aggreſſors in ſuch Violations, authorize the returning of the like: If our Author can prove, that the <hi>States</hi> have been <hi>worſe uſed,</hi> than he has uſed the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> or, that the leaſt Animadverſion was ever made <hi>on their</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Conſtitution; till His Majeſty had ſuffer'd ſo much from his moſt Injurious Pen, we will then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to that puniſhment, which the Penſioner, and the Doctor, doe deſire, and be heartily ſorry for that <hi>Atrocious Calumny,</hi> which they ſay, has ſo much deſerv'd it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54220:4"/>
I have therefore in all the preceding Treatiſe omitted ſuch Expreſſions as might give an offence, tho' they could be ſaid with <hi>truth:</hi> I have given <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of the Proceedings of thoſe Catholick Princes, whoſe Memory and Religion, Perſons and Perſwaſions, our Author thinks it his Duty barely by Reflection to defame, and if <hi>Holland</hi> has happened to be concern'd in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> as well as <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> who can help it? the Doctor might as well commence a Quarrel with <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Geography; (for Hiſtorians in a Trade can never agree) as to make us anſwerable to <hi>States,</hi> for an <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>times,</hi> and only for relating the Tranſactions of thoſe very <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that made ſuch a wonderful alteration in this Weſtern part of the World; and even an account <hi>extorted</hi> from us, by thoſe Rhetorical Reflexions, (which from a greater Zeal againſt Popery, than any regard to ſincerity and truth) I am confident he has made: Neither does this Juſtification of our ſelves like our Author's Defamation of Princes, conſiſt for the moſt part only in Flouriſh and Tropology; and I might add, in a little Malice, mingl'd with his <hi>much</hi> Learning and <hi>Wit;</hi> but the Writing of an <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is to be defended by the <hi>Law,</hi> and tho' it were <hi>of all Nations,</hi> is no <hi>Libel;</hi> by the very <hi>Jus Gentium:</hi> The <hi>World</hi> could never be ſaid to ſit in Judgment upon Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> and the ſhort Hiſtory we have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the <hi>Forreign Reformations,</hi> make us no more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to <hi>States abroad,</hi> than our Author is for the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>our</hi> own <hi>at home;</hi> though I muſt confeſs, I do not expect any <hi>thanks</hi> from <hi>Holland,</hi> becauſe he had his from the <hi>Houſe;</hi> ſo that if thoſe Paſſages, by which he ſo laboriouſly would ſtir up the reſentment of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. a part, pag. p.</note> States, have only a reſpect to Matter of Fact, to Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54220:4"/>
and that of Reformation, the Laws of <hi>Nations</hi> make it no <hi>Injury,</hi> and I hope, none of our Neighbours will teach us any better <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Injurious Defamation, conſiſts properly in <hi>Reflections,</hi> which of late is our Authors excellency, his common Topick, Title, &amp; <hi>Peculiar;</hi> and what <hi>Reflects</hi> upon the fame of <hi>private</hi> Perſons, or <hi>Publick</hi> Societies, in feigned Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, either of <note n="*" place="margin">Si quis ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famiam, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Libellum, aut Hiſtoriam, &amp;c Inſtitut. Lib. 4. Tit. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Satyr</hi> and <hi>Lampoon,</hi> both by Civilians, and <hi>other</hi> Lawyers, is truly call'd <hi>Libel.</hi> And therefore, I ſuppoſe it was, and for that <hi>only</hi> reaſon, that the Learned <note n="†" place="margin">Delen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum, <hi>aut Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam,</hi> quod nec Theop. agno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſclt, nechabent libri Emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiores. <hi>Vid.</hi> Jul. Pacii Analyſ. Scholiis Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani. <hi>Id.</hi>
                  </note> Annotator on the Inſtitutions of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> in his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Injuries,</hi> would have the word <hi>Hiſtory</hi> expung'd from being appropriated as a part of <hi>Legal Defamation;</hi> which (ſays he) an Eminent Author does not allow of; neither (indeed) do the more Corrected Books mention it: I have thought good to Apologize with this too, that our Adverſary may not retort again, that the <hi>States are worſe us'd than himſelf,</hi> whom we would ſtill reſpect, while <hi>Our</hi> Allies, tho' this Author ſhould perſiſt to Libel <hi>Theirs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Protection,</hi> (ſince he is pleaſed farther to inſiſt on) we ſhall a little further debate, with all deference, to thoſe that give it him; and though he offers to <hi>Anſwer all</hi> that relates to himſelf, I hope to ſhew that there is a great deal yet left <hi>unanſwered;</hi> and for that <hi>Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> he paſſes upon <hi>our</hi> Stile, for <hi>foul Language,</hi> we have in return, given a more <hi>civil</hi> Character of <hi>his.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> Pag</note> If a Man were to judge of the Manners of a Clime, from the Deportment of the Inhabitants, I know from whence we might expect <hi>foul Language:</hi> I confeſs, I cannot contend with our celebrated Author for that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Fame that attends his way of Writing; which leaſt it ſhould be confin'd, and too narrow for his unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54220:5"/>
Merit, himſelf has taken care in <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. on <hi>Varill,</hi> and Reflect. on Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. at <hi>Oxon.</hi> and ſeveral of his late works.</note> ſome Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Expreſſions to diyulge, but though not ſo <hi>copious;</hi> ſtill I do not find my ſelf ſo <hi>ſtreightned</hi> in ſuch a <hi>ſcanty</hi> Stile, as to be forc'd to have recourſe to <hi>Scurrility;</hi> the late Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> for his <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foon, Scara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouch, Harle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin. Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canſyr. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boon. And Quaere, If <hi>foul Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage?</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fiocco</hi>'s ſake, might have been better treated, ſince his own Name in the <hi>end</hi> of it, to which the <hi>Enquirer</hi> never read, manifeſted it to be his; and the ſame <hi>Licenſe</hi> that has ſo alarm'd him, authoriz'd it in the <hi>Front,</hi> yet ſome ſober Perſons preſume to think that <hi>Enquiry</hi> a very <hi>Scurrilous</hi> one; which with Reverence to the See, and reſpect to the Sacred Function, had been better forborn, neither was there in all our Papers, to the laſt, the leaſt Reflexion upon our Adverſary, that tranſcends the boldneſs he has taken with his Majeſty and the Crown; neither was I conſcious of any particular Opprobrious Term, for which he could reproach me, unleſs it were a Crime to call him an <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Parliam. Pacificum. pag. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> that puts upon us for <hi>Hiſtory</hi> the Defamation of the laſt <note n="*" place="margin">Thoſe that ſpeak to the diſhonour of the King's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and Progenitors, are by the Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> within the Acts of Leaſing making, and to be puniſht with loſs of Life. <hi>Jac.</hi> 6. p. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 134.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings</hi> Memory, and that of all his † <hi>Predeceſſors;</hi> the meeting with ſuch Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges might a little provoke an undecent expreſſion; for which even ſedate thought, or the mightieſt modeſty will hardly permit me now to beg his Pardon.</p>
               <p>Having thus paſt through the <hi>Praeliminarys</hi> of his moſt <hi>peculiar Vindication,</hi> with as much Compliment as may be, we are come now to conſider the <hi>Contents</hi> of it: And firſt, what further Defence our Adverſary has made, and how far he has anſwer'd to his ſecond Citation that was ſent him out of <hi>Scotland?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54220:5"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>WHatever are the Complaints of Dr. <hi>B.</hi> againſt his <hi>Countrymen,</hi> I cannot ſee how he could have wiſh'd for a better <hi>Country</hi> to have put himſelf upon his Tryal in; a <hi>Nation</hi> that governs it ſelf by the Laws of <hi>all Nations,</hi> as well as the <hi>Municipal</hi> ones of their <hi>Land,</hi> and even <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Lib. cui Tit. Reg, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtat. A Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript from the <hi>Roman</hi> Law. <hi>Vid.</hi> Duck. de Authorite. l. 2. c. 10.</note> thoſe fram'd, and compos'd according to the wiſe Inſtitutions of the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> as juſt a Legiſlator as <hi>Solon</hi> himſelf, whom our Author in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts on <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. p. 3. <hi>Id.</hi> pag. 1.</note> for his Naturalization: Thoſe <hi>Caluminators,</hi> (to give our Author a right underſtanding of the word) thoſe <hi>falſe Accuſers,</hi> whom he would have accordingly <hi>puniſht,</hi> have <hi>there</hi> but little encouragement for <hi>Perjury:</hi> I wiſh we had <hi>here</hi> but as much ſeverity to intimidate Villains from ſuch Practiſes: It is <hi>there</hi> that theſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminators,</hi> by a ſort of Arithmetical Juſtice, (as the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Stierius Praecept. Ethic. c. 14.</note> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts term it,) or by that Eternal Law of Equity, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> are expos'd, upon detection of <hi>their Perjury</hi> and <hi>falſehood,</hi> to the very <hi>Puniſhments</hi> that the Party muſt have ſuffer'd, had their Evidence been <hi>true,</hi> and this not only by the <note n="*" place="margin">Ex Lege Remnia ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatur ut <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, fronti Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminatoris inuratur, vel idem ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium de quo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reus periclitabatur. <hi>Vid.</hi> D. 4. 16. 1. c. 9. 46. 6. Zouch. Elem. pars 7. Sect. 10.</note> Civil Inſtitutions, which with them take place where their own is defective, but by their very * <hi>Parliamentary,</hi> as well as the <hi>Imperial</hi> Sanctions, and particularly, by that of King <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Jac. 6. p. 11. c. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>James</hi> 6, which comes home to our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54220:6"/>
Caſe, He that <hi>Calumniates</hi> any Perſon of <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and the Party be <hi>acquitted,</hi> incurs the ſame Crime and Puniſhment that the preſumed Guilty muſt have undergone, had he made good his Proof; a Criminal has but little reaſon to fear a <hi>falſe</hi> Evidence, where ſuch <hi>fearful</hi> Conſequences do attend it; and our Author has as little Juſtice to demand their being <hi>pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht accordingly;</hi> ſince the proceeding upon a <hi>ſecond</hi> Citation, does not prove, that he was acquitted upon the <hi>firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had there been but the ſame Proviſion by our <hi>own</hi> Laws, againſt the <hi>falſhood</hi> of <hi>Accuſation,</hi> which our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is ſo <hi>afraid</hi> of, I am <hi>afraid</hi> it would have ſav'd ſome of that <hi>Society,</hi> which his Pen ſo Perſecutes, from Periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo miſerably by the <hi>Breath</hi> of ſome Miſcreants, that might more boldly <hi>ſtop</hi> another Mans, when there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left to <hi>choak</hi> them but their own Lyes and Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and who, perhaps, were the ſooner brought to a ſhameful <hi>death,</hi> when their Accuſers were never in any danger of their <hi>Lives:</hi> I could never meet with any Objection againſt this moſt equitably proceeding, but only that it might be a diſcouragement to ſuch as might otherwiſe detect any Treaſon or Conſpiracy; but ſince the Accuſer has the ſame ſecurity for his Indemnity, or Life, againſt him that will venture <hi>falſly</hi> to accuſe him of Forgery, that the perſon had whom himſelf, perhaps, <hi>juſtly</hi> accus'd, I cannot conceive, but he may proceed as <hi>boldly</hi> in confidence of the <hi>truth</hi> of his Depoſitions, as if there were no ſuch Identity of Puniſhment an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next.</p>
               <p>But our Author again, has leſs reaſon to condemn his Accuſers there; ſince the Subjects of that Nation are more particularly bound by an <note n="*" place="margin">Car. 2. p. 2. Seſſ. 2. cap. 2.</note> Act of Parliament, that declares it their Duty, to depoſe upon Oath, when
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54220:6"/>
call'd by Authority, their knowledge of any Crimes againſt the Publick Peace, and more eſpecially, for correſponding with <hi>Fugitives</hi> and <hi>Rebels;</hi> ſo that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their <hi>Teſtimony</hi> true, which being upon Oath, we muſt have as much Charity for, as our Author's <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> they could not avoid, both by their <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> to <hi>teſtifie</hi> all that they knew; and till they are made appear by Reciprocal Oaths, and as ſtrong Circumſtantial Evidence, to have given in falſe Informations, they cannot be <hi>lookt</hi> upon as <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> much leſs, <hi>puniſht accordingly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I cannot but take notice of another conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience his Law does allow him, though the manner of his Proceſs is ſo injuriouſly reproacht. I am ſure it is a defect in our own, and which nothing but the tender regard to the Soveraign's ſafety can excuſe; and that is, the having the Evidence for his <hi>Innocency,</hi> ſworn <hi>againſt</hi> the King, as well as that which <hi>for</hi> the King is brought to prove the <hi>Guilt;</hi> for Judges, or Jurors, (whatever is pretended) muſt be more influenc'd by that regard that is given an <hi>Oath,</hi> than to the bare Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of an Evidence that lies under no ſuch Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not poſitively take upon me to define whither by the Practiſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> it is abſolutely neceſſary to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion page 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpecifie</hi> the <hi>particular</hi> Laws, upon which a <hi>Citation</hi> is founded, our Inditements we all know; ſet forth only in <hi>general,</hi> and <hi>contrary to the Statute in that caſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:</hi> And I cannot imagine, but that the ſame Learn'd Advocate, who in his <hi>firſt</hi> Citation did ſo largely ſet forth in ſo many ſeveral Statutes, the Crime that affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him; could (had it been abſolutely neceſſary) have omitted it in the <hi>ſecond,</hi> ſince they need not have been ſo far to ſeek for any <hi>Special</hi> Law, when ſome of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54220:7"/>
the former that were cited, would have ſerv'd alſo for this, for the <hi>declining of the Soveraign Authority,</hi> and <hi>putting Treaſonable Limitations</hi> upon <hi>the Prerogative of the Crown,</hi> or <hi>upon their due Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> is by an Act <hi>Car.</hi> 2. made <hi>Rebellious</hi> and <hi>Treaſonable,</hi> and <note place="margin">2 Act. 1 Seſſ. of <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note> if ſo, an entire <hi>transferring this Allegiance,</hi> and renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all Obedience, will amount to more than a meer <hi>limitation</hi> of it, and the <hi>declining</hi> of his Authority, is by an expreſs Act of King <hi>James</hi> made <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> which by the ſame <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> it muſt <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">8 Parl. <hi>Jam.</hi> 6.</note> as well as <hi>legally,</hi> be concluded, he does <hi>decline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is obſervable, that in this ſecond <hi>Citation,</hi> to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 2.</note> which he excepts, he is proceeded againſt by the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate,</hi> upon the <hi>Common Law, Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Municipal Laws</hi> of the Kingdom, which <hi>general</hi> Form is not us'd in the <hi>firſt,</hi> and ſo may ſuperſede any <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Law,</hi> being ſet forth; as it is uſual among us when Men are Indited at <hi>Common Law,</hi> there is no need of any <hi>Statutes</hi> being expreſt; but ſince our Author deſires <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Law</hi> ſo much, I think there are many other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of that Kingdom, that I am afraid, will affect him too much, if this Expedient of <hi>transferring Allegiance</hi> be but once found to fail him, and it is <hi>thoſe</hi> that <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> 1.3.4. Act of Parl. K. <hi>James</hi> 6. <hi>Vid.</hi> 10. Act 10. Parl. <hi>Jac.</hi> 6. all expreſt in the firſt Citation.</note> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that no perſon preſume to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> or <hi>Write,</hi> on <hi>purpoſe</hi> to <hi>Reproach, or ſlander the King, or the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or <hi>miſconſtrue their Proceeding, whereby diſlike may be mov'd between the Prince and his Subjects, and this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pain of Death:</hi> I am afraid many of our Authors <hi>works</hi> will riſe up in <hi>Judgment</hi> againſt him, where this is to be made the matter of his <hi>Proceſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, it is plain by this <hi>Citation,</hi> that even in <hi>Scotland,</hi> there may be <hi>Treaſon</hi> by the <hi>Common Law,</hi> and where by <hi>that</hi> it is ſet forth, I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54220:7"/>
there needs no more <hi>particular Law</hi> to be <hi>ſpecify'd</hi> than with us in <hi>England,</hi> for by common Law, even <hi>there,</hi> can be meant no more than what our <hi>Coke</hi> makes it <hi>here, common <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage;</hi> and if I miſtake not, a <note n="*" place="margin">Duck. de Authoritat. Lib. 2. c. 10.</note> Learned Lawyer of ours from the Conceſſion of their own <note n="*" place="margin">Jo. Leſlae. de moribus Scotor. Lib. 1. C. Leg. Scot. Conſtat autem jus Scotorum ſicut &amp; Anglicanum, ex <hi>conſuetudinibus</hi> Scotiae.</note> Countryman whom he cites, is of the ſame Opinion; ſo that this Authors Argument, will in ſhort, reſolve it ſelf into this Interrogatory, whither of that which <hi>Common Law</hi> makes <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> a <hi>Special Law</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to make a Man <hi>guilty?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>THe Dr. in the next place obſerves, <hi>That no Similitude</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> pag 2.</note> 
                  <hi>of hands is in Criminal Matters</hi> admitted of for proof in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that ſuch Evidence is but a <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral preſumption.</hi> I confeſs, we have here in <hi>England,</hi> the Lady <hi>Carr</hi>'s Caſe againſt it, and Mr. <hi>Sidney</hi>'s, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Tryal.</note> ſeveral others, in which hers has of late been always overrul'd; but whither they have any Preſident for it in that Country cannot aſſert, but if it be of any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that which a Learned <note n="*" place="margin">Duck de Authoritate. Lib. 2. C. 10. Conſtat ex rerum Scoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum Scripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, in Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis, ad leges ſuas, &amp; poſt eas, ad jus Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile teneri.</note> Author obſerves upon the Authority of the Civil Law in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that in their Adminiſtrations of Juſtice, they are ty'd to their <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipal</hi> Laws, and where that is deficient, to be guided by the Civil, then any one Criminated for High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there muſt expect but little favour, eſpecially in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54220:8"/>
matter of <hi>Evidence,</hi> and <hi>Preſumption;</hi> for though the <hi>Imperial Decrees</hi> are as tender of the Life of a Man, and have as great a regard to innocency, as any Laws we have in <hi>England;</hi> though they ſay too, <hi>That it is much better to ſpare the Guilty,</hi> than Condemn an <hi>Innocent;</hi> though they generally give it in the <note n="*" place="margin">Satius eſt Impunitum relinqui facinus nocentis, quam innocentem damnari. Sic inquit Ulpianus, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Trajanus Severo reſcripſit. <hi>D.</hi> 48. 19. 1. 5. Zouchei. Quaeſt. &amp;c. 9.8. <hi>Vid.</hi> etiam, ejuſdem Element. par. 7. Sect. 9. <hi>Vid.</hi> Legem Juliam. Inſt. Tit. 18. Lib. 4.</note> Negative, That <hi>no one can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd upon Preſumption;</hi> yet in their Crime of <hi>Leſae Majeſtatis,</hi> they all ſay 'tis <hi>excepted;</hi> and their very Sons and Servants upon a <hi>bare preſumption</hi> of their Guilt ſhall be Condemn'd; and this <hi>Leſe Majeſty</hi> is a term not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Alien</hi> to the Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but what I am ſure <hi>there</hi> is in frequent uſe, ſo that it may be poſſible, even according to the <hi>grounds</hi> and practiſe of the <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Laws, to find a Man guilty, upon ſmaller proof, than our Author may imagine; and if he conſider the many Acts of Parliament that were paſt, even in the Reign of their firſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prince, King <hi>Jam.</hi> 6. (and I hope hee'll condemn nothing of the Reformation) <hi>that</hi> declar'd, and ordein'd what was <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> even in the <hi>largeſt</hi> extent, and all which are (I think) ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently <hi>ſpecify'd</hi> in his <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> 1.3.4. Act 8 p. K. <hi>J.</hi> 6. 10 Act 10 p. of K. <hi>Jam.</hi> 6. 144 Act 12. p. of K. <hi>J.</hi> 6. with ſeveral of ſome other Kings.</note> 
                  <hi>firſt Citation:</hi> Then I humbly conceive, hee'll have leſs reaſon to complain of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of his Proſecutors, and the Injuſtice that is done him.</p>
               <p>I have this further to offer, it is expreſly provided <hi>there</hi> by <note n="*" place="margin">10 Act 10 p. K. <hi>Jam.</hi> 6. and 2 Act 2 Seſſ. 1 p. K. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2.</note> two ſeveral Statutes and * Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that to <hi>Write</hi> in <hi>Reproach</hi> of the <hi>Kings Perſon</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">The Earl of <hi>Orkney</hi> was Condemn'd for <hi>ſigning</hi> a Treaſonable Paper of <hi>Combination</hi> with his Neighbours at home. <hi>Treaſon</hi> by <hi>Ja.</hi> 6. p. 10. Dr. <hi>B. ſigns</hi> his League and Alliance with Forreign States. <hi>Treaſon.</hi> 1 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. p. 1. Seſſ. 1. c. 5.</note> or by <hi>Writing,</hi> to put <hi>Limitations</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:54220:8"/>
upon their due <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judg'd <hi>Rebellious</hi> and <hi>Treaſonable;</hi> if this by <hi>their</hi> Law is <hi>Statuted,</hi> or <hi>ordained</hi> (as certainly it is,) this <hi>Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude</hi> of <hi>hands</hi> muſt be allow'd a <hi>Proof,</hi> or the Intention of the Law muſt be utterly <hi>Inſignificant,</hi> for it is Morally impoſſible in ſuch caſes to give in any other Evidence; it cannot be imagin'd that thoſe who make ſuch <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> Conſtruction with their <hi>Pen,</hi> will permit any perſons to be preſent at the <hi>Penning</hi> it; <note n="*" place="margin">Praeſumptiones graviſſimae ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ad paenam capitalem, ſi deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſit occultum &amp; difficilis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis: Julii Clari ſententia. <hi>Vid.</hi> Zouch. Quaeſt. praedict.</note> and then all <hi>Laws</hi> will allow <hi>that</hi> for Evidence, where <hi>greater</hi> cannot be had, or expected: And I cannot ſee, why a <hi>ſerious</hi> Letter, <hi>ſolemnly</hi> ſent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his <hi>own</hi> hand, to a <hi>Publick</hi> Miniſter of State, about an affair which all the World knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>ſolely</hi> concern'd in, ſhould not be accounted one of the <note n="*" place="margin">Violenta praeſumptio eſt ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na probatio, ſays my Lord <hi>Coke.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſtrongeſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions,</hi> and which our Law too calls the <hi>fulleſt Proof,</hi> and this violent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; in his caſe, I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, was founded, as it ought to be, that is, <note n="†" place="margin">Violenta praeſumptio infertur ex juſtis cauſis &amp; Circumſtantiis. <hi>Vid.</hi> Zouch. El. de Evidentià cauſae. c. 9.</note> on <hi>juſt Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> for certainly, there was <hi>juſt Cauſe</hi> that gave them to believe, that <hi>our Author</hi> was the <hi>Author</hi> too of that Letter to my Lord <hi>M.</hi> and many Circumſtances that ſeconded the belief of it, ſince he <hi>there</hi> repreſents the very <hi>Cauſes</hi> of his Writing exactly conſonant with the Proceedings here, and ſince it might well be imagin'd from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its Compoſition, that none but Dr. <hi>B.</hi> was the Writer, ſome things are ſo <hi>notorious</hi> that they need no proof even by <note n="*" place="margin">Notorium probatione non indiget. Baldus ad C. 9. 2, 7.</note> Law, and our Author would have been loath that any ſhould have doubted it, from the <hi>peculiar</hi> excellency of the Style, and the reputation that himſelf ſays, his Works have gotten in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54220:9"/>
It may not perhaps, be here too impertinently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that the ſending theſe Papers to a <hi>Publick Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of State, made them from his hands ſo many <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Eandem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem obtinet, ſides Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum quam depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, maxime ſi ſint publica. C. 4. 21. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> when communicated by the <hi>Secretary</hi> to the <hi>Advocate</hi> of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and I know ſome Laws that ſay ſuch Evidence is as good as a Depoſition upon Oath; and as our <hi>Common Law</hi> calls it in other Caſes; ſo this may be here call'd a <hi>Civil Record.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, the ſole Queſtion will be, whither in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Letter; and Papers, that were ſent to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, there was any thing contain'd that <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid</hi> Letters, and Papers.</note> 
                  <hi>reproacht</hi> his <hi>Majeſty's Government,</hi> or <hi>limited our Authors Allegiance;</hi> when it threaten'd a <hi>ſlanderous Recital</hi> of the <hi>affairs</hi> of the Kingdom, and declares his <hi>Allegiance actually tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated;</hi> which the two recited Acts do <hi>literally</hi> declare <hi>rebellious</hi> and <hi>treaſonable?</hi> or whither they are only ſome <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. pag. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ill choſen Expreſſions?</hi> for which we have only the <hi>Preſumption</hi> of Dr. <hi>B.</hi> (and if <hi>general Preſumptions,</hi> as he ſays, are no proof, much leſs can a particular one be ſo) eſpecially if you conſider him, as a Party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, and that no Law will allow him to <note n="*" place="margin">Nemo Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus teſtis in re ſuà intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur. <hi>Vid. D.</hi> 9. 22. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>teſtifie for himſelf:</hi> This <hi>ill choſen Expreſſions</hi> is ſuch a modeſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation of what his <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Law calls <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> that I cannot help my ſelf to ſuch another Inſtance of <hi>civil Excuſation</hi> and Apology, than that which another Celebrated Author, now an Inhabitant about the ſame Provinces, and probable, correſpondent with <hi>ours,</hi> (though we do not hear of his <hi>Allegiance tranſlated)</hi> made for a Doctor too; but one whoſe <hi>Works have leſs reputation in the World,</hi> who was pleaſed (upon the conſideration of the contrariety and Contradiction of <hi>Oat</hi>'s in his Evidence and Diſcourſe) to grant that <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Mr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt</hi>'s Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. p. 41.</note> he was a little <hi>Apert and Incurious in his Converſation;</hi> an <hi>Apertneſs &amp; Incuriouſneſs</hi> which the <hi>Statute</hi> has been ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54220:9"/>
bold as to puniſh for <hi>Perjury;</hi> ſuch a faculty has the fame of an Author, or the <hi>quaintneſs</hi> of his Style, to give a <hi>Politer</hi> turn, to thoſe <hi>unpoliſht</hi> terms, and <hi>rigorous</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>reaſon</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing that falls in our way, is ſomewhat <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion p. 3.</note> of the ſame <hi>nature,</hi> and which he would ſo <hi>ſoftly</hi> inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, that the being declar'd in the <hi>Writ</hi> a <hi>Rebel,</hi> does only intimate, that he is <hi>Contumacious:</hi> Had our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Caſe indeed, been only the refuſing to pay his Debts; and the <hi>King</hi> only been his Creditor, I confeſs, I could then have had <hi>milder</hi> thoughts of the <hi>Rebellion</hi> that is imply'd in his <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Horning;</hi> but ſince it is ſo far from <hi>that,</hi> that the Doctor declares, he <hi>owes</hi> his Majeſty nothing, not ſo much as <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ut ſupra.</note> their Laws declare <hi>Treaſonable;</hi> I am afraid there is ſomewhat more that affects him, than barely but a <hi>formal Contumacy and Contempt:</hi> It is the <hi>matter in the Citation,</hi> with ſubmiſſion to his more <hi>peculiar</hi> opinion, that empower'd his Majeſty to demand his puniſhment or ſurrender from the States, and not his being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd Rebellious at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or the <hi>Peire</hi> of <hi>Leith;</hi> it is not for the <hi>Rebellion</hi> in the <hi>Writ,</hi> but for the <hi>Treaſon</hi> that the <hi>Citation</hi> contains; which I humbly conceive, by his Non-Appearance for the ſpace of a whole Year, he has Convicted himſelf of<hi>:</hi> I fancy he had made a better Parallel of this <hi>Scotch Horning,</hi> had he compared it to our <hi>Engliſh Outlary,</hi> and inſtead of putting it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Chancery,</hi> had brought it into the <hi>King's Bench; Writs</hi> of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> we all know, are <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>form</hi> with us in that Court; but no one will agree <hi>here,</hi> that when a Man is <hi>Out-law'd</hi> for <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> he is no more a Criminal, than he that runs into <hi>Holland</hi> for fear of an <hi>Execution,</hi> by the <hi>Bayliff,</hi> and not of the <hi>Hangmans.</hi> It was the misfortune of a <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Reſt. on <hi>Varill</hi> p. 55. Sir <hi>Tho. Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong</hi>'s-Caſe.</note> friend of <hi>His</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54220:10"/>
whom he would make to be <hi>murder'd,</hi> to meet with the <hi>difference,</hi> and yet <hi>Juſtice</hi> too; whatever have been our Authors <hi>injurious</hi> and multiply'd Reproaches, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in every Print, upon the <hi>juſt</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Much leſs Reflection on a <hi>Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> was ad judg'd a <hi>Libel</hi> with us, in 18 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.3<hi>d.</hi> Inſt. c. 76. and by the Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> for defaming a <hi>Judge</hi> falſly to be puniſht at the King's Will. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. p. 7. c. 104.</note> Judge than then Preſided: The peculiar reſentment of our Author, and that perhaps, for ſome juſt diſappointment, has ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occaſion'd thoſe <hi>unjuſt</hi> and repeated Reflections on that Loyal Peer, that as his Honour and <hi>Integrity</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede all Vindication, ſo this Authors defect of <hi>Sincerity,</hi> is betray'd beyond defence, and the reſult only this, that his Lordſhip may be ſaid to lie <hi>much above</hi> thoſe <hi>lew'd</hi> Calumnies, and but <hi>little Under.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>BUt for all what our Author does ſo <hi>plauſibly</hi> ſuggeſt, doubtleſs, there muſt be a great deal of <hi>difference</hi> between a <hi>Criminal Proceſs,</hi> and a <hi>Civil Action;</hi> which if there be, then the Iſſue that is directed thereupon, though in <hi>formality</hi> it may be the ſame, muſt in <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance</hi> greatly <hi>differ,</hi> and the Conſequences that attend it, as I have toucht upon before, are of as <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> a nature; which when the term is elaps'd, the one will <hi>only</hi> affect your <hi>Eſtate,</hi> the other both <hi>that</hi> and your <hi>life;</hi> for though in <hi>both</hi> Caſes you loſe the <hi>benefit</hi> of the <hi>Laws;</hi> yet when the Crime is <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> you may more properly be ſaid to <hi>forfeit</hi> the <hi>Protection</hi> of the <hi>King;</hi> but for that, our Author had provided for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54220:10"/>
before hand, and from his own <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Six pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, pag. 39.</note> Maxims anticipated that forfeiture, by the <hi>renouncing</hi> his <hi>Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But further, I am well inform'd, that though the Dr. would make all his Proceſs to be but a <hi>formal</hi> Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that there is no cognizance taken of the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> it contains, that even in <hi>Scotland,</hi> a <hi>Citation,</hi> and <hi>Inditement,</hi> are indeed the <hi>ſame</hi> in ſignification, tho' they are two different words. The <hi>firſt form</hi> they are forc'd too, when the Criminal abſents himſelf; and the <hi>ſecond</hi> (though the ſame in <hi>ſubſtance)</hi> in the <hi>form</hi> of a Libel, he's to plead to when in Cuſtody: Had the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> expreſt nothing of the Crime, then I confeſs, our Authors Arguments had been better apply'd, but I cannot conceive now, without the greateſt Abſurdity, how a <hi>Citation</hi> can be iſſued out, <hi>expreſſing</hi> the <hi>Matter,</hi> and yet no <hi>Cogniſance</hi> to be taken of the <hi>matter</hi> it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes; if a <hi>Citation</hi> be a <hi>Judicial</hi> Act, then ſure what is therein contain'd, is as <hi>judicially</hi> taken <hi>notice</hi> of<hi>:</hi> But though this <hi>ſecond Citation</hi> ſeem ſo ſurpriſing to him, he cannot be ſuch an only Stranger to his own <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as to <hi>know none of theſe things,</hi> unleſs the <hi>flying into Egypt</hi> has made him an utter Alien to the <hi>Common-wealth of his Iſrael;</hi> nothing is more common in his Country, then that the King's Advocate when he diſcovers ſome new Matter of Fact againſt the Criminal, to iſſue out a <hi>ſecond Citation</hi> for his Appearance? This is call'd an <hi>Additional Libel,</hi> in which there is no need to aſſert, and ſet forth any <hi>Special Law,</hi> becauſe it uſually refers to the <hi>firſt,</hi> in which the <hi>Laws</hi> are <hi>ſpecify'd;</hi> and ſince our Author ends this <hi>Citation</hi> with <hi>an &amp;c.</hi> we are left in the dark as to the latter <hi>end</hi> of it; and perhaps, he may <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 2.</note> as unſincerely have left out ſome of the <hi>beginning;</hi> but though he had been more ingenious; and this <hi>laſt Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> had no reference to the <hi>former,</hi> ſome that <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Law of</hi> Scotland <hi>too,</hi> do not agree with our <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54220:11"/>
Authors <hi>Informers,</hi> but are of Opinion, that where the King's Advocate does accuſe a Perſon of a Crime, that is in its <hi>own</hi> nature <hi>Treaſonable;</hi> and what implys the Pains and Puniſhment that is due to <hi>Treaſon,</hi> that then it is time enough for the Advocate to ſet forth the <hi>Special Law</hi> for it at the Bar, and the Judges will as certainly find the Libel, or <hi>Inditement, Relevant,</hi> which is like our Grand Juries in <hi>England,</hi> finding of the <hi>Bill,</hi> and this practiſe (if I miſtake not) of naming no <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> Act or Statute in High Treaſon, is as uſual with us here, it runs through all the <hi>forms</hi> of our late Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and Inditements, which only mention <hi>againſt the Statute, in that, or the like Caſe provided,</hi> and leave it to the <hi>Attorney,</hi> which is but another ſort of <hi>Advocate,</hi> or the <hi>Judges,</hi> to declare what <hi>Statutes</hi> they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon; but becauſe <hi>general Aſſertions</hi> may be no proof with ſome that will diſpute any, tho' the thing has been ſo often objected by the Priſoners, in all our late Proceedings, and always ſo anſwered by the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, yet our Author will particularly find Mr. <hi>Sidney,</hi> a a Man of no eaſie temper to be ſatisfy'd, to be forc'd <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> his Tryal, pag. 7.</note> to ſubmit to it; and this <hi>Judge,</hi> that our Author has ſo <hi>injuriouſly</hi> defam'd, to tell him as much <hi>Iuſtice, That when he came to his Tryal, the Attorney might tell him what Statute he went upon, and give in Evidence any Act of Parliament that comprehends Treaſon;</hi> and as the <hi>Scots</hi> did of <hi>old</hi> Symboliſe with us, from the Vicinity of the Countrys, ſo ſomewhat in their <note n="*" place="margin">Their Books of Reg. Majeſt. much after the manner of our Glanv. de legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. So alſo their Parliam. like ours. <hi>Vid.</hi> Duck. de authoritate. lib. 2. cap. 10.</note> Laws and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as well as with the more <hi>antient</hi> of the <hi>Romans;</hi> ſo I were almoſt aſſur'd that even in this <hi>modern</hi> practiſe which our Author diſputes, we might have ſomewhat of agreement too, which I would not venture to affirm poſitively, till I were by a Perſon of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity,</hi> and of the <hi>ſame</hi> Country further aſſur'd; neither is it improper to this place to obſerve, that though our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54220:11"/>
Author inſiſts on the inſignificancy of the Term <hi>Rebel</hi> in the <hi>Letters,</hi> or <hi>Writ</hi> that declare him ſo, for his Non-Appearance; that it may <hi>there</hi> have a double ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both with relation to his Contempt to the Laws, and the Crime that he is charg'd with againſt the Prince, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nivocal</hi> ſound of the ſame <hi>word,</hi> will never do him any Service in his <hi>Aequivocal</hi> Interpretation of the <hi>Senſe;</hi> and the little kindneſs that he has to the <hi>Society</hi> one would think ſhould make him as afraid of an <hi>Aequivocation,</hi> or a <hi>Mental Reſerve,</hi> as of the very <hi>Maſs</hi> it ſelf; yet ſuch is his reaſoning, notwithſtanding that Antipathy he has againſt the Name; for this is plain, that the Demands that were made of him, from the States, is founded upon the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Subſtance,</hi> and not the <hi>formality</hi> of the Word; for where it is <hi>formally</hi> us'd in <hi>Civil Actions,</hi> there <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Relaxation</hi> are granted to the Partys if they ſatisfie the Debt within a Year and a Day, and ſo acquitted, which ſhews that the Term <hi>Rebel,</hi> is there meerly us'd for <hi>form;</hi> but where in the other caſe he is a preſum'd <hi>Rebel,</hi> both by <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Form;</hi> there, though he be <hi>Relaxt</hi> of his <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Horning,</hi> by his <hi>Appearance,</hi> yet he might be <hi>hang'd</hi> for a <hi>Rebel</hi> after he <hi>appears;</hi> and I ſuppoſe, that may be one of the Reaſons, why the Reflecter ſtands out in <hi>Contempt,</hi> but then he ought to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd further of what follows in his Country uſually in ſuch caſes, which makes a greater difference; that after the <hi>publication</hi> of theſe <hi>Letters,</hi> and a year elaps'd; in his caſe, the King's Advocate can iſſue out another ſort of Writ, call'd Letters of <hi>Intercommuning,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all the Subjects of that Kingdom are forbid to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe</hi> with him, to ſupply him with any Neceſſaries, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Penalties of <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> and this to extend, not only to ſuch of the King's Subjects as reſide at <hi>home,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54220:12"/>
but to any that are Inhabitants with him in <hi>Holland,</hi> or if he had <hi>tranſlated</hi> himſelf and his <hi>Allegiance</hi> with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to <hi>Japan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that from this it will appear, that even by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> a Man (againſt whom the <hi>Writt</hi> of <hi>Horn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is directed, importing <hi>High Treaſon)</hi> is a <hi>Rebel</hi> of an <hi>higher</hi> nature, till he come and take his Tryal, and that before the <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Intercommuning</hi> are iſſued out; &amp; though Terms in Treatiſes are to be taken in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acceptation (as our Author tells us) not as in Courts of Juſtice, yet <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 2. c. 16. Sect. 84.</note> 
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> will <hi>tell him</hi> too, that there is alſo a great Liberty to be allow'd to conjecture in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monimous Expreſſions, and Amphibologys, and that Terms of Art, ſuch as <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and <hi>Parracide,</hi> and we may add, <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Fugitives</hi> muſt be all explain'd by Men moſt <hi>skill'd in the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe there can be no fairer way of dealing with your Adverſary, but by conſuting him even from his own Conceſſions, (for Arguments that are Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically oppoſite, do but in a more Eloquent manner, give one another the Lye) wee'll ſuppoſe with him for once, that theſe Letters that denounce him a <hi>Rebel,</hi> mean nothing, but that he is a <hi>little Contumacious,</hi> that they are meerly but ſo many <hi>Writs of Rebellion,</hi> which here that Honourable Perſon he ſo reviles, does many times iſſue out of Chancery; wee'll ſuppoſe our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>retir'd</hi> into <hi>Holland,</hi> only for ſome <hi>diſorder in his affairs,</hi> or for a little imaginary Debt; yet even in <hi>thoſe</hi> very <hi>Civil Actions,</hi> the Laws of Nations allow ſuch a Latitude, that <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Requeſt</hi> may be made to the <hi>Forreign State,</hi> and if they are deny'd, thoſe of <hi>Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Rolls A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment, fol 530. a Caſe to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> may be granted; and if <hi>Private Subjects</hi> have ſuch Remedys, it will be hard to deny a <hi>Prince</hi> to demand ſatisfaction for a <hi>publick</hi> offender; and the <hi>Dilemna</hi> was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54220:12"/>
never ſo much as doubted; but that a <hi>Tryal</hi> was to be order'd by the <hi>Forreign State,</hi> or the <hi>Criminal</hi> ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to the <hi>offended</hi> one; I gave our Author ſeveral Preſidents for theſe Proceedings; but he that pretends to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Parliam. Pacif.</note> 
                  <hi>anſwer all,</hi> left them <hi>all unanſwer'd;</hi> I ſhall preſent him more of the ſame nature, when we come to a more proper place, but it is ſomewhat more appoſite here, ſince he would make his <hi>Treaſon</hi> but a ſort of <hi>Civil A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and himſelf no more than the <hi>King's Debtor;</hi> to tell him, that in <hi>Edward</hi> the Second's time, ſome Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>Florence</hi> having receiv'd the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Rents, run away with the Money to <hi>Rome;</hi> the King ſends his <hi>Requeſt</hi> to the Pope, demands the Goods to be ſecur'd and their Perſon ſeiz'd, and neither of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd. The like was done to one that fled into <hi>Lorrain</hi> with 500 <hi>l.</hi> of the King's Money; the Duke upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſeizes the Perſon, and ſecures his Goods where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were found, till he had ſatisfy'd to the full, ſo that I hope from hence may be concluded, that even a <hi>Man that does not</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. pag. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>pay his Debts,</hi> or <hi>retires into</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, only <hi>for a diſorder in his Affairs, may give our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment a right to demand him:</hi> For if it be granted in the Caſe of a <hi>Forreigner,</hi> it will be good in a <hi>Native's, a fortiori.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſumm up all the Subſtance of this Point, It ſeems very ſtrange, that the Proceedings of the <hi>Juſtice</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhould <hi>be</hi> ſo Arraign'd, <hi>where</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> are ſo favourable to <hi>Offenders,</hi> as to make the very <hi>Judges</hi> the greater <hi>Criminals,</hi> if they ſhould offer to do the leaſt <hi>wrong,</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> and liable to the moſt <note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 1. p. 2. 6. 45. Jac. 5. p. 7.104.</note> rigorous Puniſhment; <hi>where</hi> the Witneſſes are in ſuch danger for their given <hi>falſe</hi> Evidence, that they expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Puniſhment of thoſe they accuſe, if they can be ever convicted of the <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>falſhood,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54220:13"/>
that whither it be <hi>Pecuniary, Corporal,</hi> or <hi>Capital;</hi> and <hi>where</hi> by <hi>particular</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 6.11. p. c. 49.</note> Act, <hi>Calumniators</hi> in <hi>High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> are (if the <hi>accuſed</hi> Party be acquitted) <hi>guilty</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> Crime, expos'd to the <hi>ſame</hi> Puniſhment. And it will be no eaſie matter, when they are expos'd to ſuch terrible Conſequences for the <hi>Perjury,</hi> to procure <hi>Knights</hi> of the <hi>Poſt,</hi> though it were to ſerve even an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of State; <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid</hi> Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. p. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>to faſten pretended Crimes (as our</hi> Author has it) <hi>on thoſe they have a mind to deſtroy:</hi> There is a <hi>Society</hi> our Author has a mind to <hi>deſtroy;</hi> and I think ſome of the Members, not long ſince, were as <hi>miſerably deſtroy'd,</hi> for want of this Severity with us, againſt ſuch Profligate <hi>Evidence</hi> as accus'd them: The Dr. knows this to be <hi>true,</hi> and is ſo far for <hi>verifying</hi> it, that he would have his <note n="*" place="margin">1. Note<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cond Citation does not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate the firſt, much leſs prove the Witneſſes forſworn, and he confeſſes, that the Matter agrees with the former, <hi>Id.</hi> p. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Accuſers accordingly puniſht,</hi> even before they are Convicted of any <hi>falſhood,</hi> and himſelf not ſo much as <hi>try'd,</hi> or <hi>acquitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I done all that <hi>Juſtice</hi> to a Nation, even in its <hi>Judicial</hi> proceedings, that they could expect from a <hi>Forreigner,</hi> from his <hi>little</hi> Learning, and <hi>leſs</hi> Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into their <hi>Laws,</hi> which he found, even upon that <hi>little</hi> he has made, both agreeable with the ancient <hi>Roman Equity,</hi> in many things Conſonant with our <hi>own,</hi> and in ſome caſes recited already, beyond <hi>ours;</hi> more equitably <hi>Juſt,</hi> ſo it will ſeem ſomewhat harder to be born, that this Nations <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſhould be ſo much <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign'd</hi> by him that is their own <hi>Criminal,</hi> but becauſe our Authors wonted Vanity, may not arrogate the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious Fame, of being the firſt Invader of the <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial</hi> Proceedings of his Country, he has only borrowed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54220:13"/>
from <note n="*" place="margin">Judices quantum in ſe eſt, lationes legum impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire, civium bona Judicum, arbitrio eſſe conceſſa: eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque eſſe perpetuam poteſtatem; Imperium plane Tyrannicum, Buch. lib 14 Rerum Scotic. ad Ann. 1532.</note> 
                  <hi>Buchanan,</hi> that went before him; who has told the World that their <hi>Judges</hi> were but ſo many <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters</hi> of <hi>Juſtice, that the Subjects property depends on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon their Arbitrary power,</hi> and that the <hi>Government</hi> is <hi>truly Tyrannical;</hi> &amp; ſuch a courteous Hiſtoriographer to his Country (as he may be well call'd, an <hi>Original;)</hi> ſo it was our Authors <hi>Peculiar</hi> to <hi>tranſcribe</hi> him, and could never have been <hi>Copy'd</hi> by a better Hiſtorian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>THe Memorial of the Marquis <hi>de Albeville,</hi> I cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit without ſomewhat of Vindication; though <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. pag. 3.</note> the Miſſive of Mr. <hi>Fagel,</hi> that was given him againſt my <hi>own</hi> Works, I more willingly paſs by; our Author when he not only reflects upon that Inſtrument, but ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicules it, tranſcends not only the bounds of a modeſt Writer, but parts with all deference to a Crown'd Head, as well as his <hi>Allegiance;</hi> the Character of an Envoy is the moſt immediate repreſentation of the King, and every Act of his, but another of the State; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Liberty our Author pretends to, their Lordſhips might have had more Honour than to ſuffer the <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> to be <hi>Burleſqu'd;</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Their Extract, out of their Regiſter, on the King's Memorial, An. 1664. Anſwer'd by Sir <hi>G. D.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54220:14"/>
but by them it may be better excus'd, ſince it has been ſo much their practiſe before, or I muſt ſuppoſe, as Dr. <hi>B.</hi> does in his Satyrs and Sarcaſms upon the King, <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> 6. pap.</note> that even this was done without their knowledge; and that though the Author has ſubſcrib'd his Name.</p>
               <p>The ſubſtance of the firſt <hi>Memorial</hi> (as himſelf has <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Abſtr. of the K. Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morial in Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat. p. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>abſtracted</hi> it among the Reflexions he has made upon me; I ſhall in ſhort reſolve into theſe three Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Whither our Author has defam'd the King and his Government, and repreſented him as a Perſecutor, and his own life in danger?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Whither by Law, any of the Kings Subjects could ſeiſe abroad on Criminals to our State, in what manner ſoever?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Whither the States ought to have puniſht our Author, and his Printer?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>As to the <hi>firſt,</hi> whither the <hi>King has been defam'd by him and the Government?</hi> If the Queſtion be taken in general terms, it might as well be doubted, whither we had any <hi>Government,</hi> or <hi>King?</hi> and after <hi>all</hi> thoſe ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Libels that have been publiſht; moſt of which, himſelf has own'd; and for the reſt no more Moral E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence can be deſir'd to aſcertain them to be his: It would be an affront upon Humane Reaſon to diſpute it. Has not the Juſtice of the Nation been arraign'd by him in all its Proceedings ſince his Majeſty's Reign? have not his <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers page 1. <hi>Id.</hi> p. 3.</note> Miniſters of State been made the moſt fearful Mercenaries? have not the Judges on the <hi>Bench</hi> been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by him in the Sayings of Mr. <hi>Sidney,</hi> as ſo many <hi>Blemiſhes to the Bar?</hi> Has not the <hi>Scarlet</hi> of thoſe <hi>Twelve men</hi> been made by him almoſt as Criminal, as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54220:14"/>
if it were only the <hi>colour</hi> of their <hi>guilt,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Badg</hi> of their <hi>office?</hi> Has he not charg'd them plainly with <hi>Corruptneſs,</hi> or <hi>Ignorance, Infamy,</hi> and a Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <note place="margin">Vid. id.</note> Contemptible <hi>Poverty;</hi> as if he had made uſe of his own Province and Sacred Function <hi>for the</hi> defaming of his Soveraign and Prince, and would have apply'd his Text of making his <hi>Judges of the Land out of the meaneſt of the People:</hi> Has he not threatned them with the Exaltation of <hi>Treſilian,</hi> and fated them to a further Promotion, that of being Hang'd? Has he not in the moſt opprobrious terms expoſed the Chiefeſt Miniſter in the State, pronounc'd his executing of Juſtice a <hi>Campagne;</hi> an <hi>Act of Hoſtility to all Law,</hi> his <note place="margin">Vid. id. p. 22. p. 33.</note> ſerving His Majeſty; an <hi>outragious Fury,</hi> and his Zeal for his <hi>Soveraign,</hi> but ſo many Brutal Exceſſes: Are not the King's Counſellors <note n="*" place="margin">Id.</note> curſt, for a few Creatures whom the <hi>Court</hi> has gained to betray the <hi>Kingdom?</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. id. p. 24.</note> I am ſure he has met with no ſuch <hi>foul Language</hi> in all our Animadverſions, tho' I may modeſtly ſay, it might have been better laid out upon him, than where he has beſtow'd it. Is there, in ſhort, any part of the Government that he has not traduc'd, or any of its Proceedings that are not moſt ſcandalouſly repreſented? If this can be called a <hi>defaming</hi> of the <hi>Government;</hi> or if in the worſt of Times the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was never ſo <hi>defam'd,</hi> then <hi>that Word</hi> in the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial,</hi> was not ſhuffl'd in <hi>with haſte,</hi> unleſ it were <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Vind.</hi> p. 4.</note> becauſe the multiply'd Reflections were ſo notoriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly plain, and there was no need to <hi>deliberate</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Government was Libell'd.</p>
               <p>Then for what Reſpects the <hi>Defamation</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> (whoſe Reputation, I ſuppoſe, might be ſufficiently wounded through the ſides of his Officers, and the Blemiſhes he has caſt upon the Adminiſtration of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54220:15"/>
Affairs) but our Author's Sublime would have been loſt in the Condeſcention, had it reſted there, and not reach'd at the Throne, and the Perſon of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; and repreſented him as a <hi>Deſpiſer of all Fame,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> p. 1.</note> and as an <hi>Heroick Practiſer</hi> upon ſome few <hi>fearful Mercenary Spirits.</hi> Not a Declaration (which His Majeſty makes his own Act by ſigning it,) but by him in the ſevereſt manner has been Satyris'd, and his Sacred Word in every one of them expos'd with ſcorn and deriſion.</p>
               <p>The term of <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> p. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> in the <hi>Toleration</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> is repreſented as a Roman Piece of <hi>Tyranny;</hi> and he might for once, with <hi>March.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Merc. Polit. Numb.</hi> 67. 79.</note> 
                  <hi>Needham,</hi> in his <hi>Mercury,</hi> made his King another <hi>Tarquin;</hi> or with Mr. <hi>Sid.</hi> in his <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. His Tryal.</note> Politicks ſome <hi>Caligula,</hi> as well as <hi>Legibus Solutus.</hi> But I muſt tell this outragious man, That this <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> is no ſuch <hi>new Term</hi> in the <hi>Scotch Law,</hi> and that there are particular <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>P. Car.</hi> 2.</note> Acts of Parliament for the declaring of the Prince, <hi>Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Abſolute:</hi> But this deſcant upon the Point muſt be carried to that height of Defamation upon His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, as if he had renounc'd Chriſtianity it ſelf, and no Oaths were able to oblige him; and his being to be <note n="‖" place="margin">Vid. id. p. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>obey'd</hi> without <hi>Reſerve,</hi> was only to render him a <hi>Turk,</hi> as well as a <hi>Tarquin:</hi> I confeſs, thoſe his Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations do carry it ſome <hi>ſizes beyond</hi> the Grand <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. p. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Seignior's,</hi> and are a pretty Eſſay of his toward the Deſcription of a <hi>Mahometan Government:</hi> But as he is pleas'd to obſerve in another place, Did the <hi>Obedience</hi> of the <note n="*" place="margin">P. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Bowſtring</hi> obtain with all ſort of Subjects, ſuch Authors might well be ordered and obliged to <hi>ſend in their Heads.</hi> How is the Perſon of his Prince trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in thoſe diſhonourable Reflections he has made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſitting ſome time ſince, as <hi>his</hi> Brother's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54220:15"/>
in <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. p. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotland;</hi> where if <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Treachery,</hi> and <hi>Deſign,</hi> be ſuch Charges as can blemiſh the Reputation of a Prince, <hi>Harriſon</hi> himſelf could never have <hi>blackened his Father more:</hi> But if we look back upon <hi>England</hi> agen, (for our Author thinks his Libels defective, if they do not villifie the King through all his Dominions, and they leave one of the Crowns untarniſh'd, or the leaſt Jewel of it without a Cloud. <note n="*" place="margin">Therefore <hi>Ireland</hi> is toucht upon too in ſome of his Papers.</note>) The <hi>Additional Exciſe</hi> (which thoſe that were more concerned in than this Author, never complained of) is by him made one of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Invaſions of Property; the Diſorder of Souldiers apply'd to the very Perſon of his Prince, and his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. The Execution of ſuch as deſert their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> p. 22.</note> but ſo many Murders, occaſion'd by the King and his ſtanding Army, <hi>in time of Peace,</hi> and an attempt upon the Property, (as he will repreſent it) of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in groſs;</hi> and all this <hi>rank Sedition</hi> aggravated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Satyrical Irony</hi> and <hi>affected Suppoſition</hi> of its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all done <hi>without His Majeſty's knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this, I hope, is ſufficient Proof that he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fam'd the Perſon of the King, as well as his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that the Envoy did not commit an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight <hi>in</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, p. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>his haſte,</hi> when he inſerted it. And theſe I think are ſuch rude Reflections, and ſevere Recrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the King and the Crown, that they are not to be defended from <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Seditioſi ſunt qui plebem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Rempb.</hi> &amp;c. C. 9. 30. Engendring Diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween K. and People, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing making, 10 <hi>Act.</hi> 10 <hi>P. Jam.</hi> 6. <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. p. 2. c. 43.</note> Sedition, and the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous attempts to diſturb the State, by any Pen, but that peſtilent one which makes them. The Service the Dr. does the Church of <hi>England</hi> by this prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous way of befriending it, I am afraid will hardly be acknowledg'd by Her, for ſuch a Favour, unleſs She mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes Her Intereſt, out of a Zeal to promote it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces thoſe loyal Principles <hi>to</hi> which ſo <hi>long</hi> She has
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54220:16"/>
ſo <hi>Juſtly</hi> pretended: And I am ſorry to ſee, that by ſome of its Members the <hi>Improvement</hi> of ill Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſhall in the ſame man be applauded, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have formerly, when he was not arrived to that <hi>pitch</hi> of <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> condemned, even in the <hi>ſame</hi> Perſon that has now amongſt many too much of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe. It is known, that our Author had once ſome of the Greateſt of its Pillars, that oppos'd his Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note n="‖" place="margin">P. 6.</note> and himſelf complains of it too: And I hope it was upon that <hi>good</hi> Principle, that they found his to be but <hi>bad.</hi> His <hi>Metropolitan</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> I am told; once was conſulted for his Character, when he firſt came out of his <hi>own</hi> Country, and he, I think, gave him none, that could recommend him much to <hi>ours;</hi> or the Church:</p>
               <p>So that when impartial People ſee thoſe that he has repreſented for his <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vindic. of himſelf. p. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Enemies,</hi> and perhaps who well might be ſo, when as I am inform'd he let them know, upon their old oppoſing of the Bill of <hi>Vnion</hi> of Diſſenters, that he hoped to ſee the time that the <hi>Eſtabliſht</hi> Church might be glad of <hi>one,</hi> of <hi>Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> for <hi>themſelves,</hi> when they ſee thoſe ſo celebrate him for a <hi>Friend,</hi> and this ſame Perſon that was at ſuch <hi>Enmity</hi> with them, ſo wonderfully chang'd and endear'd, it will certainly give ſome occaſion to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That ſincere Honeſty can never conſiſt in <hi>both</hi> the Extreams; that if our Author was once ſuch an <hi>ill man</hi> with them, he can never be <hi>meliorated</hi> now, only by being <hi>worſe;</hi> and that either the Dr. and the <hi>Church</hi> were both in the fault, for their falling out <hi>before,</hi> or very much to be blam'd <hi>now,</hi> for <hi>ſuch</hi> a contradictory <hi>Combination</hi> and <hi>Agreement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I know too, that many good men <hi>ſtill,</hi> of our Eſtabliſht Church, think D. <hi>B. ſtill</hi> to be the ſame
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54220:16"/>
man, and that his unſeaſonable Services might have been better ſpar'd, ſince it is ſo plain, that his Pleading for the <hi>Church,</hi> proceeds from the opportunity that he takes by <hi>it,</hi> to maintain his own Quarrel, and to libel the <hi>State,</hi> and that the <hi>defending</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> now with ſuch an <hi>unwonted affectation,</hi> is only done for the <hi>defaming</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> with the <hi>better Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the other part of the Interrogatory, whither the King has not been by him <hi>repreſented</hi> as a <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor,</hi> and to have <hi>deſigns upon his life;</hi> ſhall be made as apparent, and that it was <hi>well</hi> by the Envoy, put into the Memorial, and as <hi>ill</hi> by this Author, in his <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication excus'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then, he muſt admit the Charge of this unjuſt accuſation of the King, or what will, I know, be more grievous to a man of ſuch applauded Parts and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances at the Pen, His excellent ſtile, to be guilty of an incoherence and impertinency; for immediately after a long <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of his Suffering under a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> p. 49. 50.</note> Proceſs, and which we know is alwaies at the Suit of the King, after he has repreſented himſelf ſo ready to ſacrifice his Life, after ſome Deſcant on the Evidence that were to teſtifie at his Tryal; then moſt <hi>emphatically</hi> follows, <hi>That it is yet too early to ſet on a Perſecution for Religion; ſubſequent</hi> words muſt alwaies have a Relation to their <hi>Antecedent,</hi> and a celebrated Hiſtorian can never be ſaid to forget his Grammar; neither can it be thought that out of reſpect to His Majeſty, he would violate any Rules in <hi>Orthography,</hi> who in many places, to defame him, has made uſe of <note n="*" place="margin">The Liege Letter, an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Fiction. Reflection on Q. <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Varillas.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Abſurdity</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. pag. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Contradiction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The lame and ridiculous Excuſation that he forces out even in ſpight of Senſe, and oppoſition to Fact, will not ſerve the Turn. * <hi>Theſe Men</hi> are two words
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54220:17"/>
that will do him no more ſervice than the <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Firſt Part of Refl. <hi>pag.</hi> 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Still Seems,</hi> and thoſe I think I have made appear, were not ſuch <hi>ill choſen Expreſſions,</hi> but a dulneſs of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, that made them raiſe ſuch a Duſt. It is plain by <hi>theſe Men,</hi> can never be meant as he would make us believe, of his Informers; for in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Paragraph he clears all his Witneſſes, Evidences, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Pag. 20.</note> and Informers, by their own Declarations and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, from being able to ſay any thing that could affect him; and certainly <hi>theſe Men,</hi> that he was ſatisfy'd, had nothing to ſay againſt him, were not thought by him to be <hi>thoſe Men</hi> that <hi>intended to deſtroy Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will in this caſe make him a better Excuſe out of a <hi>charitable Conſtruction,</hi> than he has yet made for himſelf; I hope without that <hi>foul Language</hi> he lays to my Charge, I had convinced him in my former Animadverſions, how <hi>fouly</hi> he had fallen upon the King, and that may have made this laſt of his Papers a little more modeſt, and himſelf ſo far humbl'd, as to be pleas'd to give us a milder Interpretation of his Words, than ever was his Meaning in their firſt Compoſition and Original; for they being rang'd among the reſt of thoſe Papers that have ſo much of that unimitable boldneſs, in the blemiſhing of His Majeſties Perſon and Government, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere.</hi> Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this may not be called Evil Information of the King to his Leiges, which is Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing making by the Laws of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Jac. 5. p. 6. c. 83.</note> cannot be preſum'd to be more civilly meant: Our Author knows (if hee'll but pardon the Application of his Eccleſiaſtical Function to a Civil uſe) that it is the Practiſe of the men of his Profeſſion, to diſcover any dubious ſenſe of the Scriptures, or the Fathers, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving recourſe to Texts and Contexts, by conſidering the ſeveral Parts of the Works, how they cohaere; and from ſuch Collateral Relations to make their moſt reaſonable Conſtructions; if I may therefore deal with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54220:17"/>
the Dr. in his own way, I hope to make it very plain, That by <hi>Theſe Men</hi> might be well meant by him, the <hi>King,</hi> and His <hi>Miniſters</hi> that had a <hi>mind to perſecute</hi> and <hi>destroy him:</hi> If he can paint Him as a <hi>Terror</hi> to his People, with his fearful Mercenarys, becauſe poſſeſs'd with his own Religion, may not he think, he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and deſtroy them for the ſake of theirs; and that when our Author in his repeated Reflections, has ſo barbarouſly obſerv'd, that for Religion it ſelf, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, or <hi>Parliament. Pacific.</hi> 1 par. pag. 2. Six Papers pag. 2.</note> he muſt unavoidably do it; does he not apply the decry'd Perſecution in <hi>France,</hi> to the King of <hi>England,</hi> that Proclaims nothing but Indulgence; and that this <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 10. p. 14.</note> King, to countenance him, will copy after him; that his <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Power</hi> may declare us Hereticks, to be burnt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Reſerve;</hi> has he not forc't the King's own Words of <hi>Invincible Neceſſity,</hi> to extend to Tortures, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, and Death it ſelf, where neceſſities are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible? And if by <hi>theſe</hi> muſt be meant only Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to deſtroy you, how comes the Government it ſelf to be made Mahometan; and His Majeſty's <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 21.</note> Oath that he has made to be adminiſtred in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but an <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 14.</note> Obedience of the Bowſtring, an Order to ſend in their Heads and <hi>deſtroy</hi> themſelves? I am apt to think our Author has forgot himſelf, when he would palliate and excuſe a Reflection upon the King, or that he may be ſurpris'd at the repetition of his own Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:54220:18"/>
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>THe next Queſtion that comes to be Conſider'd, is, Whether by the King's Laws, every one of His Subjects was warranted to ſeiſe on ſuch Offenders, in <note place="margin">Vid. 1 pag.</note> what manner ſoever? if ſo, then the Dr's. Exceptions are more <hi>haſtily</hi> made than the Envoy's Memorial.</p>
               <p>The ſeiſing ſuch Offenders, I had given him ſeveral Preſidents of before; but our Author that pretends to <hi>Anſwer all</hi> that concerns himſelf, has indeed left it <hi>all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanſwer'd:</hi> By the Statute Laws of both Kingdoms (ſetting aſide the natural Leigeance that obliges them) the Subjects are bound to detect all ſuch as enter into <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> L. <hi>Coke</hi> Inſt. Vid.</note> any Treaſonable Conſpiracy againſt the King and Government, and cauſe their Perſons to be <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jac.</hi> 6. p. 14. C. 205.</note> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and that upon pain of being * puniſht as Principal Offenders; and this ſhall extend to all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> where-ever they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; and more particularly, by the Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Letters of <hi>Intercommuning</hi> extend to all their King's Subjects whatever Country they inhabit; neither will that Expedient of a <hi>tranſlated Allegiance</hi> excuſe them; neither can it be imagin'd from even our <hi>own</hi> Law, but that all Allegiance, and Obedience, is inſeparable even from thoſe Subjects that reſide in another Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and even in the Service of a foreign Prince, ſince we have an <note n="†" place="margin">3 <hi>Jac.</hi> c. 4.</note> Act that makes it Felony for any to go to any Neighbouring State, or another Prince's Territories, without taking an Oath of Obedience to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54220:18"/>
their own Prince; this my <note n="*" place="margin">Inſt. 3. c. 23.</note> Lord <hi>Coke</hi> extends to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocratical Governments, and Republicks, as well as Principalities; and that to thoſe that go thither, even without any deſign of entring into Forreign Service, barely for omiſſion of taking this Oath of Obedience, before they went out of the Kingdom; a Law though it has been look'd upon like a dead Letter, and ſo little executed, yet will ſerve to let us know, that this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Oath was requir'd; to prevent the pretence of ſuſpending your Allegiance by any forreign Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation, which though it may priviledge you in another State for the preſent, could never annull that Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Obedience, that by your Birth you ow'd, and by your own Act had ſworn to your Natural Lord; ſo that it ſuperſedes all doubt, but that by the <hi>King's Laws</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract of the Memorial.</note> all his born Subjects, wherever they reſide, are bound to obſerve thoſe Laws among themſelves, and if ſuch Offenders as our Author can be ſeiz'd by the King's Subjects at <hi>home;</hi> they are as much oblig'd and warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if they have Power and Opportunity, in <hi>what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſoever</hi> to put it in Execution <hi>abroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> do Juſtifie ſuch proceedings, it does almoſt ſuperſede any Neceſſity to defend it, by Preſidents, and Arguments, from Practiſe and Fact, but even for <hi>that,</hi> as we are not <hi>deficient;</hi> ſo we will not be wanting to produce them; though we had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd the <hi>World</hi> in it before, and one would think our <hi>Author</hi> too, ſince he has not offer'd to return to them the leaſt Reply.</p>
               <p>The Caſe of Dr. <hi>Story</hi> was ſo <hi>truly</hi> repreſented, Dr. <hi>B</hi>'s <note place="margin">13 Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1571.</note> too, and yet no otherwiſe than the <hi>truth</hi> of the Fact, and that as it is related by <hi>Fox,</hi> ſo <hi>truly parallel,</hi> that I cannot diſcover the leaſt <hi>diſparity,</hi> unleſs it be in this alone, that the one is a famous Doctor in <hi>Divinity,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54220:19"/>
the other was only as Celebrated a Doctor in the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> which ſince our Author would not take notice of, when he was <hi>anſwering all that Related to himſelf,</hi> we will repeat it here a little more at large. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> pag. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Story</hi> was Impriſon'd upon Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s coming to the Crown, only for having been zealous in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of his Religion, in the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> The Famous <hi>Fox</hi> gives no other reaſons for it, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents him (as you might expect) under the colour of <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Perſecution,</hi> though indeed he acted as a Lawyer, and an Advocate, and ſo could not be charg'd with thoſe Conſequences that attended his Vocation, no more than the King's Council in Criminal Cauſes can be ſaid to <hi>kill</hi> a Man whom the Law <hi>Condemns,</hi> or the Advocate in <hi>Scotland</hi> to Perſecute Dr. <hi>Burnett,</hi> becauſe it is he that Complains of him in the <hi>Citation:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Impriſon'd as he was, he makes his Eſcape, gets over into <hi>Flanders,</hi> is <hi>naturaliz'd,</hi> reſides at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> acts by ſpecial Commiſſion under the Governour; but being reported here, to have animated <hi>Spain</hi> to ſome Hoſtilities againſt <hi>England,</hi> as our Dr. does the <hi>Dutch</hi> to <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> 1 par. of Refl. p. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>reſentment</hi> of <hi>Injurys</hi> which ſignifies the ſame, this by the Laws of Queen <note n="*" place="margin">13 <hi>Eliz. Dyer</hi> 298.</note> 
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her ſelf, being adjudged <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and this having been Cardinal <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> 3 Inſt. c. 1. In Angliâ ſparſum eſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ut vix â Turcico, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pool</hi>'s Caſe, who was accus'd for encouraging the Emperour to invade his own Country, <hi>by writing of Books,</hi> that made the King almoſt as <hi>ill as the</hi> Turk; or as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor expreſſes it in his <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Six Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> upon our Kings <hi>Abſolute Power,</hi> by the * <hi>Bow-ſtrings of</hi> Turkey, and the <hi>Mahometan Government.</hi> Theſe things, (though acted beyond Seas, being in her Reign adjudged <hi>Treaſonable,</hi> as appear'd in the Caſe of <hi>Patrick O Cullen,</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Man, for a Treaſon at <hi>Bruſſels;</hi> (and our Author cannot with Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hill,</hi> 36 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </note> reflect upon any Reſolutions in her Reign, only
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54220:19"/>
cauſe they juſtifie againſt him the Proceedings of the preſent;) People then having theſe ſort of Judgments and Apprehenſions of Dr. <hi>Story</hi>'s Caſe in the Matters that our Dr. <hi>Burnett</hi> now diſputes in his own; they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd this Plot, that one Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> ſhould ſet Sail for <hi>Antwerp,</hi> being a Merchant, and by ſome <hi>means, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (ſays <hi>Fox)</hi> bring over this Doctor into <hi>England;</hi> and that is, as I humbly conceive, <hi>to ſeiſe on him there</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>in what manner ſoever; Parker</hi> repairs to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fox.</hi> Acts and Monuments, pag. 21 52. <hi>Lond.</hi> Edit. 1583.</note> (as our Author phraſes it) ſuborned ſome Perſons to lie ſo far for the matter, (though it cannot be believed that they had any diſpenſation for it,) as to ſignifie to him there was prohibited Books aboard in the Ship, into which, when they had Deluded the Doctor, they as ſoon ſet Sail with him for <hi>England,</hi> where by the way I cannot but obſerve, that this Celebrated Martyrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt calls him <hi>Traytor</hi> and <hi>Rebel,</hi> even <hi>before</hi> he was <hi>Try'd;</hi> but to his Tryal he was brought; and there as I formerly repreſented, pleaded <hi>his</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>Bs.</hi> firſt Letter to my Lord <hi>Mid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Allegiance tranſlated from her Majeſty, to the Soveraignty of the King of</hi> Spain, and <hi>that</hi> for ſeven <hi>years ago; that</hi> he was his <hi>Sworn Subject,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Baker</hi>'s Chron. p. 349. <hi>Dyer</hi> p. 298. 300.</note> and therefore (as he well deſerved) ſays this <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Martyrs;</hi> he was Condemn'd as a Traytor to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Queens</hi> Majeſty, and the <hi>Realm,</hi> (and as ſays another Author) becauſe all his Pleadings were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd <hi>per form</hi> of <hi>Nihil Dicit,</hi> the Judges reſolving (as I recited in the former Treatiſe) that <hi>no man can renounce the Country wherein he was born, or abjure his Prince at his own Pleaſure;</hi> and with this agrees expreſly the <hi>Civil</hi> Law, as hereafter ſhall be ſhown: The barborouſneſs of whoſe Execution, being cut up alive, and in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, after diſmembring, ſtriking the Executioner, muſt be more Condemn'd, than the Proceſs againſt him, and cannot be excus'd by ſuch an Author's outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54220:20"/>
Zeal, in terming him a <hi>Bloody</hi> Nimrod, <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and a <hi>Perſecuter;</hi> and to make the Parallel, between the two Doctors more plain, the <hi>Encouraging,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting</hi> an <hi>Invaſion</hi> of her Majeſty's Kingdom, was laid to <hi>Story</hi>'s charge too, and adjudg'd High Treaſon upon a Solemn Debate of the Judges. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>* Vid. Dyer,</hi> fol. 299.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot find that <hi>Spain,</hi> (though otherwiſe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently incens'd againſt the Queen for the Countenance and aſſiſtance ſhe gave to the Diſturbers of his State) <hi>ever</hi> made this ſeiſing of a <hi>Naturaliz'd Criminal,</hi> even in time of <hi>Peace,</hi> any Article for the Juſtifying of a <hi>War,</hi> or ſo much as complain'd againſt it as a Breach of the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Nations;</hi> and why? Becauſe it was never then diſputed, but by the <hi>Kings Laws,</hi> every one of his Subjects was warranted to <hi>ſurpriſe,</hi> or to <hi>ſeize on him there, in any manner whatſoever:</hi> Our <hi>Author</hi> muſt make himſelf more Ignorant in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> than he would make our <hi>Envoy</hi> in the <hi>French Tongue;</hi> if theſe ſort of Proceedings never occurr'd to him in his reading: but becauſe we are apt to <hi>forget</hi> ſuch Paſſages as may chance to diſpleaſe us in their application, I hope to make it appear, (without being reproacht for <hi>foul Language,</hi> or leſs reſpectful to that reverend Character he bears; then himſelf has been to that Honourable Perſon that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents his Majeſty,) that the Dr. has not <hi>taken the pains rightly to inform himſelf in this matter,</hi> and refreſh his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>* Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 3.</note> Memory with an Inſtance or two more.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Heath</hi>'s Chron. 62. part 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Corbet, Okey,</hi> and <hi>Barkſtead,</hi> ſome of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, upon the Reſtoration of the late King, and ſome that were excepted out of the Act of Oblivion for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men <hi>eminently</hi> concern'd in that Execrable Murder, were in the Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> at <hi>Delph</hi> and other places, ſeiz'd by Sir <hi>G. Downing</hi> the King's Miniſter, and the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Dutch</hi> themſelves, with the order
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54220:20"/>
of the <hi>States,</hi> and by the Marſhal of the Town.</p>
               <p>The ſeizing the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> and now Cardinal, in a free Town, tho' an Imperial City, in the ſervice of the <hi>French,</hi> was juſtified by theſe <hi>Dutch</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Their own <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Hiſtorian.</note> becauſe he being a <hi>natural born Subject</hi> of the Emperor's, he was found undermining of his Government.</p>
               <p>And that which is <hi>freſher</hi> in our Memories, and with which I had <hi>refreſh'd</hi> our Authors in the former Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, is the Caſe of Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> when he <hi>lay</hi> under the <hi>ſame</hi> Circumſtances, being <hi>Outlaw'd</hi> for <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> which in <hi>England</hi> is the ſame with the <hi>Scots</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Horning,</hi> and I think ſomewhat more than <hi>a Writ</hi> of <hi>Rebellion</hi> out of <hi>Chancery.</hi> This Gentleman, by the Procurement of His Majeſty's Envoy, then reſiding at <note place="margin">Anno 1683/4.</note> the <hi>Hague,</hi> and the help of his own Servants, with the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Town</hi> in which he was taken, was ſeiz'd at <hi>Leyden,</hi> ſent over into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and by a Rule of Court order'd to be executed; as is uſual where the Outlawry is not allow'd to be <hi>revers'd:</hi> And, I know Dr. <hi>B.</hi> remembers this ſo well, that he has paſt an Invidious Reflection for it, both on our Government, and Mr. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, p. 59, 55.</note> 
                  <hi>Varillas;</hi> tho' he is forc'd to grant, even where he would willingly make this Proceeding againſt the Knight but a ſort of <hi>Judicial</hi> Murder, That the <hi>Condemning Men</hi> in <hi>Abſence has been alway Practis'd by our Law, where the Abſence was Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful;</hi> and we all know it is ſo too by the Laws of <hi>Scotland.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">P. 54.</note> And I hope no one will imagine, that the Dr. was detain'd in <hi>Holland</hi> againſt his <hi>Will.</hi> And as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready advis'd our Author, out of Tenderneſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ſo it is ſtill my opinion, That it would have been a wiſer <hi>Reflection</hi> upon his Caſe, to conſider, that <hi>by the King's Laws every one of his Subjects is warranted to</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:54220:21"/>
                  <hi>ſeize on ſuch Offenders, in what manner ſoever,</hi> then to reflect upon nothing elſe, but the Juſtice of the Court that Condemned <hi>Him,</hi> and the Memorial of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty that demanded the <hi>Dr.</hi> And this Tranſaction is not an antiquated Preſident, that our <hi>Fathers have told us,</hi> but what we have <hi>ſeen</hi> with our <hi>Eyes,</hi> and <hi>heard</hi> with our <hi>Ears;</hi> tho' I cannot <hi>hear</hi> that the <note n="*" place="margin">The At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that was made ſince upon another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, at the <hi>Hague,</hi> was of another nature, and of which they might with more reaſon complain.</note> States ever return'd us any publick Remonſtrance againſt it, as a Breach of Priviledge upon the <hi>Law of Nations;</hi> And why? Becauſe by the <hi>King's Laws</hi> every one of his Subjects was <hi>warranted</hi> ſo to do.</p>
               <p>I could carry this <hi>view of Hiſtory</hi> further, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Dr's ſevere Droll, on the Envoy's Memorial of <hi>Dead</hi> or <hi>Alive,</hi> to aggravate his <hi>pretended danger;</hi> and tell him of <hi>Subjects</hi> that have executed their Prince's <hi>Juſtice,</hi> when he has been but in <hi>bad</hi> Circumſtances to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it; and the Dr. has heard of Attempts upon an <hi>Askam,</hi> a <hi>Liſle,</hi> and a <hi>Doriſlaws:</hi> but <hi>ill</hi> Practiſes muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make good <hi>worſe</hi> Proceedings, and ſuch a Revenge as no <hi>Nature</hi> will allow, can never be juſtify'd by a <hi>Law of Nations;</hi> ſo that his <hi>fears</hi> are as idle and <hi>need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> as his aſperſing His Majeſty for it are moſt vainly <hi>Seditious.</hi> The <hi>beſt</hi> that he can make of theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that affect him, is to be a <hi>better Subject</hi> to his <hi>natural Prince,</hi> and then he'l need no <hi>Protection</hi> from any other <hi>Lords.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, to conclude with what His Majeſty's Memorial might well do too, * <hi>That the States ought</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vindic. of himſelf, p. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>to puniſh both him and his Printer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The deference that was due to their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> from any of the Subjects of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> is as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54220:21"/>
                  <hi>Temporal</hi> too, I hope, as the Dr's <hi>Allegiance</hi> that he has <hi>transferr'd</hi> to them; and we are bound to retain no longer a reſpect, than they are found to continue that firmneſs of Alliance, which, as I may well ſay now, has been too much violated: So it might have been wiſh'd, by both ſides, the Dr. had never brought it to ſo much as a Diſpute; and tho' out of an humble regard to their Government, I <hi>do</hi> not preſume to preſcribe Meaſures to their <hi>State;</hi> I <hi>do</hi> not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to tell the <hi>States</hi> what they <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>do;</hi> yet I may, I hope, with all <hi>Humility,</hi> tell them what the <hi>States</hi> have <hi>done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Theſe <hi>High and Mighty States of</hi> Holland <hi>and</hi> Weſt-Frieſtland, to the Protection of which the Dr. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Six Pap. pag. 50.</note> does ſo zealouſly recommend himſelf, did in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reidan. Annal. Belg. <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Anno</hi> 1587.</note> 
                  <hi>decree death</hi> to <hi>ſuch</hi> as ſhould in <hi>Libels</hi> and <hi>Reflections</hi> dare to <hi>revile Her Majeſty:</hi> And I did not doubt, but that their Lordſhips would have been as tender of the Honour of Our Preſent <hi>Prince,</hi> as their firſt Anceſtors were for that of his <hi>Predeceſſor,</hi> eſpecially if they had conſider'd him, under a more <hi>Auguſt Title,</hi> and much more <hi>extended Dominion;</hi> and that their <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>England</hi> may with Modeſty be ſtiled a <hi>leſs</hi> Monarch than the King of <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is an old Edict, as I am well inform'd, and that ſtill in force, a ſolemn unanimous Act of the whole States Generals, united; which condemns to perpetual Impriſonment all Perſons, <hi>Aliens</hi> as well as <hi>Subjects,</hi> who ſhall in their Dominions, by <hi>Writing</hi> or <hi>Printing,</hi> publiſh any <hi>Letters</hi> or <hi>Libels,</hi> to the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of His Majeſty the KING of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. By Virtue alſo of this <hi>ancient Decree,</hi> did a <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> and <hi>ingenious</hi> Miniſter of the late King, Sir <hi>W. T.</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:54220:22"/>
then reſiding at the <hi>Hague,</hi> cauſe the Sieur <hi>John Rothe,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Byer,</hi> Brother to the Book-holder of the Dutch <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, with their <hi>Printer,</hi> to be ſeiz'd; Sir <hi>John</hi> was clapt up in the <hi>Raſphouſe;</hi> the other in <note place="margin">Anno 1676.</note> the <hi>Stadthouſs</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> where they are ſaid to be ſtill Priſoners, notwithſtanding they were <hi>Natives,</hi> and that is more than <hi>naturaliz'd,</hi> and related to men of more <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Wealth</hi> than our <hi>Author</hi> can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to. This I have had atteſted to me, by ſome men of Underſtanding, and one of them one of the <hi>King's Subjects,</hi> that ſeiz'd them; ſo that by their <hi>own Laws,</hi> as well as the <hi>King</hi>'s, they were warranted to do ſo, and the <hi>States</hi> bound by their <hi>own</hi> Preſidents to puniſh both <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Printer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Original</hi> Libels, for which they proſecuted both the <hi>Author</hi> and the <hi>Printer,</hi> I have ready to produce; and it was not alone the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Cauſe that occaſioned their Proſecution, but <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Eenige Sware be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchuldinge tegen de Prince van <hi>Orange, &amp;c.</hi> p. 2, &amp; 7. p. 2. Dat de Prince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> conſuleert over de wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigſte ſaken deſe Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liik, <hi>Met ſyn Ooms', den Koningh van Engelandt, en den Hertogh Van York.</hi> p 7. Dat de Staten even Van de Prince <hi>Misbryiickt</hi> en qualiick gehandelt worden als het <hi>Parlement in Engelandt van hare Koninck.</hi>
                  </note> His late Majeſty, the Preſent * King, and the Government of <hi>England,</hi> being all Libell'd in the ſame Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, animated our King to demand Satisfaction alſo for Himſelf, ſince the ſame Author had repreſented Him and His Royal Brother as ſo many Conſpirators with the Prince, and reflected upon His Majeſty, as betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and uſurping upon his <hi>Parliaments,</hi> after the ſame manner that His Highneſs did Deſign upon their <hi>States.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe High and Mighty <hi>States</hi> did then think it their Duty to do Juſtice to His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and to His Preſent Majeſty, though then
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54220:22"/>
without a <hi>Crown,</hi> who might, I hope, as well expect it from them <hi>now,</hi> while He wears one: They pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht their <hi>Placaets</hi> then againſt ſuch an <hi>Author,</hi> and his <hi>Printer,</hi> both <hi>them,</hi> and their <hi>Orders,</hi> I have by me to ſhew; look't upon them, and term'd them too <hi>lying, ſcandalous,</hi> and <hi>Seditious</hi> Paſquils, <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Their Placaet prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted too by Mr. <hi>Fagel</hi>'s <hi>Scheltus,</hi> at the <hi>Hague,</hi> 1676.</note> promis'd Three Thouſand Gu'lders for the Diſcovery, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Author</hi> to Juſtice; and Two Thouſand to any one that ſhould detect the <hi>Printer:</hi> But <hi>Time</hi> has <hi>ſhown</hi> us now the reaſon why theſe <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty</hi> Men could not comply with His Preſent Majeſty in <hi>puniſhing</hi> Dr. <hi>B.</hi> or his <hi>Printer;</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>vid.</hi> Miinheer <hi>Fagel</hi>'s Miſſive printed by the ſame <hi>Scheltus.</hi>
                  </note> tho' they thought ſo much my ſelf to deſerve it. Theſe Libels were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow'd only to facilitate this <hi>Invaſion,</hi> and the King could have no <hi>Juſtice,</hi> only becauſe they kept more in <hi>Reſerve</hi> than the Dr's <hi>Society,</hi> or the deepeſt <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, (i. e.)</hi> to do him the greateſt <hi>Injury. Time</hi> has ſhewn us <hi>now,</hi> (as our <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. on <hi>Parl. pac.</hi> part 1. p. 5.</note> Author was pleaſed to tell us, <hi>ſome time</hi> ſince) not only the <hi>unjuſt Reſentments</hi> of theſe <hi>States,</hi> but the <hi>falſe</hi> Pretences they made, of their being Ready to do His Majeſty <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and ſo verify'd <hi>a fortiori,</hi> that my <hi>juſt</hi> Accuſation, which our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was ſo ſollicitous they ſhould <hi>Reſent.</hi> And <hi>Thoſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Refl. part 1.</note> 
                  <hi>that never dealt yet ſo fairly with Princes,</hi> have now ſhewn themſelves more <hi>fair</hi> in a <hi>ſuperfluous Faith,</hi> to one that put himſelf upon them for a Vaſſal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:54220:23"/>
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>AND now, in the next place, to come to what concerns <hi>Fugitives,</hi> the Articles of Peace agreed on between <hi>this</hi> Crown and <hi>their</hi> State. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. of himſelf, p. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fugitive Criminals, and their <hi>Protection,</hi> has been often, and was ever of old, much controverted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Soveraign Princes and States; and ſo far did the <hi>Romans</hi> once invade the Power of <hi>Protection,</hi> that they procur'd the delivering of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> by the King of <hi>Bythinia,</hi> tho' he was only the nobleſt of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and ow'd not the leaſt Subjection to <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Favour he defied, as well as often had defeated their Force. This was indeed a Reproach to <hi>Pruſias;</hi> as Sir <hi>Walter</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtory of the World, l. 5. c. 6. Sect. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Raleigh</hi> ſays, upon whom <hi>Flaminius</hi> an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador from the <hi>Romans</hi> had prevailed, that it made him unworthy of the Crown he wore: Which <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,</hi> as <hi>Grotius</hi> obſerves, <hi>is due to the Oppreſſed, tho' not to Wilful Malefactors;</hi> and in the Caſe of a <hi>defeated</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De Jure Bell. &amp; Pacis.</note> Enemy, cannot be pretended unlawful, unleſs by the expreſs Articles of a League; and if in that caſe it ſhall extend to an <hi>open</hi> Enemy, it will, <hi>a fortiori,</hi> to the Subjects of either State, that were in ſuch an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, and with a more ſuperlative reaſon to ſuch as owe a <hi>natural Allegiance</hi> to their Native Prince, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Temporal Obedience</hi> to that State wherein they live. This <hi>Local Subjection</hi> my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> will allow to be <note place="margin">3d. Inſt. c. 1.</note>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:54220:23"/>
due from <hi>Aliens;</hi> ſo that <hi>during their ſtay there,</hi> their Allegiance is as much <hi>tranſlated</hi> to the Forreign State, as it can be done by the <hi>Act of Naturalization,</hi> or our Author can pretend to: for the <hi>Naturalizing</hi> Forreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, may impower them to greater Priviledges in the place wherein they live, as does our <hi>Denization</hi> too, but can never make them <hi>leſs Subjects</hi> to their <hi>natural Lord,</hi> to whom, as <hi>Natives,</hi> they belong: For when <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">De Jure Bell. &amp; Pac. lib. 1. cap. 3.</note> obſerves, that no Confederate has a right di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to apprehend and puniſh the Subjects of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confederate; and inſtances in <hi>Decius,</hi> who when bound by <hi>Hannibal,</hi> was upon pleading it ſet at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: He is there only to be underſtood of ſuch Subjects as are <hi>natural born Subjects</hi> and <hi>Natives,</hi> and not made ſo by a <hi>formality of Law:</hi> And yet this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, that is favourable enough in the Point, is of opinion too, That if a <hi>Native</hi> ſhould act any thing againſt an expreſs Article, agreed on between a neighbouring Nation, with whom they are in <hi>League,</hi> the King or State are oblig'd either to <hi>puniſh</hi> or <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> up the Offender to the Perſons injur'd: And ſince our Author makes his <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Marriage</hi> ſuch a Warrant from <hi>Solon</hi>'s Laws, for his <hi>Naturalization,</hi> that <hi>ſame</hi> Law-giver I muſt tell him, would not admit any Strangers to be enroll'd among his Citizens, unleſs they were baniſht out of their own <hi>Country</hi> for <hi>ever,</hi> ſuch whom their <hi>Country</hi> did <hi>renounce,</hi> and not thoſe that <hi>renounce</hi> their <hi>Country.</hi> And tho' this <hi>Marriage</hi> might have given him ſome ground for his being <hi>naturaliz'd,</hi> I hope it gave no <hi>Colour</hi> for the <hi>tranſlating</hi> his <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance;</hi> or elſe it would ſound a little Unlucky, that his being <hi>Married</hi> in <hi>another</hi> Country, ſhould occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion his being <hi>Horned</hi> in his <hi>own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:54220:24"/>
But then, in the Caſe of <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Fugitives,</hi> we <note place="margin">Vind. of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, p 4.</note> ſhall find agen a vaſter difference than in all the reſt.</p>
               <p>By the <hi>natural</hi> Law as well as the <hi>municipal</hi> ones of the Land, the King has a Right to the Service of <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. 11 Hen. 7. c 1. Vid. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe, K. <hi>Jam.</hi>
                  </note> all his Subjects; can command their return or removal from or to any place <hi>abroad;</hi> and nothing has been more frequently practiſed; and they refuſing to do <hi>this,</hi> (which has been as often obey'd both by whole Bodies and Societies of Merchants, as once in the <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> Company, to <hi>Stode;</hi> and ſome others) tho' but as ſingle Perſons, has been always adjudg'd <hi>Rebellious,</hi> and is indeed ſo by all Law; even where no ſuch cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal matter, as <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and the refuſal to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, does make the Offender ſo. Now, though our Author <hi>went out of</hi> Scotland <hi>fourteen Years ago, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vid. id. p. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>left</hi> England <hi>by the King's Leave,</hi> yet if upon His Command he does not return, I humbly conceive, that <hi>truly</hi> in a Legal ſenſe he may be ſtiled <hi>Rebellious,</hi> and a <hi>Fugitive;</hi> though there was no Crime that ſtain'd him deeper with that Appellation, or gave him more occaſion for his Contumacy and Flight; for the flying from Juſtice after the expiration of the term of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, is that which makes him a <hi>Fugitive,</hi> tho' he departed the Realm with all the ſolemn Leave and Permiſſion imaginable: So that the ſecond Memorial of the Marqueſs was founded upon as much Reaſon, and upon which this Author would as vainly fix as much <hi>Abſurdity;</hi> where I too <hi>cannot but take notice</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vid. ib. <hi>Vid.</hi> 1 Lett. to my Lord <hi>M. Vid.</hi> 2d. Lett.</note> how he labours to make that an Inconſiſtency in the Memorials, which he endeavours to reconcile in all his Writings, <hi>viz.</hi> That of <hi>being the Subject of the States,</hi> and yet to be puniſht as the <hi>King's Subject,</hi> for to them he is willing to be thought but a <hi>Temporal</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:54220:24"/>
                  <hi>Subject,</hi> and yet at the ſame time to retain for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as his Natural Lord, all Duty imaginable: And I muſt confeſs, had not his unhappy Expreſſion of <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated Allegiance</hi> been Treaſon by the Law of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and which, the Engliſh ones too ſay, cannot be by ſuch an <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coke</hi> 7 Rep. fol. 90. <hi>Dyer</hi> fol. 300. Alſo Dr. <hi>Story</hi>'s Caſe. <hi>ut Supra.</hi> 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Abjuration transferr'd;</hi> he had not pronounced himſelf a <hi>Rebel</hi> and a <hi>Fugitive,</hi> under his own hand; and by his <hi>Letters</hi> to the Secretary, before thoſe of <hi>Horning</hi> were iſſued out of <hi>Scotland:</hi> the moſt favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conſtruction that could have been put upon it, was, (did not his Malice againſt His Majeſty and His Government, betray'd by his Reflections ſince, prevent an excuſing it) That his profeſſing ſo much Divinity and the defence of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> had hindered, or excuſed him, from the diſcovering how deeply his <hi>unalterable Allegiance</hi> was founded by the <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Celebrated Caſe of his <hi>Countryman</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Calvin,</hi> (and the Doctor, I know, upon another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, reverences the Name) which my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> has ſo largely reported, has carried <hi>Allegiance</hi> to that pitch, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coke</hi> 7. Rept.</note> that I think it is not ſo eaſily <hi>tranſlated;</hi> he calls it <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and Obedience inſeparable from every Subject;</hi> as ſoon as <hi>born</hi> he makes it to <hi>Commence,</hi> before the firſt <note place="margin">Fol. 4. B. f. 5. A.</note> Oath of Obligation is taken in the Court Leet; for this Opinion he cites too the <hi>Scotch</hi> Expoſition of Mr. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ad Regiam Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem.</note> 
                  <hi>Skeen,</hi> who (I find) ſays this ſort of Liegiance is due to the King <hi>alone,</hi> with exception to <hi>all</hi> others; ſo that as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> obſerves in this point, <hi>the Laws</hi> of <hi>both Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries agree;</hi> and this <hi>Naturalization</hi> being but what Lawyers call an <hi>acquir'd Allegiance,</hi> cannot (as I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before) <hi>Eradicate,</hi> or defeat by ſuch a formal Contract, that <hi>natural Obedience,</hi> that is ſo deeply <hi>rooted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:54220:25"/>
It is <hi>poſitively</hi> aſſerted in that Caſe, <hi>That the King has</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Fol. 8. <hi>A. B.</hi> Poteſtatem habet in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus tranſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinis, fidem &amp; fideles in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus tranſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinis.</note> 
                  <hi>a Command over his Subjects, as well out of the Realm as within,</hi> that they owe him <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> in <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Countries,</hi> and from thence he concludes, (as I hinted before) that <hi>Abjuration,</hi> (which is an Act of Law, and by which you are forc'd many times to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your Kingdom for a Penalty) cannot excuſe you from your <hi>Natural Obedience,</hi> though under an <hi>exile;</hi> for (ſays he) <hi>the King may in mercy reſtore him;</hi> much leſs then, I may conclude, againſt our Author, ſhall a <hi>Voluntary Abjuration, tranſlate</hi> his <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and which was over-rul'd againſt Dr. <hi>Story,</hi> that he could <hi>not do it at his pleaſure;</hi> though <note n="*" place="margin">De Jure Bell. Lib. 2. cap. 5. Pag. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> is indeed of another Opinion in the <hi>point</hi> of <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> which does not come up to our Authors Caſe, he being <hi>deſir'd</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;</hi> and the <hi>Heraclidae</hi> had a better pretence when they were <hi>baniſht</hi> Argos, to plead their being no longer Subjects to <hi>Euryſtheus;</hi> yet even <hi>Grotius</hi> grants there, that by the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, where a Citizen forſook his <hi>Native</hi> Habitation, he was oblig'd ſtill to ſuch Offices as ſhould be impos'd on him, and to pay Contribution; which implys, that even in Governments <hi>Democratical, birth</hi> lies ſuch an Obligation by <hi>Nature</hi> to the place where one is <hi>born,</hi> from which we cannot ſo ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede by our own Artificial Acts and Pretences: And as he has granted too, that no <hi>number</hi> of Perſons, or <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> one, can deſert his Country, if the <hi>Publick</hi> be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd by it; ſo I may conclude, that no number of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous Men, or ſingle Seditious Subjects, can by any Expedient whatſoever, extricate themſelves from their <hi>Obedience,</hi> and be <hi>protected</hi> in it; where the Juſtice of the Nation is both <hi>affronted</hi> and evaded, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Publick</hi> Peace in danger to be <hi>diſturb'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:54220:25"/>
But as our Author could not but take notice of the <note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> great <hi>difference</hi> there was between the <hi>Memorials,</hi> ſo I cannot but obſerve the ſame in his defence, and <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> in one place he intimates his <hi>claiming</hi> and <hi>deſiring</hi> the <hi>Protection</hi> of the <hi>States;</hi> and in <hi>another, values</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Innocency, upon his never having <hi>deſir'd</hi> it; <hi>I apply'd my ſelf</hi> (ſays he) <hi>immediately to the States</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Pag. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Holland, to be <hi>Naturaliz'd;</hi> and in the next Page appeals to the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> if ever he made any Applications to them.</p>
               <p>But we muſt conſider further, what <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> have done to Perſons under his Circumſtances; whereas, all the Anſwer that was given to the Envoy, about his <hi>be comming their Subject,</hi> did (in ſhort) amount to this; <hi>They firſt Naturaliz'd him, that they might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him, and then ſay he was under their Protection, becauſe he was Naturaliz'd;</hi> but to do all <hi>Juſtice,</hi> even to thoſe that do not deſign, to any people, or to us to be ſo much <hi>Juſt;</hi> the offering to put our Author to his Tryal <hi>there,</hi> would be ſomewhat of ſatisfaction to the <hi>Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> as well as our <hi>own;</hi> had it been but as <hi>ſincerely</hi> put in Execution, and that which has already been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, had been ſufficient matter to have founded any Proceſs, had it ever been in <hi>reality</hi> deſign'd; and as we have ſhewn what they <hi>themſelves</hi> in the <hi>ſame</hi> Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances <hi>have done,</hi> and by ſome of their Edicts and Decrees are oblig'd <hi>to do;</hi> ſo we ſhall with the like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to their Authority, repreſent a little larger Draught to their View, of what <hi>other</hi> Nations have granted in ſuch Caſes; and in which <hi>all</hi> Stateſmen, and even ſome of their <hi>own</hi> do agree.</p>
               <p>It is an indiſputable point, and from the Laws of both Kingdoms plainly appears, that by the <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Horning,</hi> in the Caſe of <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> the Criminal is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54220:26"/>
declar'd, a <hi>Rebel,</hi> and a <hi>Fugitive,</hi> for the worſt of Crimes that can make him <hi>ſo;</hi> and by our <hi>Writ</hi> of <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> he is lookt upon as ſuch in the like caſe; and can (if <hi>ſeiz'd</hi> before the Year be expir'd) if the Court think fit, be deny'd to reverſe it; and though but very lately, it was offer'd from the merciful Inclination of the King and the favour of the Court, to one <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Holloway</hi>'s Caſe of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow.</hi>
                  </note> that was fled to one of our Plantations for High Treaſon, yet it was as ſoon afterward deny'd to another, <note n="†" place="margin">Sir <hi>T. A.</hi>
                  </note> we have mention'd before, who ſuffer'd as <hi>Juſtly</hi> without it; this being conſider'd, <hi>the</hi> Act of <hi>flying</hi> makes them not only <hi>Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> but <hi>Traytors,</hi> as much as if they had been Try'd and Convicted by a <hi>Judicial</hi> Proceſs, from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our Law; and therefore I ſuppoſe it is the common Quaere in the Caſes of Felony, whither the Criminals <hi>fled for the ſame,</hi> it being always to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, the greateſt Argument of their Guilt? Now no Judge, either of Law, or Reaſon, but will allow, that a perſon (though <hi>occaſionally</hi> withdrawn) that refuſes to appear when a <hi>Citation</hi> is iſſued forth, but is as much a <hi>Fugitive,</hi> as if he had but immediately <hi>fled</hi> upon his being <hi>Cited;</hi> and this being our Authors Caſe even when it's <hi>beſt</hi> excus'd; we will conſider, how by the <hi>Laws of Nations</hi> he is to be treated.</p>
               <p>It was a Saying of <hi>Tertullian, that</hi> againſt <hi>Publick Enemies every Man is a Souldier;</hi> and I ſuppoſe, <hi>that</hi> may imply that every Subject, when a Criminal is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd <hi>ſo,</hi> is <hi>warranted</hi> to <hi>ſeize him in what manner ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi> by the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> ſays <hi>Grotius, every innocent</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De Jure Bell. Lib. 2. c. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>perſon has a right to puniſh a Malefactor;</hi> and it is only the reſult of our being ſettl'd into <hi>Civil Societys,</hi> that leaves to the reſpective Bodies, both the Right and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to puniſh Offenders againſt themſelves; though this does not hinder <hi>Forreign States</hi> from puniſhing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54220:26"/>
them, which they <hi>muſt</hi> do, or <hi>deliver</hi> them up, if deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the <hi>Injur'd</hi> one; and ſince <hi>neither</hi> of them has been done here, though <hi>both</hi> demanded; it cannot be well juſtified by the <hi>partial</hi> Arguments of the Doctor, and as little to be defended by the Pen of a <hi>fairer,</hi> or a better Advocate: This ſort of <hi>Dedition, Sacred</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory affords us ſufficient <hi>Examples</hi> of, as well as the <hi>Prophane,</hi> I had given our Author <hi>ſome</hi> that I think <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated</hi> to <hi>himſelf;</hi> but ſince he ſuppoſes he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to <hi>Anſwer</hi> them, I ſhall ſend him ſo many more.</p>
               <p>We ſhall not inſiſt upon <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Caſe, and that of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> (ſince our Author pretends to engroſs all the Divinity, and will not grant us ſo much as to underſtand the Doctrine of the <hi>Arrians)</hi> and 'tis more than hee'l forgive us now, the touching upon <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> or a Text of Scripture; neither ſhall I lay any great weight upon what was done by the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> when they were deny'd by the <hi>Meſſenians</hi> ſome that had fled to them only for Felony and Rape; neither need I ſhew, how even great Commanders, or Princes, have been ſo unfortunate as to be demanded; as <hi>Cato</hi> deſir'd the Senate to deliver up <hi>Coeſar</hi> himſelf, to the <hi>Germans,</hi> and our Uſurper as impudently expected it from <hi>France,</hi> and theſe <hi>States,</hi> in the caſe of our Exil'd Soveraign, neither ſhall I repeat thoſe Preſidents I have formerly apply'd, that which is more proper in this place, ſhall be what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the ſtirring up Sedition, or diſturbing the Peace of a Forreign State, which no Government can tolerate in their <hi>own Subjects,</hi> or <hi>Fugitives.</hi> Thus did the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> demand from the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> that <hi>Amilcar</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Livii Lib. 2.8.</note> ſhould be <hi>delivered</hi> up to them, becauſe he had ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Gauls</hi> to rebel againſt them. And thus did the <hi>Athenians</hi> make publick Proclamation, that whoever ſhould plot any miſchief againſt <hi>Philip,</hi> and fly for <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:54220:27"/>
to <hi>Athens,</hi> ſhould inſtantly be <hi>delivered</hi> up to him. <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. Com. Lib. 1. c. 1.</note> The Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> being requir'd by <hi>Lewis</hi> XI. of <hi>France,</hi> to deliver up <hi>De la Marche,</hi> for <hi>writing ſomewhat againſt his Government,</hi> was anſwer'd by the Duke, that though he was not in the leaſt the King's Subject, yet if it could be made out, he had ſaid, or done any thing againſt his Majeſty's <hi>Honour,</hi> he would ſee <hi>him puniſht as he deſerv'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though <hi>Grotius</hi> obſerves in their favour, that they are not <hi>abſolutely</hi> to be <hi>deliver'd,</hi> yet grants they muſt (if that be refus'd) be <hi>neceſſarily Puniſht;</hi> and this was the Complaint of the <hi>Aelians</hi> againſt thoſe of <hi>Lacedoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that they would do <hi>neither;</hi> and where the ſame Author obſerves, that our <hi>Europoean</hi> Princes have in the laſt Age Conniv'd at the <hi>protection</hi> of ſome Malefactors, yet he grants it is only in leſſer Crimes, never to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to thoſe that are <hi>diſturbers</hi> of the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> of their <hi>own Country,</hi> or directly excepted againſt in the Articles of any League. <hi>Gylippus</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing upon this point of <hi>protection,</hi> ſays it was ever intended <hi>only</hi> for ſuch as were <hi>unfortunately miſerable,</hi> and not for thoſe that are <hi>maliciouſly wicked;</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Miſereri o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet qui propter fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam non ma litiam in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriis ſunt. <hi>Vid.</hi> Cicero, tranſlat.</note> 
                  <hi>Demoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes</hi> ſays the <hi>ſame,</hi> and I ſhall ſubmit it to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>World,</hi> as well as to the <hi>States,</hi> whither our Authors <hi>Malice</hi> againſt the King and Government, has not brought him to his <hi>misfortune.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the old Cities of refuge, which we read of in the Sacred Writ, were only granted to ſuch <hi>unfortunate</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders as we mention'd before, and all the Preſidents that can be brought where their delivery has been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd, as the <hi>Chalcidenſes</hi> did <hi>Naaplius</hi> to the <hi>Groecians;</hi> King <hi>Pepin</hi> thoſe that fled to him out of <hi>Normandy;</hi> the Emperour <hi>Lodovicus Pius</hi> thoſe that ran to him from <hi>Rome;</hi> and the <hi>Gepidoe, Ildigiſales</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> was
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54220:27"/>
either, where the accuſed had clear'd themſelves upon a <hi>Tryal,</hi> or where they fled from a <hi>Tyrannous Perſecution;</hi> and that I ſuppoſe is the reaſon why our Author would repreſent himſelf ſo <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Six Pap.</note> 
                  <hi>Perſecuted,</hi> and make the Caſe of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. of himſelf, p. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Fugitives</hi> of <hi>France</hi> to be his <hi>own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot but remark here upon the <hi>Modeſt</hi> Requeſt, that by the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> 1 Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial.</note> firſt Memorial was made againſt the Dr. and which he treats too, with as great rudeneſs, and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which deſir'd civilly, if they would not <hi>deliver</hi> him up, only that he might be <hi>baniſht</hi> out of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; this, I humbly conceive, was a Condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where it might have demanded his <hi>Tryal,</hi> and <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> for <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> this was ſuch a reaſonable Requeſt, that <hi>all</hi> Hiſtory, and Law, give a greater al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, as in the former Preſidents has been <hi>ſhewn;</hi> and in this, as by ſome, we ſhall now <hi>ſhew,</hi> was never in the leaſt controverted; ſo did the * <hi>Cymaei,</hi> who when they would not deliver up <hi>Pactyes</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> yet notwithſtanding, they would not offer to keep him, but ſent or ſuffer'd him to fly away to <hi>Mytelene;</hi> and <hi>Perſeus</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> in his Apology to <hi>Martius,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting about thoſe that had betray'd <hi>Eumenes,</hi> ſays, <hi>As ſoon as upon your Information, I found theſe Men in</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia, <hi>I commanded them immediately to depart my Kingdom, and for ever interdicted them all my Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The denial of this, I am ſure, is more to be <hi>admir'd,</hi> than <hi>defended,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> might think themſelves as injuriouſly dealt with all, if ever they ſhould happen to be ſo <hi>deny'd,</hi> if <hi>Private Subjects</hi> ſhall have ſuch a right of Proſecution? if in <hi>Civil Actions</hi> Creditors can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it for a <hi>Debt?</hi> how can it be juſtify'd, when in an offence againſt the <hi>Crown,</hi> and the higheſt too, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd to one of the greateſt Princes in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:54220:28"/>
Our Author utterly miſtakes it when he would make <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Pag. 4. 1 Conſid.</note> us believe, <hi>That by the ſenſe of the ſeventh</hi> Article, <hi>all Condemnations being to be under Publick, and Authentick Letters, muſt be meant of the Record of the Sentence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be tranſmitted them:</hi> A body would have thought a <hi>Copy</hi> of it might <hi>have</hi> ſerv'd the turn, for <hi>Records</hi> are not ſo ſoon parted with out of <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall;</hi> I do not know what may be done out of the Archieves of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or their <hi>Registers</hi> there of their Journal Books, but if I miſtake not by a Law of his Country, <hi>Letters of Horning,</hi> and their <hi>Executions,</hi> are not to be prov'd by Witneſſes, and that forbidden by <note n="*" place="margin">Ja. 6 p. 6.</note> Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that it is impoſſible to make ſuch proof as can atteſt a <hi>Copy;</hi> and for the <hi>Journal</hi> it ſelf, I ſuppoſe they would hardly ſend; but by <hi>that Article</hi> may be as well underſtood, that an <hi>Envoys Memorial</hi> repreſenting, that by the Laws of his Country ſuch a perſon ſtands Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, that this is of it ſelf a <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Authentick Inſtrument,</hi> when it comes from the hand of ſuch a <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſter</hi> of State, and therefore in the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd Caſe of the Prince of <hi>Macedon,</hi> as ſoon as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd but information that ſuch Men were retir'd into his Territories, he immediatly interdicted them, and immediately upon the demand of <hi>Bothwell,</hi> Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> ſaid, ſhe would either <hi>deliver</hi> him <hi>up</hi> or <hi>ſend</hi> him <hi>out</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuch Arguments as the Schools call <hi>ad hominem,</hi> with ſome People are moſt prevalent; therefore as I do not in other things pretend to preſcribe meaſures to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> of what they are to <hi>do,</hi> ſo I muſt offer one Inſtance more of what in <hi>this</hi> caſe too they <hi>have done,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> without proof or examination.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54220:28"/>
'Tis known <hi>then,</hi> that they of <hi>Holland</hi> not long ſince deliver'd up the Cook that had been in the Conſpiracy with the Counteſs of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> of <hi>France</hi> for <hi>poiſoning;</hi> and he that endeavours with his <hi>Venome</hi> and <hi>Malice</hi> to Alienate the Subjects Hearts from the King and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by the <hi>miſrepreſentation</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> and his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,</hi> which by the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> is call'd <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> muſt by that of <hi>all Nations</hi> be concluded to have forfeited that right of <hi>Protection,</hi> which as hath been ſhewn, in <hi>ſuch offenders,</hi> it does more particularly <hi>refuſe</hi> to favour.</p>
               <p>In the Article of the Crown of <hi>Denmark,</hi> for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing <note place="margin">5 Article <hi>Feb.</hi> 4. 1660.</note> and returning us any Regicides, that ſhould be found in their Dominions, or ſhould hereafter repair there, it was agreed, that upon the firſt notice to that Crown, aſſoon as the King was told of their being there, they ſhould be apprehended, put into ſafe hands of their <hi>own</hi> Officers, or of ſuch as the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould appoint to take them into Cuſtody, and this was obſerv'd, without any expectance of any <hi>Record</hi> of their Sentence and Attaindure.</p>
               <p>As to his ſecond Conſideration as it <hi>relates</hi> to the common Acceptation of the Word <hi>Fugitive</hi> and <hi>Rebel,</hi> when the concern is <hi>national,</hi> they may either be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued according to the <hi>Municipal Laws</hi> of the Country, or the Laws of <hi>all Nations,</hi> and by <hi>both</hi> of thoſe, his Conſtruction of the <hi>Terms,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Merit</hi> of his Cauſe, will be certainly Condemn'd; for a <hi>Fugitive,</hi> (as we have intimated before) by the Laws of <hi>both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> is ſo reputed from the time of his <hi>abſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after Citation;</hi> though he were innocently <hi>abſent</hi> long <hi>before;</hi> and by the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> according to which, <hi>all</hi> Leagues and Treaties are to be interpreted, and take their Acceptation; he that is accus'd of the <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:54220:29"/>
                  <hi>Laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> is <hi>criminated</hi> for a <hi>Rebel,</hi> and therefore it is promiſcuouſly call'd too, the <note n="*" place="margin">Idem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duellio dicitur Zouchaei. Elem. p. 4. Sect. 9. etſi is proprie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duellionis reus eſt qui hoſtili animo adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Remp. vel Principem eſt Armatus. <hi>Vid. Ibid.</hi> &amp; D. 48.4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Crimen Perduellionis,</hi> though properly in ſtrictneſs, <hi>he</hi> is only guilty of the <hi>latter,</hi> that comes, <hi>Arm'd in an Hoſtile man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to Invade the King, or the Common-wealth.</hi> I wiſh our Author could help himſelf better in his Explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which for any thing that he has offer'd yet, he muſt be concluded in the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Treaty,</hi> which have been ſo <hi>often</hi> ratify'd and confirm'd, and which deny any <hi>Protection</hi> to declar'd <hi>Rebels,</hi> and <hi>Fugitives:</hi> And this was the Opinion of the <hi>Dutch</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Their own <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Hiſtorian.</note> 
                  <hi>themſelves,</hi> in the Caſe of the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>Furſtemberg,</hi> whom they look'd upon as a <hi>Rebel,</hi> for not <hi>obeying</hi> the Imperial <hi>Mandatum Avocato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> as well as for <hi>bearing</hi> of Arms againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour; and by the ſame reaſon the Regicides might as well have been refus'd us, <hi>becauſe</hi> many of the Kings Judges never <hi>bore</hi> Arms, but even that it ſeems our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor does not decline, to make himſelf in his <hi>own</hi> ſenſe, and the <hi>Literal</hi> one, <hi>a Compleat Rebel.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Letter.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Third <hi>Conſideration is, his being Naturaliz'd by the States, before he was Proſecuted by the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did that <hi>Naturalization</hi> (as our Author in <hi>his Letter</hi> does <hi>falſly</hi> imagine) eradicate all that Relation he has to his <hi>natural</hi> Prince, and Leige Lord, did it <hi>really tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate</hi> that <hi>Allegiance</hi> which he <hi>pretends</hi> it does? much might be argu'd from it in his defence, but ſince ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Preſidents have been brought, that have prov'd it quite otherwiſe adjudg'd, and ſeconded with as much <hi>reaſon</hi> as my little ſtock could afford, and that ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd with the reſolution of all the <hi>Laws,</hi> it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that his being the <hi>States Temporal</hi> Subject, does not make him leſs the <hi>King's natural</hi> one, and if <hi>Local Protection,</hi> as he obſerves, is ſo <hi>inſeparable</hi> from Soveraign Power, I am ſure by what has been ſaid, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Allegiance</hi> will appear to be <hi>more</hi> ſo, ſo that his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54220:29"/>
here, is only the very <hi>Crime</hi> that <hi>is</hi> in queſtion; which like the <hi>glorious</hi> ills of the <hi>Roman</hi> Hero, muſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be maintain'd by <hi>doing greater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe I would give all the ſatisfaction imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, we will carry this point of a <hi>Natural Allegiance</hi> being <hi>Inſeparable,</hi> ſome few ſteps further, and ſee firſt, what the Laws of <hi>all</hi> Nations ſay of it, and then what we find ſaid in thoſe of our <hi>own;</hi> and for the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Law,</hi> in this point, it is <hi>poſitive,</hi> that every one becomes a <note n="*" place="margin">Subditus quis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fit, primúm ratione <hi>natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Zouc.</hi> part 4. Sect. 2.</note> Subject truly, and originally, with reſpect to that <hi>Nation</hi> under which he was <hi>born:</hi> And by this word <hi>Nation,</hi> (which thoſe Authors uſe to expreſs it by) I do underſtand, that <hi>Government</hi> is more properly to be intended; for I know, that People may be <hi>born</hi> the Subjects of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and yet without <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Act of Parl. de Natis ultra Mare. <hi>Vid. Crooks</hi> Rep. <hi>Banks</hi>'s Caſe.</note> his <hi>Dominions,</hi> tho' not his <hi>Government;</hi> and is the Common Caſe of thoſe that are born in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories beyond Sea, which by a Fiction in Law, <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers</hi> the place of <hi>birth</hi> to be within the Dioceſs of <hi>London,</hi> and the County of <hi>Middleſex:</hi> And this, if I miſtake not, is the Reſolution of <hi>Banks</hi>'s Caſe in <hi>Crooks Rept.</hi> ſo careful is our Law, leſt any <hi>natural Allegiance</hi> ſhould be <hi>transferr'd</hi> to a <hi>foreign</hi> State, that to avoid it, it <hi>transfers</hi> the place of your Nativity in <hi>another</hi> Country, to the Territories of your <hi>own</hi> Prince; and therefore we are told by <hi>Civilians,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Partus non tantum <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis,</hi> verum etiam <hi>reipub.</hi> naſcitur, cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi ad Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. relatio Exui non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, D. 37, 8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 12.</note> That every man is not only his <hi>Parents</hi> Off-ſpring, but that of his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> or Common-wealth, and this relation to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try he cannot renounce or <hi>tranſlate.</hi> This is poſitive againſt our Author's Aſſertion, that has occaſion'd his Proſecution in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he ſays, it is already, and actually <hi>tranſlated;</hi> when by the Laws of that Country, the very bare <hi>limitation</hi> of his <hi>Allegiance</hi> had been Crime enough to have coſt him his Life. And ſo plain and full are the <hi>Laws</hi> of Nations in this Caſe (and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54220:30"/>
which a Country that is partly governed by them cannot contradict) that they ſay no one can <note n="*" place="margin">Origine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria nemo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt voluntate ſuaſe eximere, nec ſi aliam aſſumat, quod aſſumptio ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis, quae non eſt, veritatem naturae non Perimit, c. 10. 33, 4. D. 5. 1, 6.</note> Diveſt himſelf at his <note n="†" place="margin">So alſo ſay our own Laws. <hi>Vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>Storys</hi> Caſe <hi>ut Supra. Dyer</hi> 300.</note> 
                  <hi>Will and Pleaſure,</hi> of this original rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he has to his Prince and place of Nativity; no, tho' he aſſumes unto himſelf another: For the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a <hi>pretended</hi> Origination, (and <hi>naturalizing</hi> is no more) does not extinguiſh that <hi>natural</hi> one which in reality he muſt ever retain; neither by <note n="*" place="margin">Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſando Patriam, veritatem mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare poteſt, <hi>Zouch.</hi> ibid.</note> falſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of his Country from which he had his birth and original, can he change the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of the thing. And this was ſo <hi>loyally, learnedly,</hi> and <hi>judicially</hi> reſolv'd in the very ſame words, in the recited Caſe of Dr. <hi>Story,</hi> by all the Judges in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, (who is celebrated even by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and others, for employing none but men of the greateſt Underſtanding in the State) that it muſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſede all Objection; and if the <hi>Civil Law</hi> will not by <hi>our own Municipal</hi> Reſolution of the Judges of the Land, Dr. <hi>Bur,</hi> muſt be ſilenced and convicted, even from a Proceſs in the <note n="*" place="margin">13 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Reformation,</hi> and an Hiſtorical Conſutation out of Mr. <hi>Fox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Imperial Laws do ſo expreſly oppoſe our Author's Expoſitions, that they call him a <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Transfuga</hi> eſt, qui ab Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. <hi>Defecit,</hi> &amp; <hi>Deficere</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur qui ab his quorum ſuo imperio ſunt <hi>deſciſcunt,</hi> D. 4. 5, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Fugitive,</hi> that falls off from his Country and Common-wealth; and this Defection they define to conſiſt in <hi>renouncing</hi> their <hi>Obedience</hi> to that Government, under which they were <hi>born;</hi> and this <hi>Native,</hi> in the Phraſeology of <hi>their</hi> Law, they call an <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Originarius</hi> &amp; <hi>Incola</hi> in eo differunt, qued ille <hi>perpetuus</hi> hic pro <hi>tempore</hi> ſubditus exſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. Zouchaeus Elem. Juriſp. p. 4. Sect. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Original,</hi> (a term which our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt is no Stranger to, having <hi>naturaliz'd</hi> it into his Works;) but the ſenſe of it here ſignifies a <hi>natural born Subject,</hi> whom, <hi>Civilians</hi> ſay, differs from an <hi>Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant,</hi> and adventitious one in this, that the one owes a <hi>perpetual ſubjection,</hi> and the other but a <hi>Local</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> one; and this <hi>perpetual Obedience,</hi> that is ſo <hi>inſeparably</hi> requir'd, from what has been ſaid, does appear <hi>unalien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54220:30"/>
and what courſe our Author has taken to <hi>tranſlate</hi> it, cannot apprehend, if it be ſo <hi>transfer'd,</hi> (as for the concern and ſake of his Cauſe more than from any Conviction from his Reaſon, he would perſwade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to believe) then, whenever there ſhould happen to be any breach between thoſe Crowns, or <hi>States,</hi> that were at preſent in good Amity and Correſpondence; Such Deſerters are by their <hi>own</hi> Concluſions qualify'd to <hi>fight</hi> their <hi>own</hi> Prince, and <hi>Invade</hi> their <hi>own</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and perhaps, for that end, our Author maintains the Paradox of this <hi>rebellious</hi> Poſition; for <hi>Allegiance</hi> being once <hi>renounced</hi> by him, as well as <hi>Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> there remains nothing but to exerciſe an <hi>Active</hi> Valour, and the verifying his being a <hi>Rebel,</hi> even in his own ſenſe, a <hi>Man that has born Arms againſt his Prince.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 4.</note> For where <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Birth</hi> is <hi>tranſlated,</hi> there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains no <hi>Obligation,</hi> and <hi>ty,</hi> to <hi>Duty,</hi> or <hi>Relation:</hi> but I am afraid, ſhould ſuch Expoſitors upon their <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> by the fortune of the day be made Priſoners of War, they were not to be treated as Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but as ſo many <hi>Rebels,</hi> and <hi>Fugitives:</hi> It will be too late for them then to have recourſe to the <hi>Poſtlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they have made themſelves <hi>Renegadoes;</hi> when they have <hi>renounc'd</hi> their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> by ſo ſolem an Act as their <hi>own hand writing,</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>return</hi> themſelves again to their former Rights and Priviledges, they may be <hi>receiv'd</hi> indeed, (as Civilians ſay) but then it muſt only be to puniſhment; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Principles, I ſuppoſe the Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, when it makes ſuch a <hi>Renuntiation, Capital.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Captive Enemies; that are taken in the Act of Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, have generally by the Laws of Arms Quarter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, and Liberty to depart; which is more, or leſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd; according to the dealing they meet withal from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54220:31"/>
one another; but ſhould one be found, that by a <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary abjuration</hi> has <hi>renounc'd</hi> his <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Country,</hi> amongſt their Enemies, either <hi>in Arms,</hi> or <hi>without,</hi> in <hi>Camp,</hi> or in <hi>City;</hi> he is to be put to Death as a <hi>Deſerter,</hi> and <hi>Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;</hi> and this is confirm'd, by <hi>conſtant practiſe,</hi> as well as warranted by <hi>all Law;</hi> and where the perſon <hi>owns</hi> his <hi>Allegiance,</hi> actually <hi>tranſlated,</hi> he makes himſelf the <hi>ſame</hi> Criminal, as if he were in League with his Princes Enemies; though that is a Circumſtance that will much aggravate the Crime; and the being under the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of his Friends and Allies, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Grotius Lib. 2. c. 21.</note> only hinders the Prince from entring their Territories, with an Army to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> him; but that cannot debar him from his right of <hi>demanding</hi> his <hi>puniſhment,</hi> or <hi>Dedition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So much for what Civilians ſay in this matter, and it may not be improper to ſuperadd, what common Lawyers, upon the Caſe have reſolv'd; my Lord <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Calvin</hi>'s Caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Coke,</hi> to this purpoſe obſerves, that <hi>natural Allegiance</hi> being an Act and Habit of the mind, it cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd within any place; and from thence would infer, that his Countryman <hi>Calvin</hi> in his Controverted Caſe, could not be ſaid, when he was in <hi>England,</hi> he ow'd the King of <hi>Scots, no natural Obedience;</hi> and that <hi>natural Leigance</hi> ſhould have any reſpect to <hi>a Local</hi> one, was an inſufficient Plea, and upon the whole, it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that a <hi>natural</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Vind. pag. 4. Nullis clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris Coerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, nullis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisrefraenatur.</note> 
                  <hi>Allegiance</hi> could not be <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. id.</hi> Calv. Caſe. Jura naturalia ſunt, immutabilia.</note> 
                  <hi>conſtrein'd with any force,</hi> or <hi>confin'd within any limits;</hi> it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded there, that this <hi>Allegiance</hi> is due to the King by the <hi>Law of Nature;</hi> that this <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> was long before any <hi>Municipal</hi> one of the <hi>Land,</hi> and that it is part of our <hi>own</hi> Law, and muſt be for ever <hi>immutable;</hi> and what is <hi>due</hi> by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> a <hi>Moral</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ariſtot. 5. Ethicor.</note> 
                  <hi>Heathen</hi> will not ſay can be <hi>tranſlated</hi> and <hi>transfer'd;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>Allegiance</hi> could not be deny'd to be due even
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54220:31"/>
to <hi>Tarquin,</hi> though there were then no Civil Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among the <hi>Romans</hi> that confin'd it; being before <hi>Papirius</hi> had reduc'd any into Writing; and if with the permiſſion of this moſt Polemical <hi>Divine,</hi> I may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to attempt upon his Province, thoſe inculcated Texts, of being <hi>ſubject to the higher Powers,</hi> and that, <hi>not only for fear,</hi> but for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake, ſeem to me, to have a more immediate reſpect to thoſe that are their <hi>Natural Princes;</hi> and to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which did moſt <hi>conſcientiouſly</hi> oblige them, more than any <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Municipal</hi> ones, and <hi>Civil Inſtitutions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I agree with our Author, that the point of <hi>Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lization</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 5.</note> is an Univerſal Practiſe; and the right of grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is inſeparable from Soveraign Power; ſo <note n="†" place="margin">Novel 78.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus Pius</hi> gave the <hi>Jus Civitatis</hi> to much Forreign-Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that repair'd to <hi>Rome:</hi> And though our King can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>naturalize</hi> without an Act of Parliament, (which I cannot ſee but might have been admitted, as a point of Soveraignty, it being of old allowed to his Original Anceſtors, the <hi>Roman</hi> Princes, and the denying it fixing ſomewhat of Soveraignty in the three States;) yet by our Law <hi>now,</hi> he grants Letters of Denization, which is as <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coke</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. fol. 25.</note> inſeperably aſſix'd to his Royal Perſon; yet <hi>still</hi> this being Denizen'd, or <hi>Naturaliz'd,</hi> ſhall never <hi>alienate</hi> that <hi>Allegiance</hi> you owe your <hi>Natural Prince;</hi> much leſs, <hi>protect</hi> a man from the Juſtice and reſentment of his Lawful Soveraign, for if it cannot be defended in thoſe that are <hi>born</hi> Subjects of a Forreign State, it cannot be imagin'd juſtifiable in thoſe that are <hi>Naturaliz'd;</hi> for though that puts you in a conditionas if you had been a Subject <hi>born;</hi> yet it is with relation only to perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal defects, to qualifie you for the Priviledges of a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and not to exempt you from the Obligations you owe to the Laws of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:54220:32"/>
By what has been <hi>ſaid,</hi> and ſomewhat more that I ſhall now <hi>ſay,</hi> I hope he'll retract this opinion; <hi>That</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>the</hi> Obligations of <hi>Honour,</hi> that all Soveraigns come under, to protect whom they have <hi>naturaliz'd,</hi> againſt <hi>all</hi> things but their <hi>own</hi> Juſtice, is no <hi>dark point of Law,</hi> and <hi>that it is what every Prince Practiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Obligation of <hi>Honor,</hi> (were there no Leagues to <hi>oblige</hi> them,) would on the contrary, command them not to juſtifie thoſe Crimes in <hi>Naturaliz'd</hi> Subjects, which they cannot defend in their <hi>Natives;</hi> he is ſo far from clearing this <hi>dark</hi> point of the <hi>Law,</hi> that he has made it only more <hi>obſcure;</hi> and indeed, put the Law quite <hi>out,</hi> like the <hi>Expoſitor</hi> that Writ ſo much of <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> upon his <hi>Window,</hi> till he had <hi>darken'd</hi> the whole <hi>Room:</hi> And for the practice of Princes it is plainly againſt him; ſome Preſidents there are where <hi>Protection</hi> has been much inſiſted on, as when the <hi>Venetians</hi> defended Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> againſt the Emperor <hi>Frederick;</hi> but I hope our Author will not make his Caſe that of a Soveraign Prince, when the <hi>Chalcidenſes</hi> refus'd to deliver up <hi>Nauplius</hi> to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> (as we have obſerv'd before) it was after they had found him Innocent by a formal <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al;</hi> and that obſtinacy of the <hi>Gepidae,</hi> (even by which they periſht) was not for <hi>protecting</hi> a Criminal in the Caſe of <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> and for a more Modern Inſtance; when Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> demanded <hi>Morgan,</hi> and others <note place="margin">34 <hi>Eliz. Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> fol. 25.</note> out of <hi>France,</hi> and was refus'd, it is apparent, it was upon a particular revenge the <hi>French</hi> King propos'd to himſelf by way of Retaliation; for he would not ſo much as offer her to put them to a <hi>Tryal</hi> there; which all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors do indiſputably agree in, ought to be done, and which the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Anſwer to 2d. Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</note> 
                  <hi>Dutch</hi> themſelves in his own Caſe grant to be reaſonable, though they do not put it in Execution;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54220:32"/>
for he told her plainly, <note n="†" place="margin">Si in Anglia quid machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſunt, Regem non poſſe de eiſdem cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcere. <hi>Cambd. ibid.</hi>
                  </note> that he <hi>could not</hi> (that is more truly) <hi>Would not</hi> take any <hi>Cogniſance</hi> in <hi>France</hi> for any thing they had done in <hi>England,</hi> tho' what the Queen purſu'd them for was <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> too: But when we come to <hi>Conſult</hi> the <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> we as ſoon come to ſee the <hi>Reaſon</hi> too; and that was return'd in the very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the King's, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Queen had not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note n="*" place="margin">In ſuum regnum <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomerium</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem <hi>Condaeum,</hi> &amp;c. ad miſiſſe <hi>Comd.</hi> 1585.</note> receiv'd <hi>Montgomery,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and other French <hi>Fugitives,</hi> into her <hi>Protection;</hi> and truly, if we conſider her as encouraging all the troubles of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Subjects that ſhe aſſiſted when in Arms againſt their <hi>King,</hi> in a cruel <hi>War,</hi> and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her own Articles of <hi>Peace,</hi> it cannot be expected ſhe ſhould meet with much Complement from ſuch a King, or the Common Juſtice that the Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would allow; neither would it be a rational Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from <hi>Particular</hi> Inſtances, and thoſe <hi>ill</hi> apply'd, to ſubvert a Univerſal <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Reaſon, Equity,</hi> and <hi>Right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Obligation</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> that all Soveraigns lye <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 5.</note> under, to protect, whom they Naturalize, againſt <hi>every thing,</hi> is, I think, another of his unlucky <hi>Reflections,</hi> and that upon the <hi>Honour</hi> of all Princes. I cannot tell You what ſenſe ſome ſort of People may have of this <hi>Honour,</hi> that don't uſe to ſtand much upon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>any;</hi> but <hi>Crown'd Heads,</hi> that are generally the Fountains of <hi>all</hi> that is <hi>Honourable,</hi> treat one another with more reſpect. The ſenſe that the Ancients had of this <hi>Obliging Honour,</hi> was briefly this: <hi>Dion Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> ſays, that among the many Miſchiefs that attend Governments, and cauſe all this Diſcord and Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, he counts this for one; The <hi>protecting</hi> Criminals and Offenders, that fly from one City to another;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54220:33"/>
That the next Degree to <hi>Treaſon,</hi> is to harbour and <hi>Protect Traytors;</hi> and next to the <hi>Renegadoes</hi> are thoſe that <hi>receive them.</hi> This is obſerv'd by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Grotius,</hi> Lib. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> C. 21. Quintil. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clam. 255.</note> 
                  <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> out of <hi>Quintilian,</hi> and our Authors offering to put this Principle upon the <hi>States,</hi> is by the Conſent of their <hi>own Grotius,</hi> the greateſt Libel upon their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; they might have been more <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>wiſe,</hi> than to permit a particular Perſon's Crimes to Be paum'd upon them, for an Intereſt of State, and a ſingle man's Offence, (that can hardly be ſaid to be a <hi>Subject)</hi> to make their Government ſuffer by a <hi>national</hi> Imputation<hi>:</hi> And thus <hi>Aeſchines,</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> declares, in his Treaty with K. <hi>Philip,</hi> for the Peace of <hi>Greece, That the Malefactors themſelves, and not their Cities, ſhould ſuffer for their faults;</hi> which nothing but the <hi>puniſhing</hi> or <hi>delivery</hi> of the Criminals can excuſe; and for this reaſon the <hi>Cerites</hi> preſently left it to the choice of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which they would have? And as I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd above, I thought the <hi>States,</hi> would have been more <hi>truly honourable,</hi> than to entertain ſuch Maxims of Government for a point of <hi>Honour,</hi> and that the Wiſe Adminiſtrations they have many times ſhewn, would not have permitted them to receive it, as a point of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> or <hi>Policy,</hi> and that from an Inſtance, that theſe their moſt Learned Stateſman that ever their Country afforded, (or indeed any other) has applied to the Caſe, <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and that is <hi>Baſilius</hi>'s ſending to <hi>Coſroe</hi>'s, for one that was his <hi>own</hi> Subject; but being declared a <hi>Rebel</hi> and a <hi>Fugitive,</hi> tells him, <hi>he hoped he would be ſo prudent, as not,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Somewhat to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſaid the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they ſent for <hi>Jugur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ba.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>by Protecting him, to countenance ſuch a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent againſt himſelf.</hi> And indeed, this has been in this laſt Age, the real occaſion of debauching it into our Author's degenerate Principle of <hi>Honour,</hi> when by the firſt Breach upon its Purity, other Princes were diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54220:33"/>
from thoſe <hi>Obligations</hi> that they had to it, and forc'd by a moſt prepoſterous piece of Gallantry, to recede from the very Rules of <hi>Real Honour,</hi> for fear of putting up of Injuries, and failing <hi>of</hi> the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of a glorious and <hi>honourable</hi> Revenge: And in this ſenſe indeed I can ſubmit to the Saying of our Author, That <hi>it is practiſed by all Princes as often as there is ſuch</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>occaſion for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore I can further agree with him, that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 5.</note> the <hi>States</hi> are no further bound by it to the <hi>King,</hi> then the <hi>King</hi> is bound by it to the <hi>States,</hi> unleſs we could fancy a Deeper Obligation in a Monarch to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Rules of right <hi>Honour</hi> from his Royal Blood, than can be expected from their mixt Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, in a Democracy; and this <hi>Mutual Obligation,</hi> as appears from the repeated Arguments of Hiſtory, Reaſon, and Law, is as Reciprocally <hi>obliging,</hi> where there are no Leagues or Articles to make it more <hi>bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> but where there are, it only ſuperſedes all doubt, and makes it almoſt a <hi>Forgery</hi> to diſpute it: And ſhould a <hi>Dutch-man naturaliz'd</hi> (as he puts it in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Caſe) be demanded for ſo high an offence as <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> His Majeſty might doubtleſs deliver him up, or Puniſh him, if convicted, upon a legal Trial of his Peers, and that by the Laws of all Nations, were it not ſpecify'd in any particular League; for as it is prov'd before from all the Topicks of Argument, that Law or Logick, Hiſtory or Fact can afford, that this <hi>Naturalization</hi> being but at beſt an <hi>Acquir'd Allegiance,</hi> cannot eradicate that <hi>natural</hi> one that is immutable: it priviledges them only in things that reſpect their <hi>private perſons,</hi> and not againſt the <hi>Publick Relation</hi> they retain to their Country; it cannot <hi>legitimate</hi> him, if he be there <hi>born</hi> in it, a <hi>Baſtard,</hi> and can no
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54220:34"/>
more make him a <hi>good Subject,</hi> if he be fled from it for a <hi>Rebel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cuſtom and Right of our being <hi>tryed here, per Pares,</hi> is with ſubmiſſion, nothing to the purpoſe; for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ibid. p. 5.</note> in Leagues and Alliances, we being to be guided and governed by the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> if ſuch a Criminal be <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered</hi> up, it ſuperſedes his <hi>Tryal;</hi> and if he be <hi>try'd</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our <hi>Common,</hi> it prevents his <hi>Delivery;</hi> and if it be for ſuch Crimes as are puniſhable by the Laws of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> (as <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>renouncing natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Allegiance</hi> were ever reputed;) it may be <hi>try'd</hi> by the <hi>Imperial Law,</hi> as well as the <hi>Municipal</hi> ones of any Land. Theſe are Tranſactions of <hi>States,</hi> and Meaſures of <hi>Government,</hi> that muſt no more be confin'd to our <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> than is the <hi>ſoveraign Power</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> (and upon which both of thoſe commonly depend;) but our unfortunate Author con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues only in this, his <hi>unlucky</hi> touches, ſo uſual againſt his own Intereſt; for if he's an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> (which in this Caſe, out of Favour we'll grant him leave to fancy himſelf) he ought to be <hi>try'd</hi> by his <hi>Peers,</hi> and the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of their Country, not admitting ſuch a ſort of Proceſs; the Evidence being tranſmitted hence by way of Memorial or Proof, it would only give <hi>our</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a juſter Reaſon to demand him, and <hi>theirs</hi> from the peculiar Proceedings of our <hi>Municipal</hi> Law, to think, they cannot <hi>do him full and ſpeedy Juſtice in the Court of</hi> Holland. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> p. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And in Matters of ſuch mighty moment, as the Concord and Amity of Crowns, Leagues, and Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of Princes, and States, private Perſons may lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an <hi>Obligation</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> and Honeſty, and perhaps Piety too, that may not be very pleaſing to ſuch an Offender; that is, to make a <hi>voluntary Dedition</hi> of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:54220:34"/>
themſelves, to prevent any dangerous Conteſts, and <hi>publick</hi> Calamities that might enſue, or at leaſt to retire out of thoſe Territories, where an obſtinate Continuance may create an unhappy Diſturbance: This might be counted a more <hi>becoming Prudence,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of an <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>unbecoming fear.</hi> This, ſome Caſuiſts have thought the Duty even of the moſt <hi>innocent</hi> Perſons, and is only more obliging upon thoſe that lye under the Suſpicion of the greateſt <hi>Guilt.</hi> This, though he be not bound to it by <hi>Right,</hi> yet he may be oblig'd in <hi>Charity;</hi> and thoſe which are no Acts of Juſtice, yet may be done out of Piety and Love, which as they cannot be performed without <hi>Praiſes,</hi> ſo they cannot well be <hi>Omitted</hi> without <hi>blame:</hi> And 'tis our Author's pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Affectation, that with <note n="†" place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>relation to the Publick,</hi> he is <hi>free from the very fault of Omiſſion:</hi> but he is too apt to <hi>value</hi> himſelf upon his Excellencies, and even ſuch as can't be well call'd his own, though the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Advantage he has, and that is, the being <hi>protected</hi> againſt the Reſentments of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> was of ſuch an inconſiderable <hi>value,</hi> as hardly to be <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> worth the asking. Our Author might have forſook the Country, as tender as he is of the <hi>Rights</hi> of it; which would have remain'd perhaps more <hi>unviolated</hi> than ſome Princes may think, thoſe of all <hi>Nations</hi> are in his <hi>protection;</hi> I know, the perſwading ſuch an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro to a <hi>voluntary retirement,</hi> is much ſuch another Task that an Ingenuous perſon undertook to perſwade our Uſurper to <hi>Hang himſelf;</hi> but as that <hi>killing</hi> might have been indeed no <hi>Murder,</hi> and been better juſtify'd than any of the Caſes and Arguments of Dr. <hi>Don</hi> to perſwade us to that unpleaſant diverſion of a <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> in his Learned Treatiſe of <hi>Suicidium, viz.</hi> from the great Obligation that Tyrant would have laid upon his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54220:35"/>
Country; ſo I humbly conceive, both the Countrys, to which our Amphibious Subject does owe an Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, had been better oblig'd, had he, what he ſo ſcorns, <hi>withdrawn of his own accord,</hi> it had ſuperſeded a <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> Conteſt, about a <hi>private</hi> perſon; who as high as he is, that we are ſo <hi>below</hi> his Anſwer, is really, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> his <hi>value</hi> and <hi>vanity,</hi> is more <hi>turbulent</hi> to <hi>both</hi> States, than in <hi>either</hi> of them <hi>conſiderable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Expedient was neither ridiculous, as perhaps, it would have <hi>appear'd</hi> to our Author, nor Impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as from ſome Inſtances ſhall <hi>appear;</hi> ſo <hi>Pactyes,</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> as is recorded in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> when he was not <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd</hi> up by the <hi>Cymaei,</hi> of his own accord, for an Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for the Peace of both States, fled to <hi>Mytelene;</hi> and <hi>Phocion</hi> to his Friend <hi>Nicocles,</hi> went a little further, who thought, that leaſt things ſhould come to an extremity, if <hi>Alexander</hi> demanded him, he ought to <hi>deliver</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up. It was the ſaying of a Noble <hi>Roman,</hi> that if his Enemy had ſurrounded him at Sea, and threatned a ſinking of the Ship, if he were not <hi>deliver'd</hi> up, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his <hi>Friends</hi> from danger, he ought to Sacrifice himſelf to the reſentments of his <hi>Enemy,</hi> or the mercy of the Sea; and (without the help of <hi>Horace)</hi> the Metaphor of the <hi>Veſſel,</hi> may be fitted to Kingdoms and <hi>Common-wealths,</hi> when Hiſtory has here told us, how much of misfortune has befallen Principalities, from theſe unhappy differences about Mean and Private men, but though our Author <hi>does</hi> ſo ſwagger it out with his Excellencies, and Sublimes, his <hi>ſtoutneſs,</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of his <hi>Poſt;</hi> ſuch Application to the preſent Caſe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> p. 5.</note> would I hop'd once have been for ever ſuperſeded from the prudent Adminiſtrations of two ſuch flouriſhing Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and the Publick <hi>Peace</hi> never have been inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, upon the account of a Man, <hi>that is too</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:54220:35"/>
                  <hi>mean for an Article of War,</hi> and who, if His Majeſty's Honour had not been ſo highly <hi>invaded</hi> from the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion his Libellous Defamations have met with, is as much <hi>below</hi> a <hi>Prince's Reſentment,</hi> as he is <hi>beneath</hi> the <hi>Protection</hi> of a <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Caſe</hi> of the French <hi>Fugitives,</hi> who are receiv'd <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Id. p. 5.</note> here, and which by the greateſt abuſe in the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he would make to be his <hi>own,</hi> is, as I juſt touch'd upon before, quite foreign to his purpoſe: <hi>They</hi> indeed deſerve <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>protection,</hi> when ſuch Offenders merit as much <hi>Puniſhment; Their</hi> Crimes are truly like thoſe of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> only the Religion they Profeſs; and <hi>They</hi> are but ill us'd, when Criminals that are proſecuted for High Treaſon againſt their Prince, draw ſuch unlucky <hi>Parallels,</hi> and make a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> p. 5.</note> Proſecution of the higheſt <hi>Offender,</hi> to be the ſame with a terrible Perſecution they ſuffer for no <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> after all his rude Reflections, ought to return him Thanks for making <hi>Hereſie</hi> to be <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> too; thoſe Crimes, as has been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſhewn, were never Tolerated, never <hi>protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> nor ever can be in any Kingdom or State, neither in <hi>naturaliz'd</hi> Subjects or <hi>Natives,</hi> againſt <hi>foreign</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces no more than againſt themſelves at <hi>home;</hi> whereas * <hi>Athens,</hi> and all Cities, have been ever reputed San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaries for the <note n="*" place="margin">It was for ſuch they ſet up there their <hi>Ara Miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae,</hi> ſays <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponius.</hi>
                  </note> Perſecuted and Afflicted; and <hi>France</hi> it ſelf cannot cumplain, as we ſee it neither does, againſt ſuch a Charitable Reception, ſince their own King <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> receiv'd and <hi>protected</hi> all thoſe that fled to him out of <hi>Normandy</hi> for a <hi>Perſecution:</hi> And the Emperor <hi>Ludovicus Pius</hi> did the ſame to thoſe that for the like fled to him from <hi>Rome;</hi> as they may ſee by a <note n="*" place="margin">An. 817.</note> Decree of his in their own <note n="†" place="margin">Tom. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Gallican</hi> Councils: So that our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>Libels</hi> them as much when he applies their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> as he <hi>belys</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> when he ſays he is <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>vid.</hi> 1ſt. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial.</note> 
                  <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:54220:36"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>ANd now to ſumm up this conteſted Point for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of His Majeſty, and that of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; both which are not a little concern'd in the late Tranſactions that have paſt between us and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, both with relation to the Caſe of this Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Author, and ſome other of his Subjects which comes much to the ſame, out of an humble deference to thoſe that were in Alliance with <hi>their</hi> State; He might leſs have preſum'd to cenſure, and reflect on <hi>ours;</hi> but our Author made the more bold to <hi>Invade</hi> the King firſt with his <hi>Libels,</hi> to facilitate that <hi>Invaſion</hi> he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd with <hi>force</hi> and <hi>Arms;</hi> being adopted into the <hi>Treachery</hi> of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> (which in him was <hi>Treaſon)</hi> he might more confidently flouriſh with his <hi>Pen,</hi> when he ſaw the Sword a drawing: And ſince this turbulent and pernicious <hi>Pen,</hi> which from its Excellency and Applauſe, is only qualify'd for to do the more of miſchief, has met with ſo much of Permiſſion, as to juſtifie it ſelf againſt ſo many ſeveral Memorials of the King of Great <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> and that in a Paper in which I am my ſelf ſo much concern'd, where (if he will not take it for <hi>foul Language</hi> too) I muſt thank him for <hi>abuſing</hi> me in ſo good Company as the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and this, with prefixing the Glorious <hi>Fiocco</hi> of his renowned Name, to the <hi>Front</hi> and <hi>Finis</hi> of as confident a piece, to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54220:36"/>
let the World know he would no longer be <hi>Incognito,</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> too, that they ought to take notice of it; ſince all this appears in <hi>Holland,</hi> as open as with us any of our <hi>Imprimaturs,</hi> I hope I need not Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gize <hi>much,</hi> for a <hi>little</hi> Liberty that I take, and that the Author of the <hi>Parliamentum Pacificum,</hi> ought no more to be <hi>puniſht</hi> at the Inſtance of Mr. <hi>F.</hi> only for having made but a <hi>modeſt Reflection</hi> upon the Paper of a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> then was the Author of ſo many Virulent ones (upon the <hi>Memorial</hi> of His Majeſty ſolemnly preſented;) for the defaming of his Government; and it is a real Maxime, even among the Laws of Nations, that the defenſive ſide has alway the moſt to ſay in its juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that little remark that I firſt paſt upon ſome of his Papers, (his very perſon being unknown to me) was really the reſult of thoſe many Malicious Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">Six Papers.</note> he had made long before, upon the very perſon of His Majeſty, and the Adminiſtration of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and theſe publickly diſpers'd, as I was well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, for the depraving of the Minds of the King's Subjects abroad, and tranſlated too into other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for the making the King and his Miniſters more univerſally odious, and Contemptible to Forreigners themſelves: And ſent us over here for a <hi>pack</hi> of Preſents, that like the <hi>Box</hi> of <hi>Pandora,</hi> when open'd by <hi>Epime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> contain'd only <hi>all kind of Evils,</hi> for the infecting us with the worſt of <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Calamities</hi> that can befall a Kingdom; the <hi>Diſtruſt</hi> of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and the Diſcontent of the <hi>People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Queſtion that does really ariſe from theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, is ſhortly this; <hi>How much His Majeſty was concern'd to repreſent this to that Government under which theſe His Defamations were made? And how far it</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:54220:37"/>
                  <hi>affected that Government, in which He made theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. The Obligation of <hi>Honour</hi> that all Soveraigns <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Pag. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>come</hi> under, is of great weight and <hi>Conſideration</hi> with our Author, when it muſt oblig'd them to <hi>protect</hi> all ſort of <hi>Criminals,</hi> and how comes it to be ſo <hi>inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> when ſome ſatisfaction is ſought for, even for the greateſt <hi>Crime, High Treaſon,</hi> and the <hi>higheſt</hi> indignity: I confeſs, in Countrys where more profitable Maxims ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, it is a good Aphoriſm, that <hi>he is the Moſt Honourable, that has Got moſt,</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> as well as <hi>Godlineſs</hi> with ſome People, may be <hi>great gain;</hi> but this is not the Caſe with <hi>Crown'd Heads,</hi> and a Power <hi>truly Soveraign,</hi> they are oblig'd to the moſt tender <hi>regard</hi> of their <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and Dignity, and the leaſt Violation of it <hi>unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded</hi> and neglected, is a <hi>stain</hi> upon their very <hi>Purple;</hi> and this has been formerly confeſs'd by the readineſs of thoſe people, to give ſatisfaction to the leaſt reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that perhaps are not ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward now to give a ſatisfactory anſwer to the demand and Memorial of His Majeſty; the difference lying on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this, that they were then the <hi>Diſtreſſed States,</hi> and now the <hi>High, and Mighty</hi> ones.</p>
               <p>The Reputation of a Prince does ſo far, I confeſs, (if we may with the Poet, compare great things with ſmall) Symbolize with that of the meaner ſort, and the <hi>Credit</hi> of a Merchant, (and which I know with ſuch a <hi>Trading People,</hi> muſt be mightily valued and eſteem'd) that the ſtock of his <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Wealth,</hi> his intereſt in his Subjects, his ſtrength at <hi>Sea,</hi> and his Forces at <hi>Land,</hi> like the others <hi>eſtate;</hi> his <hi>Bank,</hi> his <hi>Effects,</hi> his <hi>Eſteem,</hi> are for the ſupport of his Dignity, to be advanced rather by Fame and Report, even beyond
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54220:37"/>
the real Proportion that they bear, and then how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly muſt He be dealt withal; when by ſlander, and reproach, he ſhall be repreſented <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Six Papers.</note> 
                  <hi>oppreſſing</hi> of his Subjects, <hi>contemptible</hi> to his <hi>Neighbours;</hi> his <hi>Forces vilify'd,</hi> and his <hi>Affairs perplext;</hi> and we all know a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> Fam'd, only for a repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Bank, that carries, perhaps, and bears up <note n="*" place="margin">Quod ſi Reſpub. Veneta; Regibus aequalem dignitatem ſibi aſcribit, quanto meliori Jure Faederatum Belgium. Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius diſſertat. Hiſt. And we know an Author that ſtyles them <hi>Regum Domini.</hi>
                  </note> it's beſt reputation in the World upon <hi>this very</hi> Bottom; and in all their Civil Actions among themſelves, inſiſt mightily for reparation, where any <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> Credit is leſſen'd; or from For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign <hi>States</hi> where it is <hi>publickly</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valu'd; and if this be their <hi>Common Law,</hi> I am ſure their <hi>Civilians</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Etiam ſtant Reges &amp; Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſuo nomine &amp; Exiſtimatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne; quare nomen augeri opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, &amp; Culpa fuerit relaxare vindictam. Alber. Gentil. de jure. Bell. Lib. 1. c. 28.</note> teach Princes too as good a Leſſon, that <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> ſtand upon their <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem;</hi> and that this <hi>Fame</hi> of theirs is therefore to be <hi>defended;</hi> and that it would be a Crime in them to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give,</hi> or <hi>forget</hi> to <hi>vindicate</hi> it; and all Caſuiſtical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (if we may tell our Author any thing that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains to his own Profeſſion) do reſolve, that Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes, cannot remit thoſe Indignities that are done to themſelves, ſo ſoon as private Perſons the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries that are offer'd them; becauſe their Subjects have a ſhare in the Affronts that are offer'd to the Soveraign, which if he ſhould put up, (it being an Injury to the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick)</hi> ſuch a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> would indeed be only <hi>void</hi> and <hi>invalid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had the <hi>Memorials</hi> of His Majeſty, which this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecter here has repreſented ſo <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid,</hi> Vind. Pag. 3.4,</note> 
                  <hi>ridiculous,</hi> ſo <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> and <hi>inſignificant,</hi> and this with the Publick <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primatur</hi> of his Pompous Name, been only for Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54220:38"/>
done his Subjects, his Subjects could have more honeſtly acquieſc'd, and leſs reſented a Reparation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd, and thoſe, from the <hi>Butcheries</hi> at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> to the <hi>Buſineſs</hi> of <hi>Bantam,</hi> might all have been more hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely forgot; but where their <hi>Prince</hi> himſelf, and his <hi>Fame,</hi> by the moſt virulent Pen, and a <hi>Fugitive</hi>'s too, is Perſecuted and traduc'd, and that openly, by an Author that ſcorns to be Anonimous; this cannot be ſo ſoon put up at <hi>home,</hi> and requires a more ſignal Reparation from <hi>abroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus it moſt pertinently comes now before us in the next place to conſider, how far a Kingdom or a Common-wealth is affected, (from the general Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Caſuiſts, Stateſmen, and Hiſtorians) by thoſe very Miſdemeanours, which againſt a foreign State, their Subjects, and then <hi>a fortiori,</hi> any <hi>Fugitives</hi> may commit. In the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Our Anſwer to the 1ſt part of Dr. <hi>B</hi>'s Refl.</note> former Treatiſe it ſo fell in our way, that the touching upon it could not be well avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but even there it was referr'd to be more fully manifeſted in this more proper place, and which ſhall here be as faithfully performed.</p>
               <p>It is agreed then by all thoſe Writers, That all <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Injuries</hi> become <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>national</hi> ones, where any <hi>Kingdom</hi> or <hi>Nation</hi> does <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Albert. Gentil. id. L. 1. C. 18,</note> neglect to puniſh them in their own native Subjects, or make ſatisfaction to the Party injur'd; What then muſt be inferr'd, where the Injury has been offer'd to His Sacred Majeſty, his Publick Miniſters, and this from a <hi>born</hi> Subject of his <hi>own,</hi> and ſubjected only to them from a Naturalizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>acquir'd?</hi> And <note n="†" place="margin">De Jure Bell. l. 3. c. 20. §. 40.</note> 
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf carries it ſo high, that even in things done contrary to <hi>friendſhip,</hi> there ſhall be imply'd a Violation of <hi>Peace,</hi> and certainly the permiſſion of any Indignity, or connivance the leaſt Contumely that has occaſion'd ſo much <hi>War,</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:54220:38"/>
muſt be accounted an <hi>unfriendly</hi> Act: They further ſay, that a Government which does not prevent by expreſs Commands, ſuch Reflexions as our Author has made on their Friends and Allys, is lookt upon it ſelf, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in their making; for defect of ſuch a Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note n="*" place="margin">Qui non Prohibent <hi>Tenentur.</hi> Si Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas negligit illud factum emendare illaqueat ipſa ſe. Alber. Gent. Lib. 1. c. 21.</note>: They ſay, that a Community that neglects to make amends for ſuch a Fact, involves it ſelf in the guilt of it; and it is ſaid by the Celebrated <hi>Agapetus</hi> in the Works of a Prince, the Standard of all <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Royal Equity;</hi> that in ſuch Caſes, it is the ſame Crime not to <note n="*" place="margin">Juſtinian: pareſt delinquere &amp; delinquentes non prohibere.</note> 
                  <hi>prohibit</hi> the <hi>Offences of others,</hi> and your ſelf to be the <hi>Offending</hi> Perſon.</p>
               <p>Our own Ornament of the Civil Law, and the late <note place="margin">Zouchaeus de Jure faeciali. Part. 2. Sect. 5. Quaeſt. Utrum injuriae a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditis illatae; principem vel populum affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant.</note> Celebrated Profeſſor of it at <hi>Oxford,</hi> has ſufficiently diſcuſt this Caſe, and ſettl'd it too, in ſhewing <hi>how the injuries that are offer'd, only by private Subjects, can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Prince and People;</hi> but becauſe ſuch <hi>Partial</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority may not obtain with <hi>ſtrangers;</hi> and our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors <hi>tranſlated Allegiance,</hi> may have exempted him from giving that Credit to thoſe that could once have been call'd his <hi>Countrymen;</hi> let us ſee what <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf ſays, into whoſe <hi>Country</hi> he is adopted.</p>
               <p>It is generally held, (as he confeſſes) that no <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of Men is anſwerable for the faults of any <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> perſons, and that gives occaſion to the conſtant Clauſe in Leagues, <hi>de Publico Conſilio,</hi> and this was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd of by <hi>Livy,</hi> as an Excuſe for the <hi>Locrians</hi> in the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to the <hi>Rhodians</hi> alſo in the ſame Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; and to the <hi>Vejentes,</hi> pleading their Ignorance of their Subjects having aſſiſted the <hi>Romans</hi> Enemies; but all this is no warrantable excuſe to any Civil Society,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54220:39"/>
Principality, or Common-wealths, where any Act of Omiſſion can be prov'd in the <hi>Publick,</hi> that contributed to the promoting, or permitting any <hi>Private</hi> Man's offence: St. <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> whom <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Grot. de jure Bell, L. 2. c. 21. S. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> there Cites; (and our Reverend Author cannot reject a name ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend) has the beſt excuſe that comes neareſt to this Caſe, and argues thus, <hi>That it was not the common Crime of the City (or Community) but only of ſome Strangers,</hi> and <hi>Forreigners, that do all things rather raſhly, inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and out of ignorance of the Laws:</hi> But even this is not excuſable, where ſuch a City, or Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhall connive at any <hi>Fugitives,</hi> or <hi>Forreigners, committing</hi> ſuch a Crime, who muſt there, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the Guilt by <hi>Imputation,</hi> for not having hinder'd it <hi>before</hi> it was <hi>committed;</hi> to this does he apply the Arguments of <hi>Cicero</hi> againſt <hi>Piſo,</hi> of a Conſul that permits others to offend; of the ſaying of <hi>Salvian, That he that has a power to prohibit an ill Act, and omits it, does in effect command it;</hi> and that Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes who are able to <hi>prohibit</hi> Crimes, approve them, if they <hi>permit</hi> them to be done, and who are bound to take care that <hi>others</hi> offend not: And another of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf, <hi>That he that does not in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes reſiſt and oppoſe, ſeems to give his conſent;</hi> and this being a piece of <hi>Divinity,</hi> that interferes with the <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks;</hi> (as <hi>Grotius</hi> obſerves) our Author, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. pag. 7.</note> I hope, will pardon this little Digreſſion out of the <hi>Province</hi> he has put upon me: And for the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Fabian</hi> Laws, <hi>of Maſters being puniſht for the permiſſion of their Servants Faults; Parents for their Childrens, knowing</hi> of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment,</hi> and being <hi>able</hi> to <hi>restrain</hi> it, (both which are too apparent in this Conteſted point) all theſe Caſes ariſing only from Natural Equity, or Religious Rules, and Obſervances, are all by their <hi>own</hi> Stateſman, and a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Grotius <hi>ut Supra.</hi>
                  </note> moſt Learned one too, apply'd by a parity of reaſon to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54220:39"/>
                  <hi>Princes,</hi> and their <hi>Subjects,</hi> their <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> or their <hi>Common-wealths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>David</hi> in the buſineſs of <hi>Rabbah,</hi> and the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites,</hi> made it the Crime of their City, for not <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring</hi> thoſe Indignities done him by ſome their Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. And if we may venture once more upon our Authors <hi>Province,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in his Oration involves <note place="margin">De Stat. Orat. 1.</note> all the Inhabitants of <hi>Antioch,</hi> in the Crimes of the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> becauſe though committed only by a few, it was not puniſht by the Community, which general Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (he ſays) could have been avoided, had the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders been expelled the City: After ſo <hi>Sacred</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it would be ſuperfluous to add any Examples from ſuch Hiſtory as is call'd <hi>prophane;</hi> but Politicks (as our Author ſays) being more our <hi>peculiar Province,</hi> we may expatiate a little further upon ſome Preſidents drawn from the Practiſe of the Ancient Governments among the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> as not improper for this place; ſeeing the moſt modern Conſtitutions, and moſt renowned <hi>States,</hi> and <hi>Republicks,</hi> do commonly take their Meaſures from them. Thus the <hi>Grecian</hi> Princes were Condemn'd for not delivering up of their <hi>Iphigenia;</hi> and <hi>Polybius</hi> blames the <hi>Aetolians</hi> mightily, who while they would not willingly appear Enemys to <hi>Philip,</hi> yet ſuffer'd ſome of their Subjects openly to act againſt him, and when the Queen of the <hi>Illyrians</hi> would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd her ſelf to the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Depraeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſome of her Subjects were done without her Knowledge, or Approbation; ſhe was anſwer'd, that no Prince could plead <hi>ignorance,</hi> of what was frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and <hi>publickly</hi> done; and that ſhe was anſwerable, for not <hi>forbidding</hi> that <hi>injury</hi> to her Allies, which ſhe muſt be preſum'd to <hi>know.</hi> Our Authors moſt Injurious Reflections on the King and his Government, have been
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54220:40"/>
repeated, often <hi>Publiſht,</hi> and <hi>openly</hi> own'd; ſo that there is but <hi>little need</hi> of that <hi>proof</hi> that may be deſir'd, and I wiſh there were <hi>leſs</hi> too, for theſe Unhappy Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that tell us, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals.</note> 
                  <hi>That it is ſuch an agreeable thing to nature,</hi> That he who is born free, ſhould have the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſetling himſelf, whereſoever he ſhall think it moſt advantageous for him, I fear, will find too, from what has been here ſaid, that the Laws of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> (as <hi>agreable</hi> as they repreſent them) are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the <hi>transferring</hi> all <hi>Allegiance,</hi> after a <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on introduc'd;</hi> I confeſs, ſuch a Notion is <hi>agreable</hi> to Nature, had we no other <hi>Common-wealth</hi> but that of Mr. <hi>Hobs;</hi> and there would be no need of inſiſting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Articles of <hi>Peace,</hi> when we were bound to be in no other <hi>State</hi> but that of <hi>War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">De Jure Bell. L. 2. c. 5. Sect. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf, upon this point of <hi>natural Liberty,</hi> though he gives it as great a Latitude as any of his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen</hi> can deſire, cannot extend it beyond the Reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of all <hi>Municipal</hi> Laws, and therefore grants, that in ſome Countrys it is not lawful to <hi>renounce</hi> their <hi>Nation,</hi> or <hi>forſake</hi> their <hi>City;</hi> and mentions for an Example, that of <hi>Moſco;</hi> and though by the late Laws among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> any Citizen might remove his Habitation to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther City, yet was he ſtill oblig'd to execute ſuch Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as ſhould be impos'd on him where he <hi>first</hi> dwelt; &amp; a ſpecial Proviſo by thoſe Laws, to compel him to pay his wonted Contributions; neither were they to depart out of all their Territories without leave; but even that Author when he has made this <hi>Natural Liberty</hi> to be much reſtrain'd by <hi>Municipal Law;</hi> concludes, that it is not ſo <hi>agreable,</hi> even to <hi>Nature,</hi> and that no <hi>number,</hi> or great Companys of Subjects, can be allow'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert their Country, though ſome <hi>particular</hi> Perſons may,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54220:40"/>
and to Cap our Authors Allegory, on the <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> of the <note n="*" place="margin">Reflect. 1 part, p. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Dutch Dikes,</hi> and the difference of <hi>pulling of a flower,</hi> and <hi>breaking an Hedge;</hi> this Author ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to this Caſe too, that it is <hi>one thing to draw water out of a River, and another thing to turn the Courſe of it:</hi> So that although this <hi>Tranſlated Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Naturalization,</hi> were ſo <hi>agreeable</hi> to <hi>Nature</hi> in the <hi>particular</hi> Perſon of Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> yet from the reſolution of this their own Lawyer and moſt excellent States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, it is the moſt <hi>diſagreeable</hi> thing in the World, to extend it to ſo many <hi>Regiments,</hi> and <hi>whole Companies;</hi> for as he wiſely concludes from the neceſſity of the end, (which by all moral Maxims muſt create a right;) by the ſame Parity of Reaſon, ſuch an unbounded Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſettling one's ſelf, might be extended to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Majority, even to the Diſſolution of the whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Society: And to this I might add, That the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that ought to have been had (upon ſome <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> The Dutch Anſw. to the King's Memorial.</note> 
                  <hi>Reſolutions</hi> ſome People have of late given) of Our Subjects that were demanded, being all <hi>Souldiers,</hi> as well as ſuch a number of <hi>People,</hi> did make ſuch a <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Naturalization</hi> more <hi>diſagreeable</hi> to <hi>Nature;</hi> ſince <hi>Souldiers</hi> muſt be <hi>naturally</hi> ſuppos'd, and that in <hi>Peace</hi> as well as <hi>War,</hi> to be more immediately requiſite to the Conſervation of a Government, than a ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe Profeſſion it is not to bear <hi>Arms;</hi> or only a <hi>particular</hi> Champion at the <hi>Pen,</hi> that under the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> does only diſturb the State, and would make the Church it ſelf too, truly <hi>Militant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo highly Injurious has this aſſuming the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of another Prince been ever reſented, eſpecially when in <hi>Great Bodies,</hi> and that aggravated when the Perſons were <hi>Military men,</hi> that <hi>Zonoras</hi> diſcourſing of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54220:41"/>
King <hi>Lazus,</hi> who had Revolted from the <hi>Perſians</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> makes it a Juſt Cauſe of War, between thoſe <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Perſians,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> General had drawn over unto himſelf the Subjects of the King of <hi>Perſia.</hi> This is granted too by the Learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> and he inſiſts <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 2. c. 5. ſect. 24. Lib. 3. c. 20. ſect. 41.</note> ſeveral times upon the ſame Paſſage, for a Preſident. His Majeſty's <hi>Memorial</hi> almoſt in the ſame words expreſſes the Saying of <hi>Sabinus,</hi> That though every man has this <hi>natural Liberty,</hi> or the power to make himſelf a Member of what City he pleaſes, yet he cannot of the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Dominion,</hi> after another has been introduced; and therefore <hi>Grotins</hi> adds the authority of <hi>Paulus,</hi> That by the Laws of the <hi>Romans,</hi> all <hi>Fugitive</hi> Servants were liable to the right of <hi>Reception,</hi> whom their Maſters can <hi>over</hi> claim, and they muſt ſtill remain their Servants, and that it is the greateſt Injury to <hi>detain</hi> them from their <hi>Service:</hi> And certainly then the Soveraign will have as great a Right to that of his Subjects. So that it is indeed ſomewhat to be admired, to ſee ſo lately the Laws of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> alleadg'd to Juſtifie a Matter to which they <hi>both</hi> are ſo plainly repugnant, and by thoſe very People, againſt whom their own moſt applauded Author is the beſt of Advocates, and who plainly <note place="margin">Lib. 3. c. 9. ſect. 11.</note> tells us too, in another place, <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. lib. 3. c. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>That it is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to receive ſuch as are bound either by Oath or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to perform any Service or Duty to another Prince;</hi> and ſince their Lawyers <hi>tell them</hi> ſo, it will not be Improper to look a little into <hi>our</hi> Law, and ſee what that <hi>tells us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Stat. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <note n="*" place="margin">11 H. 7. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi>'s Caſe, <hi>Jac.</hi> 1.</note> and the Reſolution given in K. <hi>J.</hi> 1. it is Plain, the King of <hi>England</hi> cannot be depriv'd of the Service of any of his Subjects, who are bound to ſerve him in <hi>Peace</hi> as well as <hi>War,</hi> both
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54220:41"/>
                  <hi>within</hi> the Kingdom and <hi>without,</hi> that <hi>natural Allegiance</hi> is <hi>unalterable</hi> and <hi>unſeparable,</hi> whatever <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Tranſlation</hi> Some may pretend to; and by a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Act of Parliament of K. <hi>James,</hi> (as upon another oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion was before obſerv'd) the <hi>Serving of Foreign</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3 <hi>Jac.</hi> c. 5. 3d. Inſt. c. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Princes</hi> with a <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> is particularly provided againſt by the requiring an <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> before they go over, and making it <hi>Felony</hi> to go <hi>without:</hi> And, What can be imply'd from this, but their Obligation to <hi>return</hi> when call'd and <hi>commanded?</hi> And this is extended by the Comment of my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> to a going over <hi>without</hi> ſerving, or to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick</hi> Service as well as <hi>Military:</hi> The whole Deſign of the Statute ſeems directed more eſpecially againſt Souldiers entring into Foreign Service, and by a more particular Branch of it, binds them <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Form of the Obligat.</note> not only to take their Oath of Obedience, but alſo to give two ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Sureties: And it was a Caſe once that came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Queſtion, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dyer</hi> 298.</note> Whither the going only to live out of the Kingdom, without Leave, were not a Contempt, and an Offence puniſhable, and to be conſtrued as a Deſire to withdraw his due <hi>Obedience?</hi> And 'tis plain, that Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (whoſe Memory the States ought to Reverence, as well as our Author) after She had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Leave of Abſence in a <hi>Foreign Service,</hi> for ſome Years, upon a Refuſal to return on the ſending her Privy Seal, that Commanded it upon their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> fol. 375. B.</note> proceeded againſt the Perſons as <hi>Fugitives,</hi> ſeizes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcates, and ſells their Eſtates and Inheritance.</p>
               <p>If theſe then are the Laws of <hi>England;</hi> if this has been reſolv'd in the Reign of a Princeſs, whoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings no Proteſtants will diſpute, His Majeſty's En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy might well declare, <hi>The King could Recall His</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> the King's Men orial.</note> 
                  <hi>Subjects by his Royal Proclamation, or his Letters of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:54220:42"/>
                  <hi>Seal,</hi> and that they were bound to Obey thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders upon <hi>very ſevere penaltys;</hi> and the <hi>Memorials</hi> of the Marquiſs may, with the Wiſer part of the World be thought to contain a great deal of ſenſe and reaſon, notwithſtanding that our Author has endeavour'd to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vindic. p. 3. 4.</note> repreſent moſt of them ſo abſurd and ridiculous.</p>
               <p>But then all Doubt is excluded and out of doors by a <hi>general</hi> conſent and accord of <hi>all</hi> Stateſmen; and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ibid. <hi>ut Supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> in <hi>particular,</hi> where it is decided by thoſe Obligations that ariſe from <hi>Articles, Contracts,</hi> and <hi>Agreements;</hi> and to <hi>this,</hi> thoſe that have conteſted it ſo much, by their own Conſent and Reſolution are bound, and have concluded themſelves; ſo that ſince a ſolemn <hi>Capitulation</hi> has been produc'd, and which we need not inſiſt on to make out, ſince ſo publickly known: The Proceedings of His Majeſty's Miniſter of State, (which our Author has undertaken to reflect on and ridicule,) will appear to all underſtanding People to be founded upon the Principles of <hi>natural Juſtice, common Equity; National Laws,</hi> and <hi>private Stipulations:</hi> And 'tis too plain now, for what ends His Majeſty has been deny'd in ſo juſt Demands, which muſt redound with all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial People, as much to his <hi>Honour</hi> as to their <hi>Shame;</hi> and a <hi>ſucceſsful</hi> piece of <hi>Injuſtice</hi> has <hi>juſt</hi> as much <hi>Equity,</hi> as a <hi>proſperous Villany</hi> has to be entituled to the <hi>ſpecious</hi> Name of <hi>abuſed Virtue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſetting aſide the unanſwerable Argument of the Earl of <hi>O</hi>'s Convention and Agreement in 78, I cannot ſee, but the Contenders againſt it, and theſe aſſerters of this <hi>Natural Liberty,</hi> had long before concluded themſelves by their own Act, in the Articles of two ſeveral Treaties, that of <hi>Surinam,</hi> in 67. and the other ſigned at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in 73. for though by the firſt it was ſtipulated upon the Place, that inſtead of this
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54220:42"/>
                  <hi>agreeable natural Liberty,</hi> all the King's Subjects were to have the <hi>Liberty</hi> to remove themſelves after the transferring of the Place, to ſome other Plantations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der His Majeſty's <hi>Obedience;</hi> which I hope imply'd, that their <hi>Allegiance</hi> was not to be <hi>Tranſlated,</hi> no not with the <hi>Soil</hi> it ſelf; this was thought <hi>then</hi> ſo <hi>agreeable</hi> to <hi>Nature,</hi> that it was admitted immediately as an <hi>Article,</hi> tho' it may be well remembred how thoſe <hi>promiſes too were kept;</hi> the King's Subjects indeed were <hi>kept,</hi> and <hi>detain'd</hi> contrary to that <hi>very Treaty,</hi> and this <hi>Detention</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd unjuſt by themſelves in the 5 Article, in 73, and that it ſhould be lawful at any time for His Majeſty to ſend Ships for his Subjects, and that they have leave to depart with all that belong to them, and that they themſelves were to aſſiſt them in their return; and this was granted by themſelves to <hi>Grobbendonck</hi> at the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">A. D. 1629.</note> of <hi>Bois le Duc,</hi> where they could not detain the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Subjects for theirs; much leſs than the K. of <hi>Englands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to which I ſhall only add, <note n="*" place="margin">Id. <hi>Heath</hi>'s Chro.</note> That alſo in the Year 6¾ they caſhier'd <hi>our Regiments,</hi> &amp; would have had them take a <hi>New Oath</hi> to <hi>their States,</hi> which they all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly diſdain'd, refuſing to <hi>betray</hi> their <hi>natural Lord</hi> by that <hi>treacherous</hi> Expedient of <hi>tranſlating</hi> their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance.</hi> And ſuch an Averſion the <hi>whole Nation</hi> had then againſt this political Project of our Author's <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niatre</hi> which he ſo prides himſelf in, that the <hi>Opinion</hi> of the <hi>whole Parliament</hi> was againſt him; and when the <hi>Dutch</hi> propos'd this <hi>new Oath,</hi> they paſt a Bill of Attainder againſt all ſuch as went over into their Service, and that though the Laws had made it Felony before; theſe, I conſeſs, were <hi>Heroical Attempts</hi> of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> upon the Subjects of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to <hi>tempt</hi> them to <hi>betray</hi> their <hi>Maſter,</hi> (but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54220:43"/>
our Author being experienc'd in that point, wanted no <hi>Temptation)</hi> and if he will have one <hi>Heroical At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> more upon <hi>Honeſty,</hi> we know how his new <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters betray'd</hi> us, who when our Embaſſadors were <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring,</hi> their Town to <hi>treat,</hi> moſt <hi>Heroically enter'd</hi> our Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to <hi>burn</hi> and <hi>deſtroy;</hi> and who (tho' we are ſo <hi>falſly</hi> upbraided with a <hi>French League)</hi> did once really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a <hi>League</hi> with <hi>France</hi> to <hi>betray England, which (as I am well inform'd)</hi> the late King had under their <hi>own</hi> Hands to produce; and now, this <hi>Heroical Invaſion,</hi> without the leaſt <hi>denunciation,</hi> is moſt becoming the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and another <hi>Inſtance</hi> of <hi>their</hi> fair dealing with <hi>Princes,</hi> but <hi>Time</hi> may ſhew, that <hi>England</hi> dare not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>reſent</hi> this, but <hi>revenge</hi> it too.</p>
               <p>Could it poſſibly have been avoided from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of his Papers, I would not have given our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor the Glory (who of his own accord is too much given to affect it) of making <hi>his</hi> Cauſe that of a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> but ſince in this very piece he has labour'd ſo much to make it ſo; and thoſe that are his Defenders, by <hi>Publick Inſtruments, Solemn Replys</hi> and <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> (which our Adverſary here with his Name affix'd, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſiſts and relies on) have thought fit to intereſt themſelves ſo far in his <hi>defence,</hi> His Majeſty's Honour requires as <hi>defenſatory</hi> an <hi>Apology,</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as well as <hi>private Pens,</hi> reduc'd to a neceſſity of maintaining it: Argument I am ſure is an <hi>inoffenſive</hi> Weapon, eſpecially when only us'd by them that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have ſome <hi>reaſon</hi> to be <hi>offended,</hi> and till our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor returns us as much <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Law, Preſident</hi> and <hi>Examples</hi> from <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and <hi>Fact,</hi> to juſtifie his Cauſe, (as I may perhaps with Modeſty ſay) has been here offer'd to overthrow it: The <hi>Memorials</hi> of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> in ſpight of this Author's Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54220:43"/>
will appear to the reaſonable part of the World, and all People unprejudic'd, to be <hi>well grounded,</hi> and notwithſtanding the <hi>Reply</hi> from the <hi>States,</hi> to be <hi>ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwered.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>AND now to come to this <hi>Vindication of himſelf,</hi> of which there has been nothing <hi>like it,</hi> unleſs it be the words in the <hi>Title Page,</hi> he <hi>Charges</hi> me for laying to his <hi>Charge</hi> ſeveral <note n="*" place="margin">P. 6.</note> Papers that I do not prove upon him: I confeſs, I cannot Swear to the Truth of them, neither can it be expected that I ſhould, unleſs I were in the ſame <hi>Confederacy</hi> with our Author, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faming of his <hi>Country</hi> and his <hi>King,</hi> and had been a <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> p. 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Scribler</hi> more <hi>deſpicable</hi> and <hi>mean</hi> than any but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can make me, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> his <hi>Amanuenſis:</hi> But though he will not allow <note n="*" place="margin">P. 2.</note> Similitude of Hands to be Proof enough to <hi>hang</hi> him, I hope Similitude of Styles and of Circumſtances of Affairs may be ſufficient or <hi>good</hi> Evidence only to <hi>gueſs</hi> at an Author, and a <hi>bad Man.</hi> More particular Proof of my <hi>Charges</hi> might I ſuppoſe been as well referr'd to his <hi>legal Tryal,</hi> as he does his Innocency and Defence, his <hi>Juſtifying</hi> and <hi>Clearing</hi> of himſelf; but ſince he is not contented even with that <hi>Charge,</hi> (which he dares not deny) I muſt ſhew the World upon what it was grounded.</p>
               <p>1. The <hi>Papers</hi> then that I arraign'd <hi>for his,</hi> in one of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Parl. Pac.</note> the former Treatiſes, and that <hi>for</hi> the moſt audacious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on the Crown, and almoſt on the Memory of <hi>all</hi> His Majeſty's Royal Predeceſſors, were <hi>thoſe Sir</hi> that as <hi>confidently</hi> carry in their <hi>Front</hi> this Author's
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54220:44"/>
celebrated Name; They are Printed in <hi>Holland,</hi> which from the Letter, and Paper, and manner of Printing, I can prove (being no ſuch Stranger to <hi>Dutch</hi> Books,) and it may be eaſily gueſt from whence we might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Dr. <hi>Burnett</hi>'s. Theſe Papers are all <hi>Pag'd in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> with thoſe Letters of His that were ſent to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State, on purpoſe, I ſuppoſe, to let us ſee they were <hi>all of a piece:</hi> They contain all of them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>peculiar Concerns</hi> of this Author, or elſe (what is as much his <hi>peculiar Province)</hi> the higheſt Defamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Government;</hi> which for farther ſatisfaction I have in this Treatiſe <hi>ſpecify'd</hi> and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Theſe Libels were long before, by a Praelimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Menace <note n="†" place="margin">1 Lett. to my Ld. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Diſpleaſing</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> with a <hi>Recital</hi> of <hi>Affairs,</hi> threatned to be ſent us; and the Dr. was indeed ſo <hi>civil,</hi> before he began his <hi>War</hi> with the Crown, to ſend a <hi>ſolemn Denunciation,</hi> and the <hi>defying</hi> of his <hi>Prince</hi> was an arrogance ſo agreeable to ſuch a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that it ſuperſedes <hi>Proof,</hi> and a Man need not ſeek far to find out the Champion<hi>:</hi> Though I muſt confeſs too, that the fooliſh affectation of his having had ſuch a <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ib.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhare</hi> in <hi>Affairs for this Twenty years,</hi> (did not the Author's Vanity prevail againſt the Truth of the Fact, and a probable Credibility) one might be brought to believe then none of Dr. <hi>Burnett</hi>'s. I do not hear of his having been to <hi>either</hi> Crowns a <hi>Secretary</hi> of State, or a <hi>Privy Counſellor;</hi> and by what has appear'd, he was ever reputed the worſt man in the World, for to be one <hi>a Secretioribus Conſiliis;</hi> ſince, if we can credit his own Relation, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 7.</note> only of my Lord <hi>Lau—d</hi>'s <hi>Affairs,</hi> and the Character he had from an Archbiſhop of <hi>Scotl.</hi> he was not well qualify'd for ſo much as one <hi>a Sacris Domeſticis.</hi> Some things are ſo <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> ut Supra: Notorium probatione non indiget.</note> plainly <hi>probable,</hi> that they ſuperſede
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54220:44"/>
the pains of any <hi>Proof;</hi> and that <hi>Moral Certainty</hi> we have of his having writ theſe <hi>Six Papers,</hi> is as good as <hi>Demonſtration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next <hi>Papers</hi> that I have quoted <hi>as his,</hi> are the <hi>Reflections</hi> on Mr. <hi>Varilla's;</hi> no one that I ever yet met with, did ever miſtruſt them for any <hi>others;</hi> and himſelf has taken all the Care in the World, that they ſhould be known for <hi>his alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>Itinerary Letters</hi> that I have touch'd upon, I hope he does not diſpute, or has not taken ſo much the <hi>Liberty of a Traveller,</hi> as to have occaſion to be <hi>aſham</hi>'d of the <hi>Relations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Enquiry</hi> againſt the Book of the late Biſhop of <hi>Oxon,</hi> has ſo much in it of our Authors malice, and revenge, that it would argue a defect of Reaſon to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt it; the <hi>Cardinals Fiocco</hi> came in (as an Allegory, I ſuppoſe) only to let us know, the Author had been lately at <hi>Rome;</hi> or elſe, it was moſt ridiculouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd to the Biſhops being <hi>Incognito,</hi> when he had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd his <hi>Name,</hi> it is ſome Argument of his being its Author, that Dr. <hi>Burnett</hi> is the firſt Man, and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended in it, though a better Doctor, and who, I think, is more dignify'd, as well as more hardly dealt with; (than from his Learning and Doctrine to be made a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick,</hi> and <hi>unlearn'd)</hi> might have merited a more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple defence: The mighty work that it makes with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts,</hi> and <hi>Originals;</hi> the great relyance this <hi>Paper</hi> has on the <hi>Leige Letter;</hi> let us know too at what Door <note place="margin">Pag. 1. Pag. 7.</note> to lay it, and if the extolling of <hi>himſelf,</hi> and his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Reformation,</hi> ſhall be any Argument againſt his being the Author, it muſt be only with thoſe that are unacquainted with his <hi>Arrogance;</hi> his exceſſive vanity, and <hi>fooliſh</hi> affectation, which I muſt profeſs, is only more ridiculous in a perſon that has ſo many pretences
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54220:45"/>
from his <hi>Reading</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> to be more <hi>wiſe;</hi> theſe <hi>Sublimes,</hi> theſe <hi>Exalted</hi> Flights do not agree with his late <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. pag. 1 6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>humble Imitation;</hi> and the Condeſcention of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his <hi>Perſon mean;</hi> though we <hi>Deſpicable Scriblers,</hi> muſt be even <hi>below</hi> that; ſo that I ſuppoſe, at beſt, this <hi>ſeeming Modeſty</hi> was forct in only to ſerve a turn; and his <hi>opiniatre</hi> is retain'd under the more praepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous affectation of an <hi>humble Pride;</hi> but I muſt in this acknowledge our Authors Civility, that amidſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of <hi>Deſpicableneſs, Mercinarineſs, Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>Scribling,</hi> I am leſs ſcurrilouſly treated, than this Paper of his has the <hi>Prelate,</hi> whoſe Dignity might have defended his <hi>Perſon,</hi> though it had been leſs <hi>Learned,</hi> and <hi>Ingenious: foul Language</hi> is as <hi>little</hi> to be found in our own Writings; and I fancy I have ſhown out of other Peoples, where there is <hi>much:</hi> no <hi>common confidence</hi> could accuſe us for that Undecency, that had ſo much reaſon to reflect upon it <hi>ſelf,</hi> and <hi>bluſh</hi> at the Accuſation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Memoirs</hi> of the late King's Life, I charg'd him with no further, than himſelf had threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the World with the Writing them, and ſo only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipated their Credit and Authority, ſince they were to come to us from ſuch hands; and if he fancies that I faſten an Anſwer to the <hi>New Teſts</hi> upon him, which is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Par. Pacif.</note> none of <hi>his,</hi> I do ſeriouſly confeſs to him, that the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> I there cite, I never conceiv'd to <hi>be ſo,</hi> neither had reaſon ſo to do, ſince there is another to the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that is only more <hi>ſeditious,</hi> and which among the <hi>Six,</hi> himſelf does own.</p>
               <p>Thus, I hope, the <hi>Injurious</hi> Accuſation of doing him ſuch <hi>injuſtice,</hi> is but <hi>ill grounded,</hi> ſince it has been ſo well ſhewn both to <hi>him</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> upon what <hi>ground</hi> I went; neither does himſelf think fit to deny any ſingle Paper I have put upon him for <hi>his;</hi> and for
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:54220:45"/>
his Preface to <hi>Lactantius,</hi> I had no occaſion to take <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 6.</note> of it, ſince what vilify'd the Kings Government, came only under our Conſideration: I confeſs, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Piece <hi>Printed</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and that before our Author was ſo fam'd for <hi>Printing,</hi> and that with <hi>better Notes,</hi> than it has now a <hi>Preface:</hi> the beſt part of which is only <hi>borrow'd</hi> from <hi>Biſhop Taylor,</hi> though ſo much <hi>owned</hi> by Dr. <hi>Burnett;</hi> but ſeeing he takes it ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly we ſhould paſs it by, I cannot but civily give it theſe few rational remarks.</p>
               <p>1. That our Authors <hi>then running down</hi> a Perſecution, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> This <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> to <hi>Lactant.</hi>
                  </note> was rather the Reſult of his revenge againſt ſome of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that kept him from <hi>running up:</hi> It only ſhews how ready he is to write on all Subjects, to ſatisfie his <hi>reſentment,</hi> or <hi>Ambition:</hi> and when he tells us (ſo Myſteriouſly) of what hereafter <hi>may appear to his Enemies amaſement;</hi> I cannot but imagin that he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p.</note> has ſomewhat in <hi>Reſerve,</hi> (which from a Conviction of his <hi>Error)</hi> is a Contradiction to his <hi>Writings,</hi> and all that he has <hi>either ſaid,</hi> or <hi>done:</hi> And I know he could heartily <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with his <hi>Inclination</hi> to <hi>Indulgence,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than have it owing to the <hi>Grant,</hi> and Gracious <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Praef. Pag. 24.</note> of his <hi>Prince;</hi> whom even in that very <hi>Piece</hi> he does endeavour to repreſent from the tys of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, under all the <hi>Indiſpenſable</hi> Obligations to <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and <hi>Perſecution;</hi> and makes the great <hi>Turk</hi> even there too (from the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Faith) to be leſs oblig'd to be a <hi>Tyrant</hi> and a <hi>Perſecutor;</hi> this is certainly, not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to repreſent the Profeſſors of the ſame <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> worſe than ſo many <hi>Muſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and unbecoming that <hi>Charity,</hi> which more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately appertains to <hi>his</hi> Function, and which <hi>himſelf</hi> at the ſame time does ſo much ſeem to <hi>affect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:54220:46"/>
Whatever have been the <hi>Policys</hi> of <hi>States,</hi> and <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt</hi> of deſigning Men, among the Governments that are in the Countrys where the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is profeſt; it is the moſt <hi>uncharitable</hi> Reflexion, (as well as moſt <hi>unreaſonable)</hi> to make it <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 45. Yet note, that even in this <hi>Preface</hi> he grants <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> to have been more <hi>pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Reformation:</hi> and of this mind long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him was <hi>Aerodius,</hi> even in the Caſe of <hi>Hereſy, P. Aerod</hi> rer. judicat. Lib. 1. Tit. 6.</note> the <hi>Delight</hi> of a Church, to <hi>Bath her ſelf in Blood, Common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> and even <hi>Human Nature</hi> cannot admit of ſuch a <hi>Cannibal Accuſation,</hi> and is a Calumny carried a pitch above <hi>Julians;</hi> and if <hi>Papiſts</hi> muſt paſs with us for <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans,</hi> they may with Modeſty be call'd, <hi>Human Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> too, but we muſt pardon in our Author, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them ſo many <hi>Monſters,</hi> ſince from our Saviours <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Lyar, and a Murderer,</hi> he has made them ſo many <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Devils</hi> too: Theſe <hi>Barbarous Reproaches,</hi> I think ſavour ſomewhat of <hi>thoſe Brutal Exceſſes,</hi> with which he has taken the Liberty to upbraid men of no little figure; and if this <hi>Preface</hi> be ſuch an Argument of his <hi>mighty moderation;</hi> I hope I have in <hi>decency,</hi> done him <hi>Juſtice</hi> now, in <hi>taking notice</hi> of <hi>a Diſcourſe</hi> which he has ſo gloriouſly arrogated to be his <hi>own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for thoſe <hi>Reproaches</hi> he ſays I have caſt upon <note place="margin">Vindicat. p. 6.</note> him, and with which I do <hi>purſue</hi> him, <hi>which make it ſo below him to Anſwer ſuch a Scribler:</hi> I have not rely'd upon my own Judgment in this matter for a Reply, but Conſulted even ſome that are no ſuch Enemys to my Adverſary, that can as well applaud his Writings, as do Juſtice to mine, who can find nothing in them of <hi>foul Language,</hi> or <hi>Reproacb;</hi> and I believe I have ſhewn them now where <hi>both</hi> are to be found: If the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting out of his own Papers, the moſt <hi>Reproachful</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on the King and His Government, be <hi>reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the Author, I muſt acknowledge my ſelf very guilty of this Miſdemeanor; and I cannot help it, if I <hi>am become his Enemy</hi> for <hi>telling</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> or diſcovering
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54220:46"/>
his <hi>Falſehood;</hi> but ſome will be apt to think he was moſt of all his own <hi>Foe,</hi> when he ventur'd upon ſuch a piece of Confidence, of reviling the King and His Government with the worſt of Reproaches, that <hi>inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Malice,</hi> mingled with <hi>abuſive Wit,</hi> could dictate and invent; with what <hi>face</hi> will ſuch an Offender find fault, (unleſs with ſuch <hi>an one</hi> as cannot be <hi>cover'd</hi> with <hi>Confuſion)</hi> of whoſe <hi>bitter Words</hi> the <hi>Lords Anointed</hi> did of <hi>old</hi> complain; That under their <hi>Tongues</hi> was <hi>Miſchief</hi> and <hi>Vanity, Tongues ſpeaking proud things, that ſaid their Lips were their own; and who is Lord over us?</hi> The <hi>ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> of <hi>Doeg</hi> was but an <hi>Original</hi> of this Dr's, <hi>devouring Words, all Words that might do hurt, and with Lyes too, cutting like a ſharp Razor;</hi> and if ever that Royal Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt had reaſon to make his Complaint of <hi>Reproaches,</hi> I am ſure His Majeſty may, that is as much <hi>Reproach't:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Exalting</hi> of himſelf to ſuch a <hi>Sublime,</hi> in ſetting others though <hi>unknown,</hi> ſo <hi>below</hi> him; has given me occaſion to <hi>know</hi> more of the <hi>Quality</hi> of this Hero, than perhaps I ſhould otherwiſe have inquired into, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find from the <hi>Scots</hi> Herauldry, that the Name and Family is ſo famous, (though his Father is here repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, as great as any <hi>Patriot</hi> of his <hi>Country)</hi> the <hi>Standard of Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Protector of Property;</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Pag. 6.</note> to all <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> as well as <hi>Rebellion,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever has been this Noble Authors Extract and Diſcent: 'tis certain he does not much Credit to the Duſt of his Anceſtors, to taint their Honour with a Degradation; and inſtead of adding to their Atchievements, to bring them to be torn at the Market-Croſs.</p>
               <p>I confeſs if that would <hi>ennoble</hi> him, I am inform'd he has good luck with the Ladys, and that he was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>married</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. <hi>1ſt.</hi> part, p. 8.</note> (for <hi>I do not ſcorn</hi> (as he ſays) <hi>ſuch a ſimple Expreſſion)</hi> to a Perſon of Quality: but I hope he will not boaſt too much of that Happineſs, leſt it ſhould put
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54220:47"/>
people upon Enquiry, how unhandſomely he came to attain it, <hi>which I am</hi> told too, was by none <hi>of the moſt reputable means;</hi> but neither will this <hi>elevate</hi> him to that <hi>height,</hi> as to make others ſo much <hi>below</hi> him; for by our <hi>own</hi> Laws of Honour, and the old Decrees of the Emperors, Women of <hi>Quality</hi> are reputed no longer ſo, <note place="margin">Dig. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9. 8.</note> when they marry <hi>below</hi> themſelves.</p>
               <p>Our Authors meritorious Services to the <hi>Court,</hi> I cannot diſcover, though he <note n="*" place="margin">Vind. p. 6.</note> magnify's it much; but what will not an unimitable piece of Vanity aſpire to? His Merits were never ſo many to make him much <hi>known</hi> to the Government, unleſs his endeavours may be call'd ſo, to do it a diſſervice, and ſome Creatures are moſt <hi>known</hi> by the Miſchiefs they do, his preferment from his own Confeſſion, was never ſo <hi>high,</hi> and ſome <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ibid.</note> Objects are <hi>below</hi> the <hi>Diſpleaſure of</hi> a <hi>Court.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I cannot but take notice of the moſt inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate piece of Malice, that has yet paſt his <hi>Pen,</hi> tho' before we had Papers that were virulent enough, and as full of Venom and Viper; he tells us, that he is credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly inform'd, (which imports his belief of the Matter of Fact) <hi>that many have been interrogated with Tortures</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>to Accuſe him:</hi> Had he not deſign'd it as the ſevereſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination on the Crown, he might have expreſt to us the Place <hi>where,</hi> whither <hi>Scotland</hi> was the Scene of this ſeverity, and not left it to the Judgment of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking men to conclude it, a Court contrivance <hi>here;</hi> he knows our Laws admit of no ſuch Cruelty; neither (as <hi>I am</hi> too <hi>credibly</hi> inform'd) was it <hi>practis'd</hi> with relation to him <hi>there;</hi> their Laws and Cuſtoms, I confeſs, admit it in extraordinary Caſes, as well as <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi> Countrys, where the <hi>Rack</hi> is many times as rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly extended as his <hi>Boot</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> but then I am ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it is upon the ſame grounds, which by Conſulting
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54220:47"/>
of Forreigners upon this judicial ſeverity I found in theſe ſummary Proceſſes, they proceeded on, and that it is exercis'd <hi>only</hi> where they find the Evidence ſo ſtrong, and the Proof ſo preſumptive, that nothing but the Priſoners Obſtinacy can oppoſe it, and that they are never <hi>tortur'd</hi> but in Capital Caſes, where their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is only wanting to confirm their <hi>Guilt;</hi> where the Proof is ſo plain, that they could be executed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; and upon which one of our Jurys might find them <hi>Guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Charge of <hi>Betraying</hi> his <hi>Maſter,</hi> being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of an heavy one, the <hi>guilt</hi> againſt the Rules of common Gratitude and Morality, <hi>a petty Treaſon,</hi> one would have thought this Author in a <hi>Vindication</hi> of <hi>all</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> p. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>that relates to himſelf,</hi> would have made his Innocency very plain; but this defence is indeed like all the reſt; <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vin. p. 7.</note> he excuſes his not being able to <hi>betray</hi> a <hi>Maſter,</hi> becauſe he never <hi>had one</hi> that could <hi>properly</hi> be call'd ſo; and <hi>that he was</hi> ever rais'd by the <hi>King,</hi> above the <hi>ſerving</hi> any <hi>Subject:</hi> I never heard of this <hi>high</hi> preferment that did <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 7.</note> ſo incapacitate him, unleſs it were that at the <hi>Rolls;</hi> and in that, I am ſure, he <hi>ſerv'd</hi> a <hi>Subject,</hi> and <hi>had</hi> a <hi>Maſter</hi> in more Senſes than <hi>one:</hi> This is ſuch a <hi>Quible,</hi> and <hi>Equivocation,</hi> that <hi>Cambridge</hi> (whoſe true Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Ingenuity, in the common Reflection is ſo much, and ſo injuriouſly abus'd) can never be ſuppos'd to have furniſht him with ſuch an Inſipid Jeſt; and that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident and Learned Body, that perhaps out of a proſpect of his ill Principles, did once (as ſome ſay) refuſe him to Preach, will as little approve of ſuch a ſubterfuge in his defence: It is ſtrange that this Author that uſes to be ſo full <hi>of his</hi> ſlights, ſhould here ſo <hi>poorly ſtick at words:</hi> The Reflection I made, was grounded upon the known, and now his own confeſt Story, of <hi>betraying</hi> the late <note place="margin">Vid. ib.</note>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:54220:48"/>
D. of <hi>L.</hi> a Story that he <hi>Conſciouſly</hi> owns I am not the only Author of; but it ſeems, his <hi>Maſter was not thus betray'd,</hi> becauſe (ſays he) this Noble Lord was <hi>never ſuch</hi> his <hi>Maſter;</hi> I cannot, I confeſs, imagine what this manner of excuſe can mean; unleſs he thinks from the Propriety, and common Acceptation of the <hi>Term,</hi> I repreſented him as <hi>an Apprentice to the Duke;</hi> for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the Defence is very lame; it imported only in general, with all impartial people, that he had <hi>betray'd</hi> a <hi>Patron,</hi> a <hi>worthy Friend,</hi> or a <hi>Perſon of Honour</hi> that had made him his Confident, for the firſt I am credibly inform'd, that he was <hi>patronis'd,</hi> as a Chaplain <hi>there,</hi> that he has been ſeen to officiate as ſuch at that <hi>Table</hi> which he <hi>made a Snare;</hi> but had this been but in the Caſe of a <hi>Common</hi> Friend, or Confident, I humbly conceive, the <hi>Treachery</hi> had been the ſame, the <hi>Jealouſie</hi> that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd that <hi>great Ministers anger,</hi> it ſeems, was well grounded; and the Doctor tells us no more than this, <hi>That the Duke alway thought he would betray him;</hi> if this <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ib.</note> can be call'd a <hi>Vindication</hi> of <hi>himſelf,</hi> the <hi>Reproaches</hi> he accuſes me of, may paſs for his <hi>Encomiums?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for another Argument <hi>e Confeſſo,</hi> what can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <note place="margin">Vid. Ibid.</note> more fully his falſhood to be a propenſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful malice? and (which he would make a neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Diſcovery) then his diſcloſing of his <hi>own</hi> accord, the Propoſal of a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Peer, about Invading <hi>England,</hi> who was liable to the Laws of <hi>it,</hi> and that to a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of its Parliament, and who, perhaps, he knew too to be no <hi>friend</hi> to this <hi>great Miniſter</hi> whom his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected Principles had made ſo much his <hi>Enemy,</hi> Can our Author reconcile this to common ſenſe? That the telling a <hi>perſon of Honour,</hi> and a Member of the <hi>Houſe</hi> ſuch a Tale, was not <hi>betraying</hi> it, or not the ſame, as if he had publiſht it on <hi>the Houſe top: Oats</hi> and <hi>Tongue told</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:54220:48"/>
their Tale of a Plot to a <hi>perſon of Honour,</hi> and <hi>Member of the Houſe, upon which it was ſo ſet about</hi> that it was known to a <hi>great many others,</hi> upon <hi>which they were ſent</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Pag. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>for to the Houſe;</hi> and will our Author ſay <hi>theſe Men</hi> were unwillingly brought to own a deteſtable piece of <hi>Forgery?</hi> and which I am <hi>credibly</hi> inform'd <hi>his</hi> was too, for that late Loyal Peer is ſaid to have juſtify'd himſelf ſo far, that all that he offer'd at was only, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty might be able to make more uſe of his Subjects of <hi>Scotland</hi> by his being inabled to call for their Service in <hi>England,</hi> to ſerve him <hi>out</hi> of their own Realm, as well as <hi>within,</hi> which was conſonant, and agreeable, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reaſon, but to ſome expreſs <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Acts Parl. of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> Acts of Parliament, both of <hi>that</hi> Kingdom, and our <hi>own;</hi> and which, 'tis more than probable, this Doctor too, from the reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> 11. H. 7.</note> that he had of his <hi>Sufferings under that great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters anger,</hi> did improve alſo into a <hi>Plot</hi> of an <hi>Army,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ib.</note> a <hi>Scottiſh Invaſion,</hi> of <hi>Spoiling,</hi> and <hi>Subduing</hi> the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is pretty to obſerve how this Excellency of our Author does indeed conſiſt in <hi>Writing,</hi> that is, in <hi>Black,</hi> and <hi>White,</hi> when with a touch of his Pen, any Actions ſhall appear in what <hi>colour</hi> he pleaſes; he tells us of a <hi>Perfect Reconciliation</hi> that enſu'd between this great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and himſelf, but ſays, That <hi>upon ſome reaſons of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ib.</note> 
                  <hi>his own, their meeting was defer'd,</hi> or, <hi>not thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient;</hi> and I am much of this Authors mind, that upon ſome <hi>reaſons</hi> the Duke had, he <hi>did</hi> not <hi>think convenient</hi> to <hi>meet him;</hi> it was a good Argument of his Lordſhips <hi>Cunning</hi> and <hi>Policy,</hi> and as little proof of this <hi>perfect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> pag 7. Coll. 2.</note> that Celebrated Stateſman was never ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected yet for want of <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> and it is a known Maxim, That a Man may <hi>betray</hi> me <hi>once</hi> by <hi>his</hi> being a <hi>Knave,</hi> but the <hi>ſecond</hi> opportunity makes me a <hi>Fool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:54220:49"/>
And the Atteſtation this Author appeals to, of that <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> Noble Peers <hi>Nephew,</hi> is all of a piece with the reſt of his <hi>Vindication,</hi> (that is) <hi>nothing</hi> of truth in it, or <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> to the <hi>purpoſe;</hi> I have taken pains to enquire into this matter; have conſulted my Lord <hi>M.</hi> that Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Ingenious Perſon he ſo injuriouſly reflects on, and find nothing of that Paragraph to be <hi>true,</hi> but his Lordſhips being <hi>now of the</hi> Roman <hi>Communion,</hi> and that was as invidiouſly forc'd in by our Author, for a Reflection upon his being <hi>reconcil'd,</hi> but the greater a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it muſt needs be, to faſten a <hi>falſe</hi> thing upon a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Honour,</hi> who ought to be handled with more regard to modeſty and <hi>truth,</hi> than if our Author was treating only with Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> or reflecting upon his <hi>Scriblers:</hi> He <hi>Cites</hi> this Honourable Perſon, as a <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> but if he has none that could do him more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, ſhould he appear to his <hi>Citation,</hi> I am afraid it would go hard with him at his <hi>Tryal:</hi> He <hi>appeals freely</hi> to <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> his Lordſhip for <hi>bringing very kind Meſſages to him from my Lord Duke; and ſignifying them to him after his death.</hi> I confeſs, our Author ever gives himſelf a <hi>freedom</hi> with <hi>great</hi> Perſons, which is but a part of his <hi>peculiar</hi> Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to <hi>Aggrandiſe</hi> himſelf; but I muſt <hi>freely</hi> tell him too, this is found to be <hi>falſe;</hi> 'tis ſtrange, that it muſt be the misfortune of ſo <note n="*" place="margin">Lord <hi>L.</hi> Lord <hi>R.</hi> Lord <hi>M.</hi>
                  </note> many <hi>Lords</hi> to ſuffer by ſuch a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Correſpondent; this Noble Perſon <hi>remembers</hi> none of theſe <hi>very kind Meſſages</hi> he <hi>brought</hi> him, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that the Duke ever <hi>ſent;</hi> and that his Lordſhip might be more fully ſatisfy'd, not relying wholly upon his own <hi>Memory,</hi> it being almoſt ſix years ſince, as an Argument of his greater <hi>integrity</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as <hi>freely appeal'd</hi> to a perſon from whoſe <hi>Function,</hi> as well as <hi>favour,</hi> our Author can expect nothing but <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> and that is a <hi>Divine,</hi> and his own <hi>Favourite,</hi> who
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54220:49"/>
firſt introduc'd my Lord to his <hi>unhappy</hi> Acquaintance; whoſe Return is, That he <hi>aſſures his Lordſhip there was not a word ſpoken by his Lordſhip in his hearing,</hi> (who was preſent at the two ſeveral Meetings they had) <hi>of any Meſſage from the Duke of</hi> Lauderdale <hi>to the Doctor.</hi> The <hi>Original</hi> Anſwer I have by me, as <hi>alſo,</hi> the <hi>Copy of</hi> the <hi>Letter,</hi> his Lordſhip ſent.</p>
               <p>So that I muſt conclude too, <hi>I cannot leave this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking notice of our Authors ſincerity;</hi> and aſſure him <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. on Parliam. Pacificum 1 part. pag. 3.</note> when ever he makes a better <hi>Vindication</hi> of his <hi>own,</hi> I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ll pardon him the groundleſs <hi>Reflexion</hi> he has put upon <hi>mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He tells me, in the next place, I pity Mr. <hi>Varilla's</hi> defeated condition, and ſo indeed I do Dr. <hi>Burnett</hi>'s too, who wants nothing to his being baffl'd, but the modeſty to acknowledge it, he is as <hi>unlucky</hi> here in his <hi>Appeals,</hi> as I have made him appear in ſome of his Reflexions, ſince the Learned Author at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other at <hi>Paris,</hi> to both of which he has <hi>appeal'd,</hi> have both Vindicated <note place="margin">Schelſtradt &amp; Le Grand.</note> themſelves in particular Treatiſes againſt this bold <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant;</hi> and our Author can make no further defence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he intends to decide it by <hi>Combat;</hi> and I am much aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, his <hi>Appealing</hi> to his Friends there, about Monſieur <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Var. not pretending to juſtifie himſelf, and receiving an Order from the King, to inſiſt no more on the Diſpute,</hi> is as <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately</hi> falſe, and which we have taken care to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into; whatever are Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> his faults, of which he cannot be excus'd; there muſt be much of Allowance made him for being a <hi>Forreigner,</hi> where the Exactitude of Names, as well as times, may fail him; our Author might be at no little loſs, were he to Write their <hi>French History;</hi> though an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> of <hi>France</hi> has lately Corrected <hi>that</hi> of <hi>his Reformation;</hi> and (as
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54220:50"/>
ſome think) with good reaſon too; but I muſt ſtill retain this opinion, that a Native muſt alway have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opportunity, and be better qualify'd for the giving an Account of his own Country, from the eaſie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that he can have to <hi>Records,</hi> and <hi>Originals,</hi> and from the more natural Apprehenſions, and Conceptions he muſt have of the State of Affairs, and the temper of his Nation, than any Alien, though ſo long Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that Forreign Country of which he would Write an Hiſtory, that he might be ſaid to be <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliz'd;</hi> and this may make (perhaps) even <hi>Polidore Virgil,</hi> whom <hi>many Appeal</hi> to, and our Author once too much, to be leſs <hi>Authentick</hi> in our Affairs than he is commonly taken for, and whoſe <hi>Authority</hi> (if I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake not) is ſomewhat ſuſpected, if not Condemn'd, by a Celebrated <hi>Writer,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Savill;</hi> and here I <note place="margin">Vid.</note> cannot but take notice, that our Author in as Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Piece of his, puts in this <hi>Polidore Virgil,</hi> as an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. upon his Cont. Hiſtory of Hereſie. <hi>Vid.</hi> Errat.</note> of <hi>equal Credit</hi> with Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> perhaps, gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by inſtinct; but all the while means (as himſelf aſſures us afterward) honeſt <hi>Harpsfield:</hi> This ſounds at firſt ſight, as bad as <hi>Haveit</hi> for Sir <hi>Thomas Wiat;</hi> this was ſure no fault of the Preſs, neither could Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> forgive him for all his <hi>Errata,</hi> ſhould his Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be anſwered (as one would think by the <hi>beginning,</hi> he did the Book of the Biſhops) <hi>(i. e.)</hi> before he read to the <hi>End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Adverſarys fits of Arrogance often return upon him, and if the Tumors of his Body, were but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate to thoſe of his Soul, he muſt needs die in a Dropſie; to be <hi>pufft</hi> in <hi>Mind,</hi> and to have <hi>proud Looks,</hi> was the Deteſtation of King <hi>David</hi> himſelf, and then but ill ſuits a Divine, that is ſo oft bound to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54220:50"/>
read his Pſalter; our Author would have me <hi>ſucceed</hi> to that <hi>Deſpicable Writer,</hi> (as he calls Mr. <hi>Varillas;)</hi> but <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> if his Obſervations upon that Gentleman be true, he has made himſelf the Succeſſor to all his Fooliſhneſs, and Affectation, in ſetting ſuch a Value upon the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of his own <hi>Sublimes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Contradiction I <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. id.</note> fix'd upon his Writings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Temper, and Diſpoſition of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> will ſtand, in ſpite of his Diſtinctions, and Endeavors to <hi>evade</hi> it. It has been the conſtant practiſe of theſe prejudic'd, and inveterate Hiſtorians, to make her very Nature <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>bloody,</hi> and from an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrelenting Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> and ſome <hi>unmerciful Inclinations</hi> perhaps more Impartial Authors cannot clear her; and 'tis plain, that his Encomiums upon that <note n="*" place="margin">Reflect. on 3 Tome of Mr. <hi>Var.</hi> p. 150</note> inſtance of her Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, was clearly the Reſult of his <hi>Brutal</hi> Rage, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proceedings of the chief Miniſter of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Juſtice; and that very Devil (whom for a touch on the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Praeface to <hi>Lactantius.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Papiſts)</hi> he repreſents for a <hi>Lyar,</hi> and a <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer,</hi> ſhould have <hi>been</hi> made the God of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> rather than have wanted an <hi>elevated reproach,</hi> and a Scurrilous Aggravation, againſt that Honourable Perſon, whom in every Paper he ſo ſcandalouſly ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſes; this was only to <hi>ſhew how</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect. on <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation.</note> 
                  <hi>Rebels</hi> were <hi>hang'd up by Hundreds,</hi> by him whom his more <hi>exalted</hi> confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, has ſince call'd the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Apology.</note> 
                  <hi>common Hangman:</hi> That lew'd Character, and <hi>fouleſt Language,</hi> was only a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated Libel on the late King's Memory, his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his Miniſter of State together, the falſeſt Aſperſion, and entire Fiction; the Character being in all its <hi>parts</hi> ſo diſagreeable, is of it ſelf a ſufficient Proof, that it was none of the late <hi>Kings,</hi> whom this Author, upon another occaſion to abuſe his Memory,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54220:51"/>
has <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</note> extoll'd for an Excellency in that way; but he that (though an unworthy Preacher of the <hi>Rolls)</hi> would have been a Maſter of the <hi>Temple,</hi> may be angry if diſappointed, for the ſake of a better Man; Theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes could never have been made <hi>Brutal,</hi> but by one that can as <hi>brutiſhly</hi> repreſent them; and this <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Divinity,</hi> to gratifie its paſſion, does only diveſt it ſelf of <hi>Humanity,</hi> and tranſlates it ſelf too into one of thoſe <hi>beaſts</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> it fights againſt <hi>Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> againſt <hi>Paul</hi> too, as well as <hi>Peter;</hi> this Satyriſt himſelf muſt pardon <hi>this</hi> paſſage, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects upon that Majeſty, and the Miniſters of his State, he has in ſuch a ſcandalous manner, Libell'd, and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd.</p>
               <p>I made it appear in that Treatiſe, that his Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction was truly ſuch, according to the very definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. ibid.</hi> Vind. p. 7.</note> of the Schools, with a <hi>dicitur de eodem,</hi> for if Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> was to be made Cruel in <hi>Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> that Rebellion was really upon <hi>that very</hi> Score, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Match but a meer pretence, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I've proved upon him, that for his <hi>God,</hi> he can <hi>ly.</hi> And though ſome diſguſted <hi>Papiſts</hi> might joyn with him, his Followers were (to a very few) all <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and his Reflexions upon that place, at beſt, but a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Forgery:</hi> for this Match is confeſt by <note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>R. Baker's</hi> Chron. p. 318.</note> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, to have been of the two, moſt advantageous to Qu. <hi>Mary,</hi> that they reſolv'd once not to ſtir till K. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> came; that ſo their taking up Arms might have the better Colour; and the Queen complain'd to the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners,</hi> that though he pretended only the croſſing of of the Match; yet his Audacious Deſigns, were to ſeize upon her Perſon, to have the Cuſtody of her,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54220:51"/>
and the Command of her Counſellours, and 'tis ſtrange, ſince her Cruelty was ſuch in Matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſhe ſhould be ſo merciful to thoſe that really Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell'd for it.</p>
               <p>Thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments,</hi> which in all other things <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Fox</hi> 1419. <hi>Vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>B</hi>'s Praeface to Reformation.</note> muſt be ſo believ'd, and of which himſelf has ſo good opinion, as to give them his Panegerick; how comes it to paſs, that they muſt here have no Authority at all; <hi>Thoſe</hi> tell us, <hi>That it was for Religion too, they Conſpir'd among themſelves, and made a Rebellion, of which this</hi> Wiat <hi>was one of the chief Beginners, who ſaid, that upon this Match, (and as he ſaid, many elſe perceived) the Queen and Counſel would Eſtabliſh the</hi> Popiſh <hi>Religion;</hi> and in that <hi>Monumental</hi> Speech, he Records of the Queen, are theſe expreſs words, <hi>That their Pretence, as they ſaid was at firſt againſt the determined Marriage, but that ſince ſhe had ſent certain of her Privy Council unto them, to demand the cauſe of their Rebellion, and it appeared unto the ſaid Council, that the Matter of the Marriage ſeem'd to be but a</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Cloak, to cover their pretended purpoſe againſt our Religion:</hi> I cannot ſee, but this with all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> muſt paſs for truth, if they believe the Martyrologiſt, and that <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. on <hi>Var.</hi> Cont. p. 150.</note> before the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Account that may be put upon us in a Paper of his Sons, and the falſe Reflexions of a prejudic'd and diſingenuous Author: But mark the agreement of theſe Writers, Dr. <hi>Burnett,</hi> only where it makes for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, tells us of a very <hi>ſmall number</hi> that were made Examples upon this Inſurrection, but Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> ſays, though there was but about an hundred kill'd, yet of thoſe that were taken, a <hi>great many</hi> were hang'd and Executed; they were hung up by <hi>Fiftys,</hi> though not by <hi>Hundreds,</hi> if we believe the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>How</hi>'s Cont. of <hi>Stow</hi>'s Ann. pag. 622.</note> Hiſtory of Mr. <hi>How,</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:54220:52"/>
and even this <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Abridg. of Reform. l. 3.</note> Author himſelf confeſſes ſo much: it cannot be deny'd, ſays Dr. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Refor. Ann. Reg. Mar</note> 
                  <hi>Heylin, But that the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Reform'd Religion, was the matter principally aimed at in the Rebellion, though nothing but the Match with</hi> Spain, <hi>appeared on the outſide;</hi> the hope they had of the Earl of <hi>Devonſhire</hi>'s Marrying the Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and reſtoring Reformation, animated the <hi>Western</hi> part, as well as <hi>Wiat</hi> did the <hi>South,</hi> and ſo ſatisfy'd were <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> that pure Religion was the Cauſe, that <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> writes a Panegyrick upon this very Sir <hi>Thomas's</hi> Exploit, to this purpoſe: <hi>Wiat that did his Duty for the Maintenance of the Goſpel: Wiat with whom all ought to have riſen that profeſs the Goſpel: O Noble Wiat, that art now with God, and thoſe Worthy Men, that died in that happy Enterprize:</hi> Laſtly, This very Authors words are to this purpoſe, upon the place, <hi>All that lov'd the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>B</hi>'s Reform. Part 2. Lib. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Reformation, were againſt the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Match;</hi> and tells us, that <hi>Wiat</hi> in his Proclamation at <hi>Maidſtone,</hi> (where note, that is the <hi>only one</hi> we hear of his in Hiſtory) tho' he pretended nothing but the Liberty of the Nation, yet privately aſſur'd all the Reform'd, he would declare for them; and ſince there is ſuch a Concurrent Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of all ſort of Writers, of different Complexions, and even his own, is it not the moſt ſhameful piece of Impudence? to offer to obtrude ſuch a Forgery upon the World, for which he can have no other foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than this Account, which he <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid</hi> Reflect. on the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of Mr. <hi>Var.</hi>
                  </note> Prints of his <hi>Sons,</hi> contrary to the ſenſe of all Hiſtorians? Is it not more than probable, that this <hi>Relation</hi> was feign'd to excuſe the <hi>Father?</hi> And are not all Familles concern'd, as much as they can, to keep up their Reputation? If he has made no better Inferences from his conſulting the reſt of the <hi>Records</hi> that concern the Reformation, than
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54220:52"/>
he pretends to draw from this <hi>Original,</hi> he has done it the greateſt diſſervice in the World, by his Imprudent Partiality, and Inconſiderate Concluſions.</p>
               <p>But to confirm further the falſhood of this <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> upon which our Author ſo imprudently relies, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>B</hi>'s Hiſtor. of Reformation, which has not a word of it.</note> I do not find from ſeveral of our Annals and Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, that this ſame Sir <hi>Thomas Wiatt</hi> (as his <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Reflect. on Mr. <hi>Varil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi>'s 3d. Tom. 140.</note> Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſay) was ever ſent Ambaſſador to <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth's Court; I have traced it from <hi>Hen.</hi> 
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">I find in <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8th's Reign, Sir <hi>Henry Knevet</hi> and <hi>Gardiner</hi> to be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors to that Court, in 1541. and 1545. and Sir <hi>phil. Hoby</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident there in <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Reign, 1548/9:</note> the 8th's Reign down to Queen <hi>Mary's;</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> makes no mention of it in his Hiſtory; neither does our Author, as himſelf confeſſes, Record it. in his own; but this new <hi>Diſcovery</hi> is brought in now for a <hi>Supplement,</hi> as he ſays, to <hi>ſupply</hi> the <hi>Defects</hi> of it. If this be his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity ſo much applauded, I am afraid even Monſ. <hi>Le Grand</hi> muſt have a great advantage againſt him. But what is ſomewhat remarkable, upon my enquiring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this matter, I find one Sir <hi>Thomas Wiat,</hi> about the 33 <note n="*" place="margin">1641.</note> of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bak.</hi> Chron. p. 300. 8 Edit. <hi>Lond.</hi>
                  </note> ſent Ambaſſadour to the <hi>ſame</hi> Emperour, but who died of the Plague while he was going thither; but whether this might not make the Miſtake, or that one of his Sons, or of the ſame Family and Name, ſucceeded in the ſame Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I ſubmit to the conjectures of thoſe that will, I hope, make better <hi>Concluſions</hi> than our Author; I am ſure it is but a <hi>bad</hi> one that he makes from the <hi>ſame</hi> buſineſs, that is, becauſe no mention was made of B. <hi>Poynet's,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Abridg. l. 3.</note> being in the Rebellion, by his Name not being among the many that were attainted for it; <hi>he not in it,</hi> when it is very probable he was left out only for his Deſerting them before they came
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54220:53"/>
to <hi>London,</hi> ſince thoſe Writers that accuſe him of being an Accomplice, acknowledge too, that he Counſell'd them to ſhift for themſelves, took his leave of them, and went into <hi>Germany;</hi> and 'tis a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral practiſe upon all ſuch Revolutions to Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert chiefly upon thoſe that are ſeiz'd, and have been the moſt obſtinate, and perſiſted to the laſt in ſuch <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious</hi> Undertakings: And I do not ſee why Dr. <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>'s Authority in this Point; when he imparts alſo to <note place="margin">An. 1. Reg. M.</note> us, the <hi>Particulars,</hi> ſhould not be of as much force as Dr. <hi>B's,</hi> when he gives us but a general Aſſertion from his one Suppoſition and Conjecture: And I cannot but take notice, how in the Account of this Affair, our Author would excuſe thoſe Rebels, and calls it but a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Hiſt. Ref.</note> ſort of an <hi>Attempt</hi> upon <hi>Wincheſter</hi> Houſe, when both Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> agree, that they <hi>ſack'd</hi> it, and <hi>defac'd</hi> all the Biſhops Library. That Author, in ſpite of his unjuſt Character, in his Proud, and Cenſorious <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Praef. to his 1 Vol.</note> Praeface, has ſaid too much againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected for one, or hired for it; and who has not ſhewn ſo <hi>little</hi> bitterneſs againſt their Doctrines, and Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as to be thought <hi>only</hi> to write on one ſide, and to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour them ſo <hi>much;</hi> he ſhew'd himſelf ſo far a fair Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, as plainly to lay open the ſaults of both Parties, and repreſents the Sacrilegious Proceedings of King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Reign, with as much abhorrence, as the Perſecution of Queen <hi>Mary's,</hi> and the Deſcription of that, I am ſure, he has not in the leaſt favour'd; 'tis confeſs'd, he had not recourſe to thoſe many Records, that, perhaps, ſince; have not been ſo well explain'd, or truly Copy'd; neither did he deſign his Work ſo Volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous; but his Sincerity ſeems ſomewhat beyond theirs that have ſo <hi>confidently</hi> traduc'd it<hi>:</hi> and from what has been here ſaid, may be obſerved too, That
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:54220:53"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His <hi>Apology.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>there are ſome degrees of ſhame, over which when people have paſt, they cannot be put out of Countenance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I hope I ſhall clear my ſelf from his <hi>laſt</hi> Accuſations, having ſo ſucceſsfully been able, (even from his own malice and miſtakes, to defend my ſelf againſt all the <hi>reſt)</hi> He ſays, That in <hi>State Matters</hi> I <hi>have not blemiſh'd</hi> him much; but he muſt mean <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p.7.</note> it for the ſame reaſon, that he has not <hi>blemiſh'd</hi> any <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>State, (i.e.)</hi> by his <hi>own</hi> being ſo full of blots and <hi>blemiſhes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Ib. Vind. p. 7.</note> Accuſes me for venturing upon a <hi>point of Divinity,</hi> which (as he ſays) is <hi>above me,</hi> ſince I were only <hi>entertain'd</hi> to <hi>Scrible</hi> upon the <hi>Politicks: Scribler</hi> and <hi>Scribling</hi> are the beſt Terms that alwaies our Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant piece of <hi>Opinatre</hi> beſtows upon Perſons that write with more ſincerity, though not with the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Fame that this piece of Arrogance affects; but ſo many times does a <hi>Mountebank</hi> attract the <hi>Mobile</hi> with his pompous Name, and his having appear'd ſo much upon the Stage: I cannot ſee upon what this prodigious Vanity ſhould ſo ineſtimably value himſelf, unleſs it be for that Function which in <hi>any other</hi> I ſhall alwaies reſpect, and which himſelf has in <hi>All</hi> endeavour'd to defame. <hi>Luther</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for his undecent Reply to our <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. and that by thoſe Proteſtants for whom he was the firſt Champion at the Pen: And ſure the Church of <hi>England</hi> muſt be aſham'd then of ſuch a Defender, that villifies his <hi>King</hi> with <hi>Reproaches</hi> that would be a <hi>Scandal</hi> to a <hi>Dutch Scavenger:</hi> Had the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt the Dr. been ſo ſevere, a ſubmiſſive Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcence would have better become his <hi>Coat</hi> and Character; and where he ſays he had ſo many <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:54220:54"/>
procur'd him more <hi>Friends;</hi> People are apt to pity thoſe that take Hardſhips patiently, when their uneaſineſs may make them ſeem to merit it<hi>:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as his Vindications only diveſt him of the Habit he wears, the <hi>Caſſock</hi> of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Divine, cannot Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal ſo much Sedition, a <hi>Cloak</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> will become it <hi>better,</hi> and <hi>cover</hi> it <hi>more.</hi> But though he makes <hi>Politicks</hi> my ſole <hi>Province,</hi> and <hi>Divinity</hi> ſo <hi>much above me,</hi> it may appear I underſtand as much of it as this comes to, though I don't make it my <hi>Trade;</hi> and it might be wiſh'd this Dogmatiſt out of the Pulpit, did not put upon us for Doctrine ſo much of his <hi>Politicks</hi> too; but it ſeems with ſuch vain men as our Author, all <hi>Human</hi> Learning, as well as <hi>Divine,</hi> muſt be look'd for like the <hi>Keys</hi> (for which we condemn another Church) to <hi>be hung at his Girdle;</hi> I cannot ſee, but I might venture as bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon his <hi>School-Divinity,</hi> as our Author upon the <hi>Court-Politicks:</hi> And for my being <hi>entertain'd</hi> for that purpoſe, is but another Inſtance of Dr. <hi>Burnett's</hi> Faithfulneſs in his giving of Characters, which is ſtill at a venture; thoſe that are better acquainted with me, know beſt what has been my <hi>Entertainment,</hi> and I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie even Malice to make out my being Mercenary; but we ſee now for what he was <hi>entertain'd</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> Whatever Reflections may be paſt upon our Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, they have been alwaies really the Reſult of defending the Crown againſt all Antimonarchical Principles, and ſuch ſeditious <hi>Reflections,</hi> by one who ſhall never be brought to make any Mollifying Diſtinctions or <hi>Modalitys,</hi> for the ſake of any Perſons or Perſwaſions, that behave themſelves diſreſpectfully to their King, and ſhall ever condemn thoſe that have
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54220:54"/>
                  <hi>done</hi> it, as much as what our celebrated Author has been ſo long a <hi>doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have ſeen ſo much of Government <hi>abroad,</hi> as to learn, that there is no Country that takes ſo much Licentious Liberty with their Prince, as our own at <hi>home,</hi> and whatever ſide was <hi>faulty,</hi> did think it my Duty, without being <hi>entertain'd,</hi> to tell them of their <hi>faults:</hi> Could our Author prove <hi>me</hi> (what he calls <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,</hi> an <hi>Hired</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Apology, p.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Buffoon,</hi> whom againſt his <hi>Apology</hi> I leave to <hi>defend</hi> himſelf (if he can from being <hi>hir'd)</hi> being a more celebrated Pen, and one that was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies willing, that the Government by none other ſhould be <hi>defended;</hi> for <hi>Penſion</hi> and <hi>Pay</hi> will make the moſt Loyal Services a <hi>Trade,</hi> and ſo we muſt give ſome people leave to put in for a <hi>Monopoly.)</hi> Our Author might have then perhaps more handſomely paſt upon us the Reflection; but ſince from the <hi>Firſt</hi> moſt <hi>famous</hi> Attempt againſt the <hi>King's Succeſſion,</hi> to his <hi>own</hi> late Libels upon the <hi>King,</hi> I have with the ſame <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>ſincerity</hi> vindicated his cauſe againſt Authors as <hi>celebrated</hi> as himſelf, and that without the <hi>leaſt</hi> ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, but what Duty and Loyalty could afford, which indeed, like the <hi>beſt</hi> of <hi>Virtue,</hi> is the beſt <hi>Reward</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelf: This <hi>Reflection</hi> will come from him now with no good Grace, eſpecially if he reflects upon ſome Application himſelf made to the late King that he Libels; and upon the * Account he gives us of the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his <hi>own</hi> Works, which, if I miſtake not, was <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Pref. to Refor. 1 vol.</note> not compaſt without a <hi>Collection</hi> too, and his kind Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors not only Courted out of their <hi>Manuſcripts,</hi> but their <hi>Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſince our Author would make me ſo Ignorant in this Notion of <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> I ſhall let him know,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54220:55"/>
I a <hi>little underſtand</hi> it, and that he <hi>much</hi> miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood me; The Doctrine of <hi>Arrius</hi> is delivered down to us as a <hi>Disbelief of the Divinity of our Saviour;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 7.</note> that which gave the <hi>firſt</hi> occaſion for it, was indeed what has caus'd the many Perplexities about Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Matters <hi>ſince,</hi> and that is the Sophiſtry of ſuch Polemical Divines, that make but a piece of Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks of their Faith and Religion, and muſt needs give Expoſitions and Solutions upon what without examining they are bound even from the very Bible to believe: The Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> upon a ſolemn Aſſembly of his Clergy, falls upon a ſpeculative Diſcourſe of this Mighty Myſtery, and manages it ſo confus'dly, that <hi>Arrius</hi> fancied he was introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing an <hi>Hereſie</hi> before him, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Sabellians,</hi> and while he was concern'd againſt the Uniting of the Perſons, divides their Natures, and to defend the Trinity, deſtroys the Unity. This I take to be <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianiſm;</hi> This the occaſion of it; This the Source <note place="margin">Neicene, <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſ.</hi> &amp;c.</note> of our being perplext with ſo many explanatory Creeds, which I could never comprehend ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, though thought ſit to be made ſo Canonical.</p>
               <p>Now the nice Diſquiſition about theſe matters, I thought, might be better omitted, &amp; even the ſearching into Manuſcripts about it, at leaſt the troubling the World with the Account; Since ſuch unhappy Curioſity in theſe Scholaſtick Speculations occaſion'd the very <hi>Hereſie</hi> againſt which we contend, and ſince it is an Opinion that has no footing in all our Weſtern Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whether Catholick or Proteſtant, not ſo much as in a ſingle Heretick: It can be no Service to the Chriſtian Religion in general, to retrieve thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes that among unwary men and illiterate might
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54220:55"/>
create Doubts and Diſturbances. Much leſs can it be defended, the giving the World to underſtand, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> His Letter from <hi>Zurich.</hi>
                  </note> that the plaineſt Text that we have in our Bibles againſt it, is not to be found in their Original Manuſcripts; for ſince thoſe <hi>Sacred</hi> Books are by the indulgent Charity of the Reformation, and the reaſonableneſs of all Peoples reading what they are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, permitted to the meaneſt Capacities, the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt words will beſt Satisfie ſuch, who cannot ſo well ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it from ſome dubious Expreſſions, which though clear to ſuch a Doctor, to them may ſeem <hi>dark,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when that <hi>light</hi> they rely'd on, is ſo <hi>officiouſly</hi> put out. <hi>This</hi> was the <hi>true ground</hi> of the Reflection, and <hi>This</hi> what he <hi>grounds</hi> upon an Accuſation as <hi>falſe;</hi> for any one that views the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Parlia. Pacif.</note> Paſſage, will find I accus'd him only for <hi>dealing</hi> thus <hi>boldly</hi> about the Trinity; and it plainly appears, that it had been better for the Church, if ſuch buſie men had never been ſo <hi>bold:</hi> I charg'd his Perſon with no Opinion, but only this Unhappy Conſequence of his Fatal and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Induſtry. So that when he ſays I repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him as an <hi>Enemy to the Divinity of Chriſt,</hi> tho' he would <hi>not</hi> be thought to <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Vind. p. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>lye</hi> for <hi>God;</hi> yet for <hi>Man,</hi> for <hi>himſelf,</hi> what is worſe, for an <hi>ill man</hi> he <hi>doth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
